<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academics on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/categories/academics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Academics on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT License</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/categories/academics/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Chris Walker at Faculty Senate</title>
      <link>/2016/04/15/chris-walker-at-faculty-senate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/04/15/chris-walker-at-faculty-senate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dance.wisc.edu/dance/people/faculty/chris-walker&#34;&gt;Chris Walker&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.wisc.edu/media/Professor+Chris+Walker/1_5k9npnxs&#34;&gt;powerful speech&lt;/a&gt; at the Faculty Senate on 4 Apr 2016 (see &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2016/04/04/hateful-shit-at-uw-madison/&#34;&gt;Hateful shit at UW-Madison&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;) was &lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.wisc.edu/media/Professor+Chris+Walker/1_5k9npnxs&#34;&gt;recorded&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.wisc.edu/media/Professor+Chris+Walker/1_5k9npnxs&#34;&gt;You &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; listen to it!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Action items in response to hateful shit</title>
      <link>/2016/04/05/action-items-in-response-to-hateful-shit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/04/05/action-items-in-response-to-hateful-shit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;UW-Madison faculty got an email update from Vice Provost and Chief Diversity Officer Patrick Sims regarding the things we can do in response to the hate and bias incidents on campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the things he had mentioned yesterday at the Faculty Senate meeting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Address hate/bias incidents in your curriculum to ameliorate unacceptable occurrences in our campus community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Look at &amp;ldquo;bullying&amp;rdquo; language as a way to address possible hate/bias incidents in the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commit to engaging in ongoing cultural competency training. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.library.wisc.edu/lcice/&#34;&gt;Learning Communities for Institutional Change &amp;amp; Excellence (LCICE)&lt;/a&gt; as an infrastructure already provides these services campus-wide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commit to experiencing the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.library.wisc.edu/lcice/&#34;&gt;leadership institute&lt;/a&gt; and become a facilitator, carving out 10-15% of your time towards these efforts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Support the request for additional staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://campusclimate.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;the Campus Climate website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An attached letter from the Hate &amp;amp; Bias incident team added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your school/college/department can host a bystander intervention workshop on hate and bias. This workshop will provide tools for UW-Madison community members on when and how to intervene. If you would like to host a workshop, please contact &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:Joshua.johnson@wisc.edu&#34;&gt;Joshua Moon Johnson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many incidents go unreported for a variety of reasons. We encourage students and campus community members to &lt;a href=&#34;www.students.wisc.edu/reporthate&#34;&gt;report incidents of hate and bias&lt;/a&gt; to ensure that campus can best support the victim and work to prevent future incidents. We encourage you to post &lt;a href=&#34;www.students.wisc.edu/reporthate&#34;&gt;the link to report&lt;/a&gt; on your school/college/department websites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oftentimes students do not report incidents because they are unaware of the reporting process. To increase awareness of the reporting process, we encourage you to share brochures and posters with information on how and why it is important to report. These will be distributed across campus in the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Students who are victims of hate and bias incidents may need immediate support. Please be sure to refer/provide students with appropriate resources such as mental health/counseling services through University Health Services (UHS). The &lt;a href=&#34;http://msc.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;Multicultural Student Center&lt;/a&gt; also has drop-in hours with UHS counselors as well as support and discussions groups for students of color.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many students who are victims of hate and bias incidents identify with an underrepresented racial group, gender identity or sexual orientation, or religious group. We encourage you to specifically reach out to marginalized student groups to raise awareness of the bystander intervention workshop and reporting process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a reasonably positive response to &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2016/04/04/hateful-shit-at-uw-madison/&#34;&gt;my email to my faculty colleagues&lt;/a&gt; suggesting that we all commit to cultural competency training. But the training from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.library.wisc.edu/lcice/&#34;&gt;LCICE&lt;/a&gt; mentioned above looks to be semester-long, Tuesdays 4:30-7:30pm. I think I&amp;rsquo;ll have a difficult time convincing my colleagues of that. We need something in between nothing and 45 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hateful shit at UW-Madison</title>
      <link>/2016/04/04/hateful-shit-at-uw-madison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/04/04/hateful-shit-at-uw-madison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a privileged white male university professor. As privileged as they come, really. My father was a professor of chemistry; my mother also has an advanced degree in chemistry. The jobs I&amp;rsquo;ve held have been more about personal fulfillment than money: dancer, dance teacher, secretary for intellectual property lawyers, research and teaching assistant, professor. People assume I know what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about, even if I&amp;rsquo;m in shorts and a t-shirt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that&amp;rsquo;s just to say that, when it comes to the ongoing hateful acts that have been happening at the University of Wisconsin-Madison, I&amp;rsquo;m really the last one that you should be listening to. You should instead listen to UW students, such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unitedcouncilofuw.org/&#34;&gt;United Council of UW Students&lt;/a&gt;, who have submitted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unitedcouncilofuw.org/the-student-voice/2016/2/24/blackout-uw-system-administration-press-release-1212016&#34;&gt;a list of 5 reasonable demands&lt;/a&gt;, or Vice Provost and Chief Diversity Officer &lt;a href=&#34;http://provost.wisc.edu/climate.htm&#34;&gt;Patrick Sims&lt;/a&gt;, who made an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zMBQUzwnCL0&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&#34;&gt;important 8-min video&lt;/a&gt; in response to a recent hateful incident that you should now go away and watch (really, stop reading what I have to say and spend 8 minutes watching that video), or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dance.wisc.edu/dance/people/faculty/chris-walker&#34;&gt;Chris Walker&lt;/a&gt;, Asst Prof in the dance department, who spoke movingly today at the UW-Madison Faculty Senate meeting about the shit that faculty and students of color have to put up with on campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lot&amp;rsquo;s of crap has been happening in Wisconsin lately. My focus has been on what Scott Walker and company have been doing to the state and to the University of Wisconsin, most recently by making huge cuts to state support to the UW System and by weakening tenure and shared governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all been an embarrassment, and depressing, but in comparison to the hateful racist shit that&amp;rsquo;s been happening on campus, and Vice Provost Sims reported that there have been &amp;gt;30 &lt;em&gt;reported&lt;/em&gt; hate or bias incidents on campus this year, tenure and funding just don&amp;rsquo;t seem that important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Walker&amp;rsquo;s speech at the Faculty Senate today really hammered this home. As a black man on campus, he&amp;rsquo;s experienced a lot of shit: worse shit then we&amp;rsquo;re seeing in the papers. And if we don&amp;rsquo;t fix this, our students can&amp;rsquo;t be successful. We &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; fix this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can a biostatistics professor do? I&amp;rsquo;m open to suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for now, I&amp;rsquo;ll follow Patrick Sims&amp;rsquo;s suggestion and start with one of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unitedcouncilofuw.org/the-student-voice/2016/2/24/blackout-uw-system-administration-press-release-1212016&#34;&gt;United Council of UW Students&amp;rsquo; demands&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;We demand that the University of Wisconsin System creates and enforces comprehensive racial awareness and inclusion curriculum and trainings throughout all 26 UW Institution departments, mandatory for all students, faculty, staff, campus &amp; system administration, and regents. This curriculum and training must be vetted, maintained, and overseen by a board comprised of students, staff, and faculty of color.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve written an email to the faculty in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;my department&lt;/a&gt;, asking that we, as a department, &lt;em&gt;volunteer&lt;/em&gt; to participate in such racial awareness training:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2016/04/email_to_dept1.png&#34; alt=&#34;email_to_dept&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Correction&lt;/strong&gt;: There&amp;rsquo;s an error in my email; Chris Walker is Associate Professor, and has been for a couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: Chris Walker&amp;rsquo;s speech at the 4 Apr 2016 Faculty Senate meeting was &lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.wisc.edu/media/Professor+Chris+Walker/1_5k9npnxs&#34;&gt;recorded&lt;/a&gt;! Must listen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducibility is hard</title>
      <link>/2015/09/09/reproducibility-is-hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/09/09/reproducibility-is-hard/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Reproducibility is hard. It will probably always be hard, because it&amp;rsquo;s hard keeping things organized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently had a &lt;a href=&#34;http://g3journal.org/content/early/2015/08/21/g3.115.019778.abstract&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; accepted at &lt;a href=&#34;http://g3journal.org/&#34;&gt;G3&lt;/a&gt;, concerning a huge set of sample mix-ups in a large eQTL study. I&amp;rsquo;d discovered and worked out the issue back in December, 2010. I gave a talk about it at the Mouse Genetics meeting in Washington, DC, in June, 2011. But for reasons that I will leave unexplained, I didn&amp;rsquo;t write it up until much later. I did the bulk of the writing in October, 2012, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until February, 2014, that I posted a &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1402.2633&#34;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;, which I then finally submitted to G3 in June this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In writing up the paper in late 2012, I re-did my entire analysis from scratch, to make the whole thing more cleanly reproducible. So with the paper now in press, I&amp;rsquo;ve placed all of that in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/Paper_SampleMixups&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;, but as it turned out, there was still a lot more to do. (You can tell, from the repository, that this is an old project, because there are a couple of Perl scripts in there. It&amp;rsquo;s been a long time since I&amp;rsquo;ve switched from Perl to Python and Ruby. I still can&amp;rsquo;t commit to just one of Python or Ruby&amp;hellip;want to stick with Python, as everyone else is using it, but much prefer Ruby.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic issue is that the raw data is about 1 GB. The clean version of the data is another 1 GB. And then there are results of various intermediate calculations, some are rather slow to calculate, which take up another 100 MB. I can&amp;rsquo;t reasonably put all of that within the GitHub repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the raw and clean data have been &lt;a href=&#34;http://phenome.jax.org/db/q?rtn=projects/projdet&amp;amp;reqprojid=532&#34;&gt;posted in the Mouse Phenome Database&lt;/a&gt;. (Thanks to Petr Simecek, Gary Churchill, Molly Bogue, and Elissa Chesler for that!) But the data are in a form that I thought suitable for others, and not quite in the form that I actually used them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I needed to write a script that would grab the data files from &lt;a href=&#34;http://phenome.jax.org&#34;&gt;MPD&lt;/a&gt; and reorganize them in the way that I&amp;rsquo;d been using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In working on that, I discovered some mistakes in the data posted to MPD: there were a couple of bugs in my code to convert the data from the format I was using into the format I was going to post. (So it was good to spend the time on the script that did the reverse!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the raw and clean data on MPD, I posted a zip file with the 110 MB of intermediate results on &lt;a href=&#34;http://figshare.com/account/projects/4842&#34;&gt;figshare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I&amp;rsquo;m hoping that one can clone the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/Paper_SampleMixups&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt; and just run &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/software/make/&#34;&gt;make&lt;/a&gt; and it will download the data and do all of the stuff. If you want to save some time, you could download the &lt;a href=&#34;http://figshare.com/account/projects/4842&#34;&gt;zip file from figshare&lt;/a&gt; and unzip that, and then run make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not quite there, but I think I&amp;rsquo;m close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;aspects-i-m-happy-with&#34;&gt;Aspects I&amp;rsquo;m happy with&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, my work on this project wasn&amp;rsquo;t terrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wrote an R package, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/lineup&#34;&gt;R/lineup&lt;/a&gt;, with the main analysis methods.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;That I re-derived the full entire analysis cleanly, in a separate, reproducible document (I used &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.methods.co.nz/asciidoc/&#34;&gt;AsciiDoc&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://yihui.name/knitr/&#34;&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt;) was a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The code for the figures and tables are all reasonably clean, and draw from either the original data files or from intermediate calculations produced by the AsciiDoc document.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I automated everything with GNU Make.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-should-i-have-done-differently&#34;&gt;What should I have done differently?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a lot more after-the-fact work that I would rather not have to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a project reproducible is easier if the data aren&amp;rsquo;t that large and so can be bundled into the GitHub repository with all of the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a larger data set, I guess the thing to do is recognize, from the start, that the data are going to be sitting elsewhere. So then, I think one should &lt;em&gt;organize the data in the form that you expect to be made public&lt;/em&gt;, and work from those files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you write a script to convert data from one form to another, &lt;em&gt;also write some tests&lt;/em&gt;, to make sure that it worked correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then &lt;em&gt;document, document, document!&lt;/em&gt; As with software development, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to document data or analyses after the fact.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2015 AAAS in San Jose</title>
      <link>/2015/02/13/2015-aaas-in-san-jose/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/02/13/2015-aaas-in-san-jose/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://aaas.confex.com/aaas/2015/webprogram/start.html&#34;&gt;2015 AAAS meeting&lt;/a&gt; in San Jose, California. This is definitely not my typical meeting: too big, too broad, and I hardly know anyone here. But here&amp;rsquo;s a quick (ha ha; &lt;em&gt;yah sure&lt;/em&gt;) summary of the meeting so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;opening-night&#34;&gt;Opening night&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerald_Fink&#34;&gt;Gerald Fink&lt;/a&gt; gave the President&amp;rsquo;s Address last night. He&amp;rsquo;s the AAAS President, so I guess that&amp;rsquo;s appropriate. But after five minutes of really lame simplistic crap (for example, he said something like, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/c_fenster/status/566061155026624513&#34;&gt;A single picture can destroy our known understanding of the universe,&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; like innovation and improving our understanding is a bad thing), I left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and before that: the emcee of the evening, who introduced &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janet_Napolitano&#34;&gt;Janet Napolitano&lt;/a&gt;, totally couldn&amp;rsquo;t pronounce her last name. (Her remarks, particularly her comments in support of public universities, were quite powerful.) Old dude: practice such things! Your ineptness reveals that you haven&amp;rsquo;t paid proper attention to her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sightings&#34;&gt;Sightings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge meeting, but I know next to no one here. But I ran into &lt;a href=&#34;http://faculty.mdanderson.org/Sanjay_Shete/&#34;&gt;Sanjay Shete&lt;/a&gt; in the exhibit hall, where I attempted to get two of every tchotchke. (My kids will pitch a fit if one gets something, no matter how lame the thing, and the other doesn&amp;rsquo;t.) Sanjay was named AAAS Fellow, that&amp;rsquo;s why he&amp;rsquo;s here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also ran into &lt;a href=&#34;https://med.stanford.edu/profiles/steven-goodman&#34;&gt;Steve Goodman&lt;/a&gt; (not the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Goodman&#34;&gt;folk singer&lt;/a&gt; who died too young, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lamplighters.org/images/press/pir14/DSCF4590.jpg&#34;&gt;a singer&lt;/a&gt;, nevertheless). Gotta love Steve Goodman! He produced &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ba5eNi0KzHk&#34;&gt;Behind the tan door&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;highlights&#34;&gt;Highlights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to a dozen talks. A half-dozen I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; liked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://aspuru.chem.harvard.edu/&#34;&gt;Alan Aspuru-Guzik&lt;/a&gt; talked about how to find (and visualize) useful organic molecules among the 1060 (or 10180?) possible. Cool high-throughput computing and interactive graphics to produce better solar panels (particularly for developing countries) and huge batteries to store wind- and solar-based power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://people.stanford.edu/rbaltman/&#34;&gt;Russ Altman&lt;/a&gt; talked about how to search databases, web-search histories, and social media, to identify pairs of drugs that, together, give bad (or good) side effects that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be predicted from their on-their-own side effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Altshuler&#34;&gt;David Altshuler&lt;/a&gt; had a &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/566328355570475008&#34;&gt;hilarious outline slide for his talk&lt;/a&gt;, but the rest was really awesome. A key point: to develop precision medicine will require hard work and there&amp;rsquo;s no magic bullet. And basic (not just translational) research is critical: we can&amp;rsquo;t make a medicine that gets to the precise cause (and that&amp;rsquo;s what precision medicine is about) if we don&amp;rsquo;t understand that basic biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations/AAAS&#34;&gt;a talk myself&lt;/a&gt;, in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://aaas.confex.com/aaas/2015/webprogram/Session9760.html&#34;&gt;session on visualization of biomedical data&lt;/a&gt;, but it was definitely &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the best talk in the session, nor the second best. Mine might have been the worst of the five talks in the session. But that&amp;rsquo;s okay; I think I did fine. It&amp;rsquo;s just that &lt;a href=&#34;http://physics.cancer.gov/opso/hanlon.aspx&#34;&gt;Sean Hanlon&lt;/a&gt; (brother of my UW-Madison colleague, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.wisc.edu/~hanlon/&#34;&gt;Bret Hanlon&lt;/a&gt;) put together a superb, but thinly-attended, session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.utah.edu/~miriah/&#34;&gt;Miriah Meyer&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s was my favorite talk of the day. She develops visualization tools to help scientists make sense of their data. And her approach is much like mine: specific solutions to specific data and questions. She talked about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.utah.edu/~miriah/multeesum/&#34;&gt;MulteeSum&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.utah.edu/~miriah/pathline/Overview.html&#34;&gt;PathLine&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.utah.edu/~miriah/mizbee/Overview.html&#34;&gt;MizBee&lt;/a&gt;. Favorite quote: &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s amazing how much people like circles these days.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www-pls.llnl.gov/?url=about_pls-scientific_staff-streitz_f&#34;&gt;Frederick Streitz&lt;/a&gt; from Lawrence Livermore National Lab talked about simulating and visualizing the electrophysiology of the human heart at super-high  resolution using a frigging huge cluster, with 1.5 million cores. I loved his analogies: if you are painting your house, having a friend or two over to help will reduce the time by the expected factor, but having 1000 friends or 100k friends to help? In parallel computing, you need to rethink what you&amp;rsquo;ll use the computers for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His second analogy: The DOE cluster at Livermore is 100k times a desktop computer. That&amp;rsquo;s like the difference between &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pac-Man&#34;&gt;PacMan&lt;/a&gt; (1980, 2.1 megaFLOPS) to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Assassin%27s_Creed&#34;&gt;Assassin&amp;rsquo;s Creed&lt;/a&gt; (2011, 260 GigaFLOPS). And their cluster is 100k times &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daphne_Koller&#34;&gt;Daphne Koller&lt;/a&gt; talked about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coursera.org&#34;&gt;Coursera&lt;/a&gt;. She&amp;rsquo;s awesome; Coursera&amp;rsquo;s awesome; I&amp;rsquo;m a crappy teacher. That&amp;rsquo;s my thinking at the moment, anyway. (&lt;a href=&#34;http://meetings.aaas.org/live-video-stream/?utm_source=redirect&amp;amp;utm_medium=visual-link&amp;amp;utm_campaign=opp_am15stream#x&#34;&gt;A video of her talk is online&lt;/a&gt;. Have I mentioned how much I hate it when people screw up the aspect ratio? It seems like they screwed up the aspect ratio.) University faculty exist to help people, and with Coursera and other MOOCs, we can help &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of people. Key lessons: the value of peer grading (for &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt;), not being constrained by the classroom or the 60-min format, ability to explore possible teaching innovations, and just having a &lt;em&gt;hugely&lt;/em&gt; broad reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;d heard the quote that Daphne mentioned, &lt;a href=&#34;http://quoteinvestigator.com/2012/08/17/lecture-minds/&#34;&gt;attributed to&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edwin_Emery_Slosson&#34;&gt;Edwin Emery Slosson&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;College is a place where a professor&#39;s lecture notes go straight to the students&#39; lecture notes, without passing through the brains of either.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still laughing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/566423868265353216&#34;&gt;mentioned on twitter&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve eaten &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of tacos. But I also had &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/566263267048161281&#34;&gt;some donuts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;boy-am-i-old&#34;&gt;Boy, am I &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I seem to be staying at the same hotel as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Junior_Academy_of_Sciences&#34;&gt;American Junior Academy of Sciences (AJAS)&lt;/a&gt;. Are these high school or college students? Man, do I feel old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My contribution to education, today: if all of the elevators going down are too packed to accept passengers, press the &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; button and ride it up and then down. (Later I learned, from one of the AJAS youth, that the &amp;ldquo;alarm will sound&amp;rdquo; sign at the bottom of the stairs is a lie. You &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; take the stairs.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initial steps towards reproducible research</title>
      <link>/2014/12/04/initial-steps-towards-reproducible-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/12/04/initial-steps-towards-reproducible-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In anticipation of next week&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Reproducible-Science-Curriculum/Reproducible-Science-Hackathon-Dec-08-2014&#34;&gt;Reproducible Science Hackathon&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nescent.org/&#34;&gt;NESCent&lt;/a&gt;, I was thinking about &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/cbahlai&#34;&gt;Christie Bahlai&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s post on &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://practicaldatamanagement.wordpress.com/2014/10/23/baby-steps-for-the-open-curious/&#34;&gt;Baby steps for the open-curious&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving from Ye Olde Standard Computational Science Practice to a fully reproducible workflow seems a monumental task, but partially reproducible is better than not-at-all reproducible, and it&amp;rsquo;d be good to give people some advice on how to get started - to encourage them to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I spent some time today writing another of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/pages/tutorials&#34;&gt;minimal tutorials&lt;/a&gt;, on &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/steps2rr&#34;&gt;initial steps towards reproducible research&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a bit rough, and it could &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; use some examples, but it helped me to get my thoughts together for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Reproducible-Science-Curriculum/Reproducible-Science-Hackathon-Dec-08-2014&#34;&gt;Hackathon&lt;/a&gt; and hopefully will be useful to people (and something to build upon).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The value of thesis intro/discussion</title>
      <link>/2014/12/03/the-value-of-thesis-introdiscussion/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/12/03/the-value-of-thesis-introdiscussion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/FuSchmu&#34;&gt;Kelly Weinersmith&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/FuSchmu/status/536909452457172992&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Is any task a more monumental waste of time than writing an introduction and discussion for a dissertation where the chapters are published?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think many (or most?) of my colleagues would agree with her. The research and the papers are the important things, and theses are hardly read. Why spend time writing chapters that won&amp;rsquo;t be read?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/536961364166979584&#34;&gt;My response&lt;/a&gt; was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Intro &amp; disc of thesis get the student to think about the broader context of their work.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to expand on that just a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, a PhD dissertation was more of a monograph. The new style is to have three or so papers (published or ready-to-submit) as chapters, sandwiched between introductory and discussion chapters. Those intro and discussion chapters are sometimes quite thin. I would prefer them to be more substantial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus on papers is a good thing, as they will be easier to find and more widely read. But a thesis/dissertation is not just a research product, but also a vehicle to get a student to think more deeply and broadly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The individual papers will include introductory and discussion sections, but journal articles tend to be aimed towards a relatively narrow and specialized audience. More substantive introductory and discussion chapters can help to make the work accessible to a broader audience. They also help to tie the separate papers together: what is the larger scientific context, and how do these pieces of work fit into that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want students wasting time on &amp;ldquo;busy work,&amp;rdquo; and writing a thesis &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; seem like busy work. But I think a thesis deserves more than a ten-paragraph introduction. And the value of that introduction is not so much in demonstrating the student&amp;rsquo;s knowledge, but in being part of the development of that knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scholarly Publishing Symposium at UW-Madison</title>
      <link>/2014/10/30/scholarly-publishing-symposium-at-uw-madison/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/10/30/scholarly-publishing-symposium-at-uw-madison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;a href=&#34;http://go.wisc.edu/publishing-symposium&#34;&gt;Scholarly Publishing Symposium&lt;/a&gt; at UW-Madison today. Has interesting list of supplemental materials, but apparently only on paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/img_3422.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Supplemental materials from UW-Madison Scholarly Publishing Symposium&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here they are electronically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://go.wisc.edu/l7k7vt&#34;&gt;Know your Copy Rights, Association of Research Libraries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://go.wisc.edu/181xyi&#34;&gt;Optimize Your Publishing, The Right to Research Coalition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://go.wisc.edu/904z4t&#34;&gt;Right to Research, The Right to Research Coalition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://go.wisc.edu/39ef9o&#34;&gt;About SPARC (Scholarly Publishing and Academic Research Coalition)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://go.wisc.edu/74guz3&#34;&gt;Open Data Factsheet, SPARC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://go.wisc.edu/9980c2&#34;&gt;Open Education Factsheet, SPARC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://go.wisc.edu/iqg0jj&#34;&gt;Open Access to Scholarly and Scientific Research Articles, SPARC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://go.wisc.edu/fl0kop&#34;&gt;SPARC Author Addendum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The mustache photo</title>
      <link>/2014/08/28/the-mustache-photo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/08/28/the-mustache-photo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A certain photo of me has been following me around for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/pictures/moustache.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Karl with a mustache, 15 Nov 2002&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/pictures/moustache.jpg&#34;&gt;sitting on my website&lt;/a&gt;, so I suppose I have only myself to blame. I actually quite like the photo. I look happy. I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; happy. I&amp;rsquo;m not always happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s shown up in a lot of talks, particularly by &lt;a href=&#34;http://rafalab.dfci.harvard.edu/&#34;&gt;a certain friend of mine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/StrictlyStat/status/495240349225607169&#34;&gt;appeared on the seminar board&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Hopkins Biostat&lt;/a&gt; earlier this month. Perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/simplystats/status/505066800842047488&#34;&gt;still there&lt;/a&gt;. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/simplystats/status/505066800842047488&#34;&gt;My own innocent comments&lt;/a&gt; prompt some of this.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://hilaryparker.com&#34;&gt;Hilary Parker&lt;/a&gt; confirmed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[trufax -- this photo would make its way into department events all. the. time.](https://twitter.com/hspter/status/505091094804455424)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[like if there was no pizza for computing club, &#34;no pizza&#34; would link to this photo](https://twitter.com/hspter/status/505091356822609922)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems time to tell the story behind the photo. This will probably be longer than it should be. But I&amp;rsquo;ve included photos of cats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;movember&#34;&gt;Movember&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think November, 2002, was the first time that a group of young &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Hopkins Biostat&lt;/a&gt; faculty participated in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://us.movember.com/&#34;&gt;Movember Campaign&lt;/a&gt;, in which guys shave and then grow a mustache (or moustache) for a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For various reasons, I didn&amp;rsquo;t actually participate. Among the least important: I had a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Dyke_beard&#34;&gt;Van Dyke&lt;/a&gt; at the time. It probably took me a couple of months to grow the thing, so damned if I was going to shave it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/pictures/van_dyke.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Karl with a Van Dyke beard (playing with Francis), 10 Nov 2002&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(There was a big controversy during the competition. &lt;a href=&#34;http://rafalab.dfci.harvard.edu/&#34;&gt;Rafa&lt;/a&gt; was growing an impressive handlebar mustache, but it was revealed that on weekends or when traveling, he&amp;rsquo;d grow out the bit on his chin, so that it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a proper mustache anymore. I believe he was disqualified.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-beard-trimming-incident&#34;&gt;A beard-trimming incident&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I thought the whole &lt;a href=&#34;http://us.movember.com/&#34;&gt;Movember&lt;/a&gt; thing went from Nov 1 to Nov 30. But this photo was taken 15 Nov 2002, and I recall that it was the last day of this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Hopkins Biostat&lt;/a&gt; competition. Actually, if you look at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://us.movember.com/about/history#2003&#34;&gt;history of Movember&lt;/a&gt;, it seems that &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; started in 2003, so the Hopkins guys were ahead of their time. (And surely it was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bcaffo.com/&#34;&gt;Brian&lt;/a&gt; who was responsible for this? As I recall, he was trying to introduce some Florida traditions, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mud_bogging&#34;&gt;mud bogging&lt;/a&gt; was viewed to be infeasible.) So maybe we went from Oct 15 to Nov 15?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it was the morning of 15 Nov 2002, and I had a bit of an accident with my beard trimmer – I forgot to use the guard or some such. And so I shaved off a big patch of the beard part. Well, it was the last day of the mustache competition, so I figured what the heck, I&amp;rsquo;ll shave it all off, except for the mustache. I think I was made an honorary participant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;jhsph-happy-hour&#34;&gt;JHSPH Happy Hour&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/departments/biochemistry-and-molecular-biology/&#34;&gt;Biochemistry&lt;/a&gt; graduate students organize a Happy Hour every Friday at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Biostat Faculty&lt;/a&gt; were enthusiastic participants. (As you may recall, Happy Hour was featured in the whole JHSPH logo saga; see parts &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/16/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-1/&#34;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/21/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-2/&#34;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/06/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-3-karls-revenge/&#34;&gt;three&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/pictures/moustache&#34;&gt;The photo&lt;/a&gt; was taken at Happy Hour. So that&amp;rsquo;s why I was happy. (There exists a dual photo of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~jmcgread/&#34;&gt;John McGready&lt;/a&gt;, who was a true participant in the competition. But, as I recall, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to detect the presence of a mustache in the photo of John, so it&amp;rsquo;s not gotten the same play.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;wilmer-dinner&#34;&gt;Wilmer dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may ask, &amp;ldquo;But why were you wearing a proper shirt and a sport coat? This was long after that incident with the Dean, where you were subsequently required to wear a proper shirt on a daily basis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, my wife worked at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/wilmer/&#34;&gt;Wilmer Eye Institute&lt;/a&gt;, and we were going straight from Happy Hour to dinner with a group of her colleagues. I think it was in honor of some important visitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why bring this up? Well, at the dinner, I was sitting next to &lt;a href=&#34;https://webapps.jhu.edu/namedprofessorships/professorshipdetail.cfm?professorshipID=145&#34;&gt;Oliver Shein&lt;/a&gt;, and for reasons that I suspect you can infer quite well yourself, I was unusually exuberant, and I was telling him about the mustache competition. He asked me, &amp;ldquo;Is there a prize for the winner?&amp;rdquo; And I responded, &amp;ldquo;A really bad mustache!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was then that I realized the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/profiles/results/directory/profile/0002003/oliver-schein&#34;&gt;Oliver Shein is a mustache guy&lt;/a&gt;. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-mustache-didn-t-last-long&#34;&gt;The mustache didn&amp;rsquo;t last long&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like people think I was a mustache guy myself, from that photo. But it actually lasted just the one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/pictures/karl_and_fisher.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Karl clean-shaven (with Fisher), 17 Nov 2002&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-s-really-shocking-about-the-photo&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s really shocking about the photo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure why my Hopkins friends are so fascinated by the photo. Possible explanations include&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the mustache&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;that I look happy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;that I&amp;rsquo;m wearing a shirt with a collar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;that I&amp;rsquo;m wearing &lt;em&gt;a sport jacket&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m just glad to have people thinking of me, even if I&amp;rsquo;m not entire sure what they&amp;rsquo;re thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reform academic statistics</title>
      <link>/2014/05/01/reform-academic-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/05/01/reform-academic-statistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wehi.edu.au/faculty_members/professor_terry_speed&#34;&gt;Terry Speed&lt;/a&gt; recently gave a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chalmers.se/en/areas-of-advance/ict/calendar/Pages/Terry-Speed.aspx&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; on the role of statisticians in &amp;ldquo;Big Data&amp;rdquo; initiatives (see the &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/91502942&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; or just look at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chalmers.se/en/areas-of-advance/ict/events/Documents/Terry%20Speed_Data%20Science,%20Big%20Data%20and%20Statistics%20-%20Can%20We%20All%20Live%20Together.pdf&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;). He points to the history of statisticians&amp;rsquo; discussions of massive data sets (e.g., the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=5505&#34;&gt;Proceedings of a 1998 NRC workshop on Massive data sets&lt;/a&gt;) and how this history is being ignored in the current Big Data hype, and that statisticians, generally, are being ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was thinking of writing a polemic on the need for reform of academic statistics and biostatistics, but in reading back over &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.org&#34;&gt;Simply Statistics&lt;/a&gt; posts, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that &lt;a href=&#34;http://rafalab.dfci.harvard.edu/&#34;&gt;Rafael Irizarry&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;jtleek.com&#34;&gt;Jeff Leek&lt;/a&gt; have already said what I wanted to say, and so I think I&amp;rsquo;ll just summarize their points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rss.org.uk/&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofstatistics.org/presentations-and-panelists&#34;&gt;Future of the Statistical Sciences Workshop&lt;/a&gt;, Rafael was &lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/11/18/feeling-optimistic-after-the-future-of-the-statistical-sciences-workshop&#34;&gt;quite optimistic&lt;/a&gt; about the prospects for academic statistics, as he noted considerable consensus on the following points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We need to engage in real present-day problems&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Computing should be a big part of our PhD curriculum&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We need to deliver solutions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We need to improve our communication skills&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff said, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://simplystatistics.org/2013/04/15/data-science-only-poses-a-threat-to-biostatistics-if-we-dont-adapt/&#34;&gt;Data science only poses a threat to (bio)statistics if we don&amp;rsquo;t adapt,&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; and made the following series of proposals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remove some theoretical requirements and add computing requirements to statistics curricula.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Focus on statistical writing, presentation, and communication as a main part of the curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Focus on positive interactions with collaborators (being a scientist) rather than immediately going to the referee attitude.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add a unit on translating scientific problems to statistical problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add a unit on data munging and getting data from databases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Integrating real and live data analyses into our curricula.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make all our students create an R package (a data product) before they graduate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most important of all have a &amp;ldquo;big tent&amp;rdquo; attitude about what constitutes statistics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree strongly with what they&amp;rsquo;ve written. To make it happen, we ultimately need to reform our &lt;em&gt;values&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, we (as a field) appear satisfied with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Papers that report new methods with no usable software&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Applications that focus on toy problems&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Talks that skip the details of the scientific context of a problem&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data visualizations that are both ugly and ineffective&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, we tend to get more excited about the &lt;em&gt;fanciness&lt;/em&gt; of a method than its &lt;em&gt;usefulness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; value&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Usefulness above fanciness&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tool building (e.g., usable software)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data visualization&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In-depth knowledge of the scientific context of a problem&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In evaluating (bio)statistics faculty, we should consider not just the number of &lt;em&gt;JASA&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Biometrics&lt;/em&gt; papers they&amp;rsquo;ve published, but also whether they&amp;rsquo;ve made themselves useful, and to the scientific community and well as to other statisticians.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple web sites with GitHub Pages</title>
      <link>/2014/04/05/simple-web-sites-with-github-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/05/simple-web-sites-with-github-pages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you love &lt;a href=&#34;http://git-scm.com&#34;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, you&amp;rsquo;ll also love &lt;a href=&#34;http://pages.github.com&#34;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;, for producing websites using &lt;a href=&#34;https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&#34;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://git-scm.com&#34;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;: you write pages in Markdown within a &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch in a git repository; when you push to GitHub, a corresponding site is automatically constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night, I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.github.io/simple_site&#34;&gt;minimal tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on how I&amp;rsquo;ve been using this (for example, for the website for my &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.github.io/qtlcharts&#34;&gt;R/qtlcharts package&lt;/a&gt;, on interactive graphics for QTL data).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the tutorial, I wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;(For example, I don&#39;t like how simple code is rendered in red within a gray box. Ultimately I&#39;ll try to figure out how to change that, but for now I just pretend that I like it that way.)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this morning, I figured out how to change that: create &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/simple_site/blob/gh-pages/assets/themes/twitter/css/kbroman.css&#34;&gt;my own css file&lt;/a&gt; with the following code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;code {
  padding: 0;
  font-size: 90%;
  color: black;
  background-color: white;
  border: 0px solid white;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/simple_site/blob/gh-pages/_includes/themes/twitter/default.html#L20&#34;&gt;add a line&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/simple_site/blob/gh-pages/_includes/themes/twitter/default.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;default.html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Startling lack of training in statistical computing</title>
      <link>/2014/03/14/startling-lack-of-training-in-statistical-computing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/03/14/startling-lack-of-training-in-statistical-computing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is shocking to me that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;a statistics department&lt;/a&gt; would offer a graduate-level statistical computing course only &lt;em&gt;every fourth year&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/05/25/a-course-in-statistical-programming/&#34;&gt;had been arguing for a statistical programming course&lt;/a&gt;: that we supplement the usual course on the &lt;em&gt;theory&lt;/em&gt; of statistical computing (numerical linear algebra, EM algorithm, MCMC, etc.) with a course on the &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; of statistical computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was assuming that the more theoretical statistical computing course was &lt;em&gt;actually being taught&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a department teaches a course at a frequency less than every-other-year, it&amp;rsquo;s unavailable to many students, or it comes too late in their training to be useful. And statistical computing should really be considered part of a statistics department&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;core curriculum&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update: As you might have anticipated, I&amp;rsquo;ve been asked to teach the course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Copyright of video lectures</title>
      <link>/2014/02/09/copyright-of-video-lectures/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/09/copyright-of-video-lectures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Quite a while back, I was wondering about copyright of video lectures produced by university faculty. In particular, did I need to get the university to sign some sort of waiver in order for the Jackson Laboratory to post a video of a lecture I&amp;rsquo;d given for a course there? (The Jackson Lab lawyers wanted that.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spoke to my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.giso6150.com/&#34;&gt;family librarian&lt;/a&gt;, who pointed me to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.library.wisc.edu/directory/staff/Carrie-Kruse&#34;&gt;Carrie Kruse&lt;/a&gt;, directory of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://college.library.wisc.edu/&#34;&gt;College Library&lt;/a&gt; at UW-Madison. And really, librarians are the people to talk to about this sort of thing, as they not only think a lot about copyright and fair use, but also they&amp;rsquo;re on the side of more access. (But don&amp;rsquo;t hold &lt;em&gt;Carrie&lt;/em&gt; accountable if I say anything wrong below; this is my own interpretation, 14 months after corresponding with her.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most jobs, the product of your work is owned by the company, even if they didn&amp;rsquo;t have anything to do with it. But universities have a different tradition. Typically, the university doesn&amp;rsquo;t assert any rights over a faculty member&amp;rsquo;s instructional materials. For example, if you write a textbook, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to negotiate with the university over its publication, nor do you have to give the university a cut of the royalty income. That&amp;rsquo;s different than patents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UW-Madison has &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uwsa.edu/fadmin/gapp/gapp27.htm&#34;&gt;an explicit policy about faculty instructional materials&lt;/a&gt;. (Really, it&amp;rsquo;s a UW System policy.) As I understand it, the university will assert some rights over your instructional materials only if they had contributed special resources or support to their creation (for example, if university staff assisted you with the recording and editing of a video).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to the video issue: since the university wasn&amp;rsquo;t involved in the production of the video, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to get their okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carrie mentioned another important thing to pay attention to: if I had used any photos or other media to which I don&amp;rsquo;t have rights, I need to be careful about their inclusion in videos posted online. Within a classroom, or in a video posted online but only made accessible to a defined group of students, inclusion of such material could fall under &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair_use&#34;&gt;fair use&lt;/a&gt;. But if such material is included in a video that is posted online for general viewing, others may question my fair use claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That may explain why so many instructors here are using password-protected sites, like &lt;a href=&#34;https://learnuw.wisc.edu/&#34;&gt;Learn@UW&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://courses.moodle.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;Moodle&lt;/a&gt;. I can&amp;rsquo;t even look at my colleagues&amp;rsquo; course material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dislike web pages via online forms. (Well, except for you, wordpress; I wish I&amp;rsquo;d started this blog with &lt;a href=&#34;http://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt;, but you&amp;rsquo;re okay.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I &lt;em&gt;despise&lt;/em&gt; the password protection of instructional materials. If I spend a bunch of time preparing material, I want to distribute it as widely as possible. If another instructor uses it in their own class, I consider that a Good Thing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I still don&#39;t like it</title>
      <link>/2014/02/09/i-still-dont-like-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/09/i-still-dont-like-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got a book in the mail this week, a book I hadn&amp;rsquo;t ordered and would never have ordered. The publisher sent me a complimentary copy, as I&amp;rsquo;d reviewed the book proposal last year. (It&amp;rsquo;s the one where &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/07/what-a-waste-of-paper/&#34;&gt;the author refused to allow me to have an electronic copy&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I soundly trashed the proposal in my review. In the nicest possible way, of course. For example, I said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
And then there are things that are just plain wrong. For example, &#34;We then express our confidence in the H0 with a p-value, which might crudely be considered the probability that the H0 is true.&#34; That is not a _crude_ interpretation of the p-value; that is just _wrong_.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like if a reviewer says, &amp;ldquo;This particular book should not be adopted,&amp;rdquo; the publisher can interpret that to also mean, &amp;ldquo;and whatever you do, don&amp;rsquo;t send me a copy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Things to avoid as a new faculty member</title>
      <link>/2013/12/05/things-to-avoid-as-a-new-faculty-member/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/12/05/things-to-avoid-as-a-new-faculty-member/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The transition from graduate student or postdoc to tenure-track faculty member is hard. You discover that there are a ton of new things to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some thoughts on things to &lt;em&gt;avoid&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may see lots of ways in which your department could be improved; don&amp;rsquo;t try to fix all of them at once.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may see needs for many new courses.  Don&amp;rsquo;t try to develop all of them.  Try to teach the same courses at least three years in a row.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t agree to work with just any student who asks.  While a good student can really help, a bad student can suck up all your time and energy. Students may be worried about money and feigning interest in order to get a research position, but if they&amp;rsquo;re not &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; interested, they won&amp;rsquo;t make much progress and it will be bad for both of you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t agree to collaborate with someone in the two weeks before a grant deadline. You might get stuck in a commitment with some total jerk.  Find out if you&amp;rsquo;d really enjoy working with them, first.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t agree to write a book chapter.  It&amp;rsquo;s almost as much work as a formal paper, but not as many people will read it and it won&amp;rsquo;t count for much on your CV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It was a really bad idea to use slides in that class</title>
      <link>/2013/10/08/it-was-a-really-bad-idea-to-use-slides-in-that-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/08/it-was-a-really-bad-idea-to-use-slides-in-that-class/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I gave a presentation in the Statistical Consulting course at UW-Madison today. I&amp;rsquo;ve done so a number of times in the past 6 years. Until today, I&amp;rsquo;d just spoken informally from a few pages of notes. (Earlier this year, I wrote up those notes as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/02/thoughts-on-statistical-consulting/&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, just 45 min before the class, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d quickly create some slides to present. I thought it&amp;rsquo;d be an interesting &amp;ldquo;experiment&amp;rdquo; (not in the formal sense):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Could I quickly create usable slides using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/10/07/better-looking-latexbeamer-slides/&#34;&gt;LateX/Beamer template I wrote about yesterday&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Would it be useful to have slides in this class?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome was pretty clear: It was easy to create a bunch of bullet-point-based slides. They look nice. (See the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/teaching/misc/consulting.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf here&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/kbroman/Talk_StatConsulting.git&#34;&gt;source here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But&lt;/strong&gt;, the slides themselves worse than useless: Unnecessary, and they interfered with the desired informal nature of the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t be using those slides again. I&amp;rsquo;ll go back to just talking from notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the students were really good and involved and asked great questions, anyway. So no real harm done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Better-looking LaTeX/Beamer slides</title>
      <link>/2013/10/07/better-looking-latexbeamer-slides/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/07/better-looking-latexbeamer-slides/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I like to use &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.latex-project.org/&#34;&gt;LaTeX&lt;/a&gt; to make slides for talks, largely because I prefer to write code (rather than use a mouse and menus) for control of things like colors and figure placement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people that use LaTeX to make slides seem to use &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beamer_(LaTeX)&#34;&gt;Beamer&lt;/a&gt;, but the resulting slides are usually a bit busy, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://deic.uab.es/~iblanes/beamer_gallery/individual/Warsaw-default-default.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://deic.uab.es/~iblanes/beamer_gallery/large/Warsaw-default-default-01.png&#34; alt=&#34;Typical beamer slide&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I admire &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Till_Tantau&#34;&gt;Till Tantau&lt;/a&gt; for creating Beamer; it was a great idea and it&amp;rsquo;s been widely adopted. But I don&amp;rsquo;t like talk outlines at all; I certainly don&amp;rsquo;t want to see one on every page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several days work, I&amp;rsquo;ve finally figured out how to create LaTeX/Beamer-based slides that look like what I want:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations/openaccess.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/10/openaccess_pg1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Open Access talk, title page&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll explain what I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-history&#34;&gt;My history&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at my &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/pages/talks.html&#34;&gt;list of presentations&lt;/a&gt; (going back to 1998), and you&amp;rsquo;ll see that I switched from LaTeX to powerpoint in 2004 and then switched back to LaTeX in 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My LaTeX-based slides (e.g., see &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/kbroman/Talk_Graphs&#34;&gt;my talks on data visualization&lt;/a&gt;) have been made using &lt;code&gt;\documentclass{article}&lt;/code&gt;, just changing the page size and increasing the font and then hard-coding placement of stuff. It leads to some pretty ugly and awkward code, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\headsize \color{myyellow}
\hfill \begin{minipage}{5.75in}
\centering
Example 1
\end{minipage}

\vspace{30mm}

\centerline{\includegraphics[height=6in]{Figs/fig1a.png}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew Beamer would give cleaner code, but how to also have cleaner slides?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-starting-point&#34;&gt;A starting point&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I googled &amp;ldquo;clean Beamer slides&amp;rdquo; or something like that, and I came across &lt;a href=&#34;http://mikedewar.wordpress.com/2009/02/25/latex-beamer-python-beauty/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://mikedewar.wordpress.com&#34;&gt;Mike Dewar&lt;/a&gt;, with a picture of a slide that looked much like what I wanted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://mikedewar.files.wordpress.com/2009/02/beamer_screen.png&amp;amp;h=360&#34; alt=&#34;Slide from Mike Dewar&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I read his post and studied his code and played around. Then I searched for stuff on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://tex.stackexchange.com/&#34;&gt;LaTeX Stack Exchange&lt;/a&gt; and played around some more. Then I read the &lt;a href=&#34;ftp://ftp.dante.de/tex-archive/macros/latex/contrib/beamer/doc/beameruserguide.pdf&#34;&gt;Beamer manual&lt;/a&gt; and played around some more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s really not much to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-benefits-of-beamer&#34;&gt;The benefits of Beamer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main benefits of using Beamer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simpler code, because it will place elements in reasonable places without a lot of messing about&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simple animations using less code, so you &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don&#39;t_repeat_yourself&#34;&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t repeat yourself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Easy way to create handouts with notes on what you&amp;rsquo;re going to say. This is especially useful for others to learn from your presentation even if they can&amp;rsquo;t attend (which is most of the world). Here&amp;rsquo;s an example page from such a handout:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations/openaccess_withnotes.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/10/openaccess_withnotes_pg15.png&#34; alt=&#34;Example notes page from Open Access talk&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;here-s-what-i-did&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I did&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was preparing a talk on open access publishing. Here&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/kbroman/Talk_OpenAccess&#34;&gt;the source&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations/openaccess.pdf&#34;&gt;the pdf&lt;/a&gt;; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations/openaccess_withnotes.pdf&#34;&gt;a pdf with notes on what I intend to say&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll go through the details of the code, in case it might be useful to someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the first two lines of the &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file. The &lt;code&gt;12pt&lt;/code&gt; makes the default font a bit bigger, but not actually twelve point. The &lt;code&gt;t&lt;/code&gt; makes the body of each slide top-justified rather than vertically centered. You don&amp;rsquo;t need many packages, as lots of them (like &lt;code&gt;color&lt;/code&gt;) are included by default with Beamer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\documentclass[12pt,t]{beamer}
\usepackage{graphicx}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These next two lines are for the notes pages (if you are going to use that feature); more below.  By default, the notes are hidden. I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/Talk_OpenAccess/blob/master/createVersionWithNotes.rb&#34;&gt;ruby script&lt;/a&gt; to switch the &lt;code&gt;hide&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;show&lt;/code&gt; and add &lt;code&gt;handout&lt;/code&gt; to the options in the &lt;code&gt;\documentclass&lt;/code&gt; command (more on that below). The &lt;code&gt;\setbeamertemplate&lt;/code&gt; command makes the note pages completely plain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\setbeameroption{hide notes}
\setbeamertemplate{note page}[plain]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These next lines choose the default Beamer theme, get rid of all of the navigation stuff, and make it so any bookmarks are not shown when you open the PDF in Acrobat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\usetheme{default}
\beamertemplatenavigationsymbolsempty
\hypersetup{pdfpagemode=UseNone} % don&#39;t show bookmarks on initial view
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These next lines change the font to Helvetica Neue, with Palatino used for the notes pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\usefonttheme{professionalfonts}
\usefonttheme{serif}
\usepackage{fontspec}
\setmainfont{Helvetica Neue}
\setbeamerfont{note page}{family*=pplx,size=\footnotesize} % Palatino for notes
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I define a bunch of colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\definecolor{foreground}{RGB}{255,255,255}
\definecolor{background}{RGB}{24,24,24}
\definecolor{title}{RGB}{107,174,214}
\definecolor{gray}{RGB}{155,155,155}
\definecolor{subtitle}{RGB}{102,255,204}
\definecolor{hilight}{RGB}{102,255,204}
\definecolor{vhilight}{RGB}{255,111,207}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use those colors, for the titles, subtitle, institute, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\setbeamercolor{titlelike}{fg=title}
\setbeamercolor{subtitle}{fg=subtitle}
\setbeamercolor{institute}{fg=gray}
\setbeamercolor{normal text}{fg=foreground,bg=background}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stuff changes the color of bullets in &lt;code&gt;itemize&lt;/code&gt; environments and changes nested bullet symbols to en-dashes (-) in gray, and a bit smaller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\setbeamercolor{item}{fg=foreground} % color of bullets
\setbeamercolor{subitem}{fg=gray}
\setbeamercolor{itemize/enumerate subbody}{fg=gray}
\setbeamertemplate{itemize subitem}{{\textendash}}
\setbeamerfont{itemize/enumerate subbody}{size=\footnotesize}
\setbeamerfont{itemize/enumerate subitem}{size=\footnotesize}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives me a slide number in the lower-right, in gray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\setbeamertemplate{footline}{%
    \raisebox{5pt}{\makebox[\paperwidth]{\hfill\makebox[20pt]{\color{gray}
          \scriptsize\insertframenumber}}}\hspace*{5pt}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adds a bit of space between paragraphs on the notes pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\addtobeamertemplate{note page}{\setlength{\parskip}{12pt}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also made a few small macros to simplify some things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\newcommand{\bi}{\begin{itemize}}
\newcommand{\ei}{\end{itemize}}
\newcommand{\ig}{\includegraphics}
\newcommand{\subt}[1]{{\footnotesize \color{subtitle} {#1}}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;code-for-example-slides&#34;&gt;Code for example slides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the code to create the title slide. (The content is determined by &lt;code&gt;\title&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;\author&lt;/code&gt;, etc., before the &lt;code&gt;\begin{document}&lt;/code&gt;.) The first line is to get rid of the page number. The text in &lt;code&gt;\note{}&lt;/code&gt; will appear on a separate page after the title slide, in the version of the PDF with notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
\setbeamertemplate{footline}{} % no page number here
\frame{
  \titlepage
  \note{These are slides for a talk I will give on 24 Oct 2013, at a
    symposium on open access publishing, organized by the Ebling
    Library, UW{\textendash}Madison.}
}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an example regular slide. &lt;code&gt;\subt&lt;/code&gt; is a macro defined above and just makes that text smaller and in a different color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\begin{frame}{Access in action}
\subt{Interesting reference}

\bigskip
\centerline{
\ig[height=0.75\textheight]{Images/img01.jpg}
}

\note{I&#39;ll begin with an illustration of what I mean by
  access.

  The other day I was reading a manuscript and saw an
  article of interest.}
\end{frame}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a fancier slide, with a bit of animation: codes like &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;2-&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, which means that bit is not on the first version of this slide but appears on subsequent versions. When the LaTeX file is turned into a PDF, four versions of this slide are created. But in the handout (with the notes), there&amp;rsquo;ll be just one, and the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;3| handout 0&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; bits are to control the separate look on the animated slides and on the single-slide version that shows up with the notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;\begin{frame}{It&#39;s all about money}
\subt{(Costs in scientific publishing)}

\vspace{24pt}

\bi
\item {\color&amp;amp;lt;3| handout 0&amp;amp;gt;{hilight} Research}
\item {\color&amp;amp;lt;3| handout 0&amp;amp;gt;{hilight} Writing}
\item {\color&amp;amp;lt;3| handout 0&amp;amp;gt;{hilight} Peer review, editorial oversight}
\item {\color&amp;amp;lt;4| handout 0&amp;amp;gt;{hilight} Journal administration}
\item {\color&amp;amp;lt;4| handout 0&amp;amp;gt;{hilight} Copy editing, typesetting}
\item {\color&amp;amp;lt;4| handout 0&amp;amp;gt;{hilight} Distribution}
\item&amp;amp;lt;2-&amp;amp;gt;{\color&amp;amp;lt;2| handout 0&amp;amp;gt;{vhilight} \color&amp;amp;lt;4| handout 0&amp;amp;gt;{hilight} Profit}
\ei
\note{ [clip] }
\end{frame}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-version-with-notes&#34;&gt;A version with notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s nice to have a version of one&amp;rsquo;s slides that includes notes of what you&amp;rsquo;re going to say. I like &lt;a href=&#34;http://bost.ocks.org/mike&#34;&gt;Mike Bostock&lt;/a&gt; approach, as in &lt;a href=&#34;http://bost.ocks.org/mike/d3/workshop/#0&#34;&gt;these slides&lt;/a&gt;, with little sticky notes. But I don&amp;rsquo;t want to spend time trying to implement that in LaTeX, so I went with the built-in functionality in Beamer, though selecting a very plain template and adding a bit of space between paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also chose to create a handout with just a single snapshot of the animated pages (in which I sequentially overlayed a number of images).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having added a &lt;code&gt;\note{}&lt;/code&gt; to each &amp;ldquo;frame,&amp;rdquo; there are just a few simple commands to add to the &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file to get it to compile to the handout with notes. So I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/Talk_OpenAccess/blob/master/createVersionWithNotes.rb&#34;&gt;ruby script&lt;/a&gt; to make those changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then used &lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/statistics/staff/academic-research/firth/software/pdfjam/&#34;&gt;pdfnup&lt;/a&gt; to make the notes PDF be 2-up: the slide above and the notes below. The details are in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/Talk_OpenAccess/blob/master/Makefile&#34;&gt;Makefile&lt;/a&gt;; if that&amp;rsquo;s not obvious, see my &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.github.io/minimal_make/&#34;&gt;minimal tutorial about GNU make&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complaints about the NIH grant review process</title>
      <link>/2013/10/02/complaints-about-the-nih-grant-review-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/02/complaints-about-the-nih-grant-review-process/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, I met with a collaborator to discuss what to do with our NIH grant proposal, whose &amp;ldquo;A1&amp;rdquo; was &amp;ldquo;unscored&amp;rdquo; (ie, the revised version, and you don&amp;rsquo;t get a third try, received a &amp;ldquo;preliminary score&amp;rdquo; in the lower half and so was not discussed by the review panel and couldn&amp;rsquo;t be funded).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NIH proposals are typically reviewed by three people and given preliminary scores on five aspects (significance, approach, investigators, environment, innovation) and overall, and the top proposals based on those scores are discussed and scored by the larger panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reviewers gave our proposal an 8 for &amp;ldquo;approach&amp;rdquo; (on a scale of 1-9, with 1 being good and 9 being terrible) with the following review comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
**4. Approach:**
**Strengths**

&gt;
&gt;

&gt;   * Well described details for mining of [data] and genotyping of [subjects].
&gt;

**Weaknesses**

&gt;
&gt;

&gt;   * There is no power analysis for Aim 2. Without knowing which and how many [phenotypes] will be evaluated it is not possible to estimate the statistical power.
&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valid comments, but is that really all the reviewer had to say? What about Aims 1 and 3, or the other aspects of Aim 2? &lt;em&gt;That is totally fucking inadequate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at this review again, I was reminded of how much I despise many aspects of the NIH review process. So it&amp;rsquo;s led me, finally, to write down some of the things that annoy me.
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-scoring-system-is-too-discrete&#34;&gt;The scoring system is too discrete&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been involved in reviewing NIH grants for 15 years. A bunch of changes were made in about 2009 or so, with a few things for the better (like having the review order of grants based on preliminary score) but many for the worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst change was to the scoring system. In the old system, reviewers scored grants on a scale of 1-5, in tenths (1.0, 1.1, 1.2, &amp;hellip;), with 1 being best and 5 being worst. Scores were averaged and multiplied by 100, so the best possible score was 100 and the worst was 500. (And note that the middle value was 300 not 250, a point of confusion for many.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new system, reviewers score grants on a scale of 1-9, in single digits, with 1 being best and 9 being worst (and 5 being the middle value). Scores are averaged and multiplied by ten, so the best possible score is 10 and the worst is 90.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the new scale was introduced, we were given the following handy chart:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/10/nih_score_chart.png&#34; alt=&#34;NIH 9-point score chart&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I understand it, there were two main reasons for revising the scoring system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fix the &amp;ldquo;grade inflation&amp;rdquo; problem (too many good scores)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reviewers can&amp;rsquo;t score grants with 0.1 precision.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as a fix for the grade inflation problem, revising the scoring system could only be a temporary solution. And as I understand it, the problem is now worse than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big problem with the new scoring system is that reviewers have just 9 choices of scores, whereas before they had 41. Yes, a reviewer can&amp;rsquo;t really discriminate 1.3 from 1.4. **But if you have 25 imprecise measure instruments, would it be better to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;average and then round&lt;/em&gt;, or&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;round and then average&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s obviously better to &lt;em&gt;average and then round&lt;/em&gt;, but the new scoring system &lt;em&gt;rounds and then averages&lt;/em&gt;. (&lt;a href=&#34;http://churchill.jax.org/about/churchill.shtml&#34;&gt;Gary Churchill&lt;/a&gt; pointed this out to me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to the frequent statements like, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;d put this somewhere between a 1 and a 2.&amp;rdquo; And with line (or &amp;ldquo;band&amp;rdquo;) between funded and not funded being well above 20, it seems like, in many cases, &lt;em&gt;whether a grant is funded has to do with the proportion of reviewers that give it a 1&lt;/em&gt; rather than a 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-bullet-point-based-reviews-lead-to-superficial-and-incomplete-comments&#34;&gt;The bullet-point-based reviews lead to superficial and incomplete comments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be that the written reviews of grant proposals were much like reviews of journal articles: for each aspect of a proposal (significance, approach, etc.), we&amp;rsquo;d write a few paragraphs, in some cases a full page. Such reviews were hard to write, were often long, and sometimes didn&amp;rsquo;t do a good job of making clear what were the really important issues and what were the less important ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the big review change in 2009, reviewers were asked to write bullet points for &amp;ldquo;Strengths&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Weaknesses.&amp;rdquo; (And in a Microsoft Word template!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a lot easier to write a few bullet points than to construct coherent prose, but the bullet points that reviewers produce are generally shallow and incomplete. In some cases, a reviewer&amp;rsquo;s thinking about a proposal may be left in a shallow and incomplete state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review at the top of this post is the best (or really &lt;em&gt;worst&lt;/em&gt;) instance of this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;don-t-drop-the-proposal-summary-from-the-beginning-of-the-discussion&#34;&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t drop the proposal summary from the beginning of the discussion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, the discussion of a proposal would begin with the primary reviewer giving a brief summary: what are the investigators proposing to do? This is critical, as only 3 of the 25 or so people on the panel will have read the proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know if they&amp;rsquo;re still doing this, but with the other changes to the review process, we were asked to skip the summary of proposal and just discuss the significance of the work. But how on earth can you talk about the significance of the work without some mention of what the work actually is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-electronic-grant-format-is-often-not-human-readable&#34;&gt;The electronic grant format is often not human readable.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first reviewed NIH grant proposals, we each got a copy-paper-sized box with all of the proposals (and when proposals were triaged, all 25 reviewers would simultaneously throw the proposal into a big pile). It was great to move to electronic versions of grants (initially scanned, then fully electronic), but the electronic versions of proposals are not constructed in a way that has a human reader in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front page of grants used to be quite clear and informative, but now all of the form-generated pages are a design mess. For example, the pages listing the key personnel and their institutions are really hard to parse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there are loads of useless pages describing what documents were included. Couldn&amp;rsquo;t the reviewers get a version without all of that crap?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the PDF bookmarks are often off by a page. If you want to go to the biosketches, you need to click the biosketch bookmark and then page down one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things aren&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; big of a deal, but they&amp;rsquo;re a constant annoyance, and they should be easy to fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony Scarpa, the former director of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://public.csr.nih.gov/Pages/default.aspx&#34;&gt;NIH Center for Scientific Review (CSR)&lt;/a&gt; who was responsible for the big change in the NIH review system, once visited U Wisconsin, and I asked him about whether these electronic proposals could be improved, and he said, &amp;ldquo;Oh, that&amp;rsquo;s not us; that&amp;rsquo;s grants.gov.&amp;rdquo; So I asked who I should talk to about the issue, and he said, &amp;ldquo;Call your Congressman.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;there-needs-to-be-some-review-of-reviewers&#34;&gt;There needs to be some review of reviewers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final comment: there needs to be some formal way for reviewers to comment on other reviewers. I think most reviewers are very careful and responsible, but there&amp;rsquo;s often at least one total jerk on a review panel: didn&amp;rsquo;t read the proposal carefully, didn&amp;rsquo;t write a coherent review, didn&amp;rsquo;t pay any attention to what the other reviewers said, gave completely unfair scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There should be some system for other reviewers to say, &amp;ldquo;So-and-so on the panel was a complete jerk and shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be brought back.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiring computational biologists</title>
      <link>/2013/09/25/hiring-computational-biologists/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/25/hiring-computational-biologists/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://discovery.wisc.edu/home/morgridge/morgridge.cmsx&#34;&gt;Morgridge Institute for Research&lt;/a&gt; (MIR), a private research institute associated with UW-Madison, is looking to hire some computational folks working in biology. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/About/Jobs/adPLV77619.pdf&#34;&gt;One position&lt;/a&gt; is joint with my department,  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;Biostatistics &amp;amp; Medical Informatics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yet-another-symposium&#34;&gt;Yet another symposium&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday afternoon, they held a symposium on &amp;ldquo;Computation in Biology&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/09/computation-in-biology-agenda.pdf&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the agenda.&lt;/a&gt;) Great speakers: &lt;a href=&#34;http://faculty.biomath.ucla.edu/msuchard/&#34;&gt;Marc Suchard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://shoichetlab.compbio.ucsf.edu/&#34;&gt;Brian Shoichet&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://pages.cs.wisc.edu/~dpage/&#34;&gt;David Page&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/winston-hide/&#34;&gt;Winston Hide&lt;/a&gt;. They were asked to speak broadly about computation in biology and on the key issues for the future, and there was plenty of time for discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what MIR was hoping to get out of the symposium, but if they were looking for guidance regarding their hiring efforts, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t effective. At the beginning, the discussion was quite heated but not terribly constructive. In the middle, it became more like the usual sort of question/answer after a seminar. I must admit I didn&amp;rsquo;t stay to the end. Perhaps some important insights were gained after I left. But it seems unlikely that the symposium provided much guidance about hiring in computational biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-key-issues&#34;&gt;The key issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are what I think the key issues are, when a scientific organization is looking to hire some computational folks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you want a targeted search (for particular kinds of applications or approaches), or do you want to leave it general and just pick the best folks who apply?. (&lt;em&gt;In my experience, targeted searches don&amp;rsquo;t work as well; you miss out on some great people.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What service role is expected of the person? Do you want them to meet some particular scientists&amp;rsquo; needs, or are you going to let them do whatever they want, with the hope that they form useful (to the organization) collaborations? (&lt;em&gt;The expectations should be made explicit.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;At promotion time, who is going to evaluate the person? If it&amp;rsquo;s a separate academic department (say, Statistics, or maybe Biochemistry), do they share your organization&amp;rsquo;s values? (&lt;em&gt;Some of the best applied computational scientists may not be generating the NIH grants that a traditional biological sciences department might expect, nor the JASA or Biometrics papers that a Statistics department might expect.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Will the person have appropriate mentors? Is there anyone at the institution who really understands the nature of their position and what they need to do to succeed? (&lt;em&gt;I worry particularly about computational scientists who are isolated from their computational peers.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have any great answers, but those are the issues that I&amp;rsquo;m concerned about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;: The real point I&amp;rsquo;m trying to make: academics doesn&amp;rsquo;t do a good job of rewarding tool building (eg, software tools). It&amp;rsquo;s often viewed as better to write papers with toy implementations than to make generally useful software. That&amp;rsquo;s a real problem for computational biology, and for folks seeking to hire truly useful computational biologists.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Department websites</title>
      <link>/2013/09/11/department-websites/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/11/department-websites/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I was thinking about department websites, partly because &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;my own department&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt; is terrible, and recently a colleague asked me whether I could suggest some &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; department sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll describe the basic principles for a good department website, and then I&amp;rsquo;ll comment on a number of examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first: No discussion of academic web pages is complete without referring to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/773/&#34;&gt;xkcd comic&lt;/a&gt; on University websites, so let&amp;rsquo;s start with that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/773/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/university_website.png&#34; alt=&#34;xkcd comic: University Websites&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;basic-principles&#34;&gt;Basic principles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are what I see to be the basic principles for constructing a department website:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Think of the audiences and what they&amp;rsquo;d be looking for&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prospective students&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prospective/visiting faculty&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Current students&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Collaborators&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Administrators&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Current faculty&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Department staff&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keep the important stuff near the top; minimize bloat&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the key stuff that should be prominent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Degree programs; courses; how to apply&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Faculty and student pages&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Staff contact information&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seminars&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Job opportunities&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t use stock photos or (even worse!) clip art&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avoid deep nesting of information&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have meaningful URLs (in particular, don&amp;rsquo;t let &lt;a href=&#34;https://drupal.org/&#34;&gt;drupal&lt;/a&gt; use &lt;code&gt;node/134&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have a consistent style across the official pages &amp;ndash; particularly in the location and layout of menus of hyperlinks&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I prefer minimalism. Think &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com&#34;&gt;google&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com&#34;&gt;apple&lt;/a&gt; rather than &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.microsoft.com&#34;&gt;Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-examples&#34;&gt;Some examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I briefly perused a number of statistics and biostatistics department websites. Here are my first impressions. The sites for &lt;a href=&#34;http://statistics.berkeley.edu/&#34;&gt;Berkeley&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://statistics.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;Stanford&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.umn.edu/&#34;&gt;Minnesota&lt;/a&gt; Statistics were my favorites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Hopkins Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key bits are half-way down the page, due to unnecessary (in my mind) school-related crap along the top, plus the news items. The &amp;ldquo;Quick find&amp;rdquo; looks-like-a-drop-down-menu at the top right seems to just link to a &lt;em&gt;different department&amp;rsquo;s web page&lt;/em&gt;. The news items at the top result in the menu moving upward when you click on a link (as those news items don&amp;rsquo;t appear in the subsequent pages).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/biostatistics&#34;&gt;Harvard Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s too much school-related crap at the top, but it&amp;rsquo;s not as bad as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Hopkins site&lt;/a&gt;. I like having pages &amp;ldquo;For Prospective Students,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;For Current Students,&amp;rdquo; etc., but they pop to pages that look totally different and lose that menu, so you have to go back and then forward again. &amp;ldquo;Student Profiles&amp;rdquo; maybe should just be called &amp;ldquo;Student Profile&amp;rdquo; as there doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be more than one. The &amp;ldquo;BIO&amp;rdquo; in &amp;ldquo;BIO Faculty&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;BIO Researchers&amp;rdquo; was a little confusing: Is it obvious what &amp;ldquo;BIO&amp;rdquo; means, and is it really necessary?  I&amp;rsquo;d put the Faculty and Researchers links closer to the top and may try to distinguish the different classes of links: the ones that people are really there for, and then all of the &amp;ldquo;For Such-and-Such&amp;rdquo; somewhat separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.washington.edu/&#34;&gt;Washington Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reasonably clean, but a bit of the &lt;code&gt;node/134&lt;/code&gt; problem. And there are two kinds of menus: tabs at the top, and a menu at the right side. I think it&amp;rsquo;s okay, but it was a bit confusing initially: It wasn&amp;rsquo;t immediately obvious that I click a different tab to get a different set of menu choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sph.unc.edu/department-pages/biostatistics/&#34;&gt;UNC-Chapel Hill Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main page looks nice, but the sub-pages have a different format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.ncsu.edu/&#34;&gt;NC State Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I generally like it, but why split the faculty list across multiple pages? I see no reason to limit the length of a web page; scrolling is our friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sph.umn.edu/biostatistics/&#34;&gt;Minnesota Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Way&lt;/em&gt; too much bloat at the top; links all over the place at the bottom&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.umn.edu/&#34;&gt;Minnesota Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this one. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure about the color choices, but the site is clean, and it&amp;rsquo;s easy to navigate. And I like the choice and order of topics in the menu at the left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://statistics.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;Stanford Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like this one: Just the facts, plus a picture of Sequoia Hall. There&amp;rsquo;s a little menu bar at the top that has the key stuff. You want to know about courses or degree programs? Click &amp;ldquo;Academics.&amp;rdquo; You want to know about People or Seminars? They&amp;rsquo;re right there at the top. How do you apply? Click &amp;ldquo;Admissions.&amp;rdquo; They could maybe trim the news on the left of the front page; some of it is getting old and at least one of the links doesn&amp;rsquo;t work anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://statistics.berkeley.edu/&#34;&gt;Berkeley Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berkeley is slightly better than Stanford. The websites, I mean. It&amp;rsquo;s simple, there&amp;rsquo;s a clean little menu at the top, and the menus at the top have clear little drop-down menus when you hover over things. I like that they use more horizontal space. I guess I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t put &amp;ldquo;Seminars&amp;rdquo; under &amp;ldquo;Research&amp;rdquo; Nor would I put &amp;ldquo;Alumni Connections&amp;rdquo; under &amp;ldquo;Industry.&amp;rdquo; So there are ways in which Stanford is better than Berkeley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sph.umich.edu/biostat/&#34;&gt;Michigan Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front page looks a bit cluttered. And they list University rankings front and center, which is a bit of an embarrassment. There&amp;rsquo;s a bit of school-related stuff at the top, but it&amp;rsquo;s not as bothersome as some others. There may be too many choices on the left. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to pick out the ones you want, even if they&amp;rsquo;re there. And &amp;ldquo;Students&amp;rdquo; should really be &amp;ldquo;For Students,&amp;rdquo; while &amp;ldquo;Careers&amp;rdquo; should really be &amp;ldquo;Alumni Profiles.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I could look at a ton more, but I&amp;rsquo;m sort of sick of this. Go have a look yourself, and let me know if you find good ones.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stack Exchange: Why I dropped out</title>
      <link>/2013/05/13/stack-exchange-why-i-dropped-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/05/13/stack-exchange-why-i-dropped-out/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://stackexchange.com&#34;&gt;Stack Exchange&lt;/a&gt; is a series of question-and-answer sites, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com&#34;&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; for programming and &lt;a href=&#34;http://stats.stackexchange.com/&#34;&gt;Cross Validated&lt;/a&gt; for statistics.  I was &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2011/09/26/gamified/&#34;&gt;introduced to these sites&lt;/a&gt; at a short talk by &lt;a href=&#34;http://geospaced.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Barry Rowlingson&lt;/a&gt; at the 2011 UseR! meeting, &amp;ldquo;Why R-help must die!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sites have a lot of advantages over R-help: The format is easier to read, math and code can be nicely formatted, the questions are tagged, search is easier, and there should be less redundancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;additional-pros&#34;&gt;Additional pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s good to help people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s fun to rack up reputation points for helping people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s good exercise, in both thinking about statistical questions and in articulating useful answers (and there are some interesting questions).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;however-some-cons&#34;&gt;However, some cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reputation points thing is a bit too addictive to me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The easy questions go fast; you have to watch constantly if you want a chance at them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Far too many questions are either dreadfully dull or terribly sloppy.
(See &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeromyanglim.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Jeromy Anglim&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jeromyanglim.blogspot.com.au/2011/03/how-to-ask-me-statistics-question.html&#34;&gt;How to ask me a statistics question&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://catb.org/~esr/&#34;&gt;Eric S. Raymond&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html&#34;&gt;How to ask questions the smart way&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;ldquo;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Good answers are, at times, insufficiently appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;so-i-gave-up&#34;&gt;So I gave up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started spending time on &lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com&#34;&gt;stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://stats.stackexchange.com&#34;&gt;cross-validated&lt;/a&gt; soon after returning from UseR! 2011, but I lost my patience and quit within three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One needs to treat each question with respect, and I eventually seemed to lose my ability to sustain such goodwill.  I think I take things too personally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update&#34;&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should clarify: I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; continue to use Stack Exchange, mostly through google.  Many problems I run into have already been answered.  I just don&amp;rsquo;t have the right temperament to participate regularly in answering others&amp;rsquo; questions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>$18 for a two page PDF? I still don&#39;t get it.</title>
      <link>/2013/05/02/18-for-a-two-page-pdf-i-still-dont-get-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/05/02/18-for-a-two-page-pdf-i-still-dont-get-it/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Ananyo/status/329545985149775873&#34;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Ananyo&#34;&gt;@Ananyo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Time that biologists stopped telling the public oversimplistic fairy tales on Darwinian evolution, says P Ball ($) [nature.com/nature/journal...](http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v496/n7446/full/496419a.html)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I clicked the link to the Nature paper and realized, &amp;ldquo;Oh, yeah.  I&amp;rsquo;ve got to enter through the UW library website.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I thought, &amp;ldquo;Wait&amp;hellip;$18 for a two-page Nature comment?  WTF?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/329560393922002944&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
DNA: Celebrate the unknowns, like this Nature comment, which costs $18. [nature.com/nature/journal...](http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v496/n7446/full/496419a.html)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thinking about it some more, I got more annoyed, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/329566578024775683&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Why do publishers charge such high per-article fees? At $18/artcl, you&#39;d have to be desperate or stupid to pay; at $1-2, prob&#39;ly lots would.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I thought, I&amp;rsquo;ll &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/329575795716661250&#34;&gt;ask Nature directly&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
@NatureMagazine Why is the per-article charge so high? It seems like you&#39;d make more profit at $2/article.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/NatureMagazine&#34;&gt;they&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/NatureMagazine/status/329655405355614210&#34;&gt;responded&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
@kwbroman For a while now, individual papers can be rented through @readcube for $3-5. A full tablet subscription to Nature costs $35.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that didn&amp;rsquo;t quite answer my question.  So I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/329683444051365889&#34;&gt;asked&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
.@NatureMagazine So is the $18 charge for a 2 pg PDF just to discourage piracy?
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought a lot about whether to put &amp;ldquo;piracy&amp;rdquo; in quotes or not, or whether to write &amp;ldquo;copyright infringement&amp;rdquo; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anyway, they &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/NatureMagazine/status/329692960205725696&#34;&gt;responded&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
@kwbroman just as with any product, the more you buy, the more you save. Media/publishing subscriptions have worked this way for decades.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That again didn&amp;rsquo;t quite answer my question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;it-s-a-scam&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a scam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still don&amp;rsquo;t understand the $18 business.  It&amp;rsquo;s not &amp;ldquo;The more you buy, the more you save.&amp;rdquo;  It&amp;rsquo;s, &amp;ldquo;Buy the whole season for $35, or buy 5 min from Episode 1 for $18.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that the cover price of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com&#34;&gt;Wired&lt;/a&gt; is $5 per issue, while I could get a year&amp;rsquo;s subscription for $15-20.  But that&amp;rsquo;s not the same as $18 for &lt;em&gt;one article&lt;/em&gt; vs $200 per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The $18 for a two-page PDF is like 900 numbers and paycheck advances.  These are &lt;em&gt;scams&lt;/em&gt; taking advantage of desperate or stupid people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they don&amp;rsquo;t want to sell the PDFs for individual articles for a reasonable price, they should just not sell them at all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Methods before results</title>
      <link>/2013/04/29/methods-before-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/29/methods-before-results/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s great that, in a step towards improved reproducibility, the Nature journals are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/ng/journal/v45/n5/full/ng.2621.html&#34;&gt;removing page limits on Methods sections&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
To allow authors to describe their experimental designs and methods in enough detail for others to interpret and replicate them, the participating journals are removing length restrictions on Methods sections.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But couldn&amp;rsquo;t they include the Methods section in the pdf for the article?  For example, consider &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/ng/journal/v45/n5/full/ng.2591.html&#34;&gt;this article in Nature Genetics&lt;/a&gt;; the Methods section is only available in the html version of the paper. The PDF says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Methods and any associated references are available in the online version of the paper.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Methods&lt;/em&gt; are important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be separated from the main text.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be placed after the results (as so many journals, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosbiology.org&#34;&gt;PLoS&lt;/a&gt;, do).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be in a smaller font than the main text (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org&#34;&gt;PNAS&lt;/a&gt; does).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They certainly shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be endnotes (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/276/5316/1268.long&#34;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; used to do).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;supplements-annoy-me-too&#34;&gt;Supplements annoy me too&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love supplemental material: authors can give the full details, and they can provide as many supplemental figures and tables as they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But supplements can be a real pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to have to click on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosgenetics.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pgen.1003321#s5&#34;&gt;10 different links&lt;/a&gt;.  Put it all in one document.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to have to open Word.  Put text and figures in a PDF.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to have to open Excel.  Put data in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caitlinrivers.com/1/post/2013/04/send-me-your-data-pdf-is-fine-said-no-one-ever-how-to-share-your-data-effectively.html&#34;&gt;plain text file&lt;/a&gt;, preferably as part of a git repository with related code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least supplements are now included at the journal sites!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/19/8/956.long&#34;&gt;This paper&lt;/a&gt; in Bioinformatics refers to a separate site for supplemental information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Expression data and supplementary information are available at
http://www.rii.com/publications/2003/HE_SDS.htm.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But &lt;code&gt;rii.com&lt;/code&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist anymore.  I was able to find &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.archive.org/web/20080719125540/http://www.rii.com/publications/2003/HE_SDS.html&#34;&gt;the supplement&lt;/a&gt; using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.archive.org&#34;&gt;Wayback Machine&lt;/a&gt;, but&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The link in the paper was wrong: It should be &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt; not &lt;code&gt;.htm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final version on Wayback has a corrupted PDF, though one can go back to previous versions that are okay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-like-genetics-http-www-genetics-org-and-g3-http-www-g3-journal-org&#34;&gt;I like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org&#34;&gt;Genetics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.g3-journal.org&#34;&gt;G3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org&#34;&gt;Genetics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.g3-journal.org&#34;&gt;G3&lt;/a&gt; put the Methods where they belong (before the results), and when you download the PDF for an article in Genetics, it includes the supplement.  For a G3 article, the supplement isn&amp;rsquo;t included in the article PDF, but at least you can the whole supplement as a single PDF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, consider my recent Genetics articles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org/content/190/2/403.full&#34;&gt;Genotype probabilities at intermediate generations in the construction of recombinant inbred lines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org/content/192/1/267.full&#34;&gt;Mapping quantitative trait loci onto a phylogenetic tree&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you click on &amp;ldquo;Full Text (PDF),&amp;rdquo; you get the article plus the 3 supplemental figures and 23 supplemental tables in the former case, and article plus the 17 supplemental figures and 2 supplemental tables in the latter case.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use meaningful URLs</title>
      <link>/2013/04/10/use-meaningful-urls/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/10/use-meaningful-urls/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/natesmoyer/qr-codes-are-stupid&#34;&gt;QR codes are stupid&lt;/a&gt;.  See the well-known &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jcolman/status/320917928881033218&#34;&gt;flowchart&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don&amp;rsquo;t like &lt;a href=&#34;http://drupal.org&#34;&gt;Drupal&lt;/a&gt;.  Sites that use it give things URLs like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.wisc.edu/node/577&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;http://www.genetics.wisc.edu/node/577&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for their seminar list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And can we get rid of the &lt;code&gt;www&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&#34;What&#39;s your web site?&#34;

&#34;double-u double-u double-u ...&#34;

&#34;Zzz...&#34;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;URLs should be meaningful and short.  I like deep hierarchies of folders, but it makes for long URLs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bitly.com&#34;&gt;URL-shorteners&lt;/a&gt; help, but you don&amp;rsquo;t really want to read out (or type) one of those short URLs.  And they tell you nothing about where they&amp;rsquo;re going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you want is something like &lt;a href=&#34;http://bcaffo.com&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bcaffo.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://stodden.net&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;stodden.net&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  Or &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rqtl.org&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But&amp;hellip;I guess you could just say &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll send you an email.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;and-customize-title&#34;&gt;And customize &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while I have your attention, note that the title of your web page shows up on Google (and at the top of the browser).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s nice to see others make use of my html code, but you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;a href=&#34;http://darwin.cwru.edu/~iyengar/publications.html&#34;&gt;leave my name in the title of your publication page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put the important words first (not like the title for my &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/People/faculty/broman.htm&#34;&gt;official page&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;), and perhaps nothing else. For example, the title &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pophealth.wisc.edu/faculty/palta&#34;&gt;shouldn&amp;rsquo;t include &amp;ldquo;Drupal&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;: Read this: &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.not-implemented.com/urls-are-for-people-not-computers/&#34;&gt;URLs are for People, not Computers&lt;/a&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could have just given the URL:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.not-implemented.com/urls-are-for-people-not-computers/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;http://www.not-implemented.com/urls-are-for-people-not-computers&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knuth: Journal referees should assist authors</title>
      <link>/2013/04/08/knuth-journal-referees-should-assist-authors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/08/knuth-journal-referees-should-assist-authors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When serving as referee for a journal, who are you working for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The editor&lt;/em&gt;: Will the paper add to the journal&amp;rsquo;s prestige?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The reader&lt;/em&gt;: Is it worth reading?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The author&lt;/em&gt;: How can it be improved?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d long thought that the referee&amp;rsquo;s duty was to the journal editors and then to the readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Donald Knuth&amp;rsquo;s comments on refereeing persuaded me that I should focus primarily on helping the author to improve the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See pages 31-35 (as numbered; actually 33-37 in the pdf) in his &lt;a href=&#34;http://jmlr.csail.mit.edu/reviewing-papers/knuth_mathematical_writing.pdf&#34;&gt;notes on mathematical writing&lt;/a&gt;. And here&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifs.tuwien.ac.at/~silvia/research-tips/Knuth.pdf&#34;&gt;missing page on &amp;ldquo;Hints for referees&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even a terrible manuscript can be published, if the author is sufficiently persistent. Your primary job as referee should be to help the author to make it as good as it can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost immediately after I first read Donald Knuth&amp;rsquo;s comments (back in 2002), I received one of the worst manuscripts I&amp;rsquo;ve ever read. It was one of those cases where I really wish the authors were anonymous, because I can&amp;rsquo;t forget who was responsible for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was hard for me to say, &amp;ldquo;You have no idea what you&amp;rsquo;re doing&amp;rdquo; in a constructive way. (&amp;ldquo;You should abandon this manuscript&amp;rdquo; is not constructive, but it could be good advice. The scientific literature could use a bit more self-censorship.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to use the &amp;ldquo;Comments to the editor&amp;rdquo; as my opportunity to vent. (I would pity the poor editor on the other end, but she/he sent the thing to me!) I&amp;rsquo;d give an example of my venting, but I think I&amp;rsquo;ll leave that to another time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ENAR highs and lows</title>
      <link>/2013/03/19/enar-highs-and-lows/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/19/enar-highs-and-lows/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I attended the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;ENAR meeting&lt;/a&gt; in Orlando, Florida, last week. (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org&#34;&gt;ENAR&lt;/a&gt; = &amp;ldquo;Eastern North American Region&amp;rdquo; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biometricsociety.org&#34;&gt;International Biometric Society&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time, but I did come to the strong realization that what I view as important is distinctly different from what the typical ENAR attendee views as important.  (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rafalab.org&#34;&gt;Rafa&lt;/a&gt; said, incredulously, &amp;ldquo;You knew that already!&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you about the high- and lowlights, for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also see the ENAR-related comments from &lt;a href=&#34;http://yihui.name/en/2013/03/on-enar-or-statistical-meetings-in-general/&#34;&gt;Yihui Xie&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://alyssafrazee.wordpress.com/2013/03/18/ideas-for-super-awesome-conferences/&#34;&gt;Alyssa Frazee&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;highlights&#34;&gt;Highlights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Getting to know &lt;a href=&#34;http://yihui.name&#34;&gt;Yihui Xie&lt;/a&gt;, and the introductory part of his talk on &lt;a href=&#34;http://yihui.name/knitr/&#34;&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Having lunch with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Hopkins Biostat&lt;/a&gt; students.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Twittering, particularly with &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/StrictlyStat&#34;&gt;@StrictlyStat&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/hspter&#34;&gt;@hspter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hadley Wickham&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://ggplot2.org&#34;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt; tutorial, in which I really learned how to teach.  (Can I put it into practice?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://genes.uchicago.edu/contents/faculty/stephens-matthew.html&#34;&gt;Matthew Stephens&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s talk, and spending time with him.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://faculty.mdanderson.org/Jeffrey_Morris/Default.asp&#34;&gt;Jeff Morris&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s orientation to Epcot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The large data visualization session, with &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/StrictlyStat&#34;&gt;John&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://had.co.nz&#34;&gt;Hadley&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IVdwJvQXeg4&#34;&gt;Amy Heineke&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman&#34;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt;.  (Thanks, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~bswihart/&#34;&gt;Bruce&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lowlights&#34;&gt;Lowlights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They should have emphasized the cheaper shuttle from the airport (vs taxi); the information was hard to find.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They should have emphasized that wifi was actually free; ignore the $14.95/day charge as it gets waived from your bill.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Registration on Sunday closed early, so many at the poster session were without name badges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The program guide PDF should have had bookmarks, and the schedule should have included links to the abstracts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Realism regarding the start time for the President&amp;rsquo;s invited address.  But I guess if we knew the awards ceremony would take not 15 min but 45, &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; would skipped.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The venue was too isolated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The hotel was too expensive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The $85 admission to Epcot was a required part of the registration fee (23%).  The registration fee ($365) was the same as for ENAR 2012 in Washington DC, but it could have been $280.  And there&amp;rsquo;s a striking difference between &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s free!&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;You already paid for it!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lighting in meeting rooms was not great.  We needed a ladder and a can of spray paint to &amp;ldquo;turn off&amp;rdquo; those lights shining on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said at the beginning, I had a good time. But I worry particularly about accessibility to students paying their own way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a really useful and inspirational meeting, right up there with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2011/08/20/user-conference-2011-highlights/&#34;&gt;UseR 2011 meeting&lt;/a&gt; in the UK, but less from talks and more from individual interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LaTeX &#43; Unicode → XeTeX</title>
      <link>/2013/03/19/latex-unicode--xetex/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/19/latex-unicode--xetex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m co-organizing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ctc2013.org&#34;&gt;a scientific meeting&lt;/a&gt; at the end of May.  The abstracts are all in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get them in an Excel file, and I was working on a Perl script to parse the file to create a LaTeX file with the abstracts, so we could have nicely formatted versions for review.  (I&amp;rsquo;m using &lt;a href=&#34;http://search.cpan.org/~dmow/Spreadsheet-XLSX-0.13-withoutworldwriteables/lib/Spreadsheet/XLSX.pm&#34;&gt;Spreadsheet:XLSX&lt;/a&gt; for the first time; it&amp;rsquo;s really easy.  Why have I always converted Excel files to CSV before parsing them?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent way too much time trying to deal with special characters.  I was looking to do a search-and-replace for all possible &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unicode&#34;&gt;Unicode&lt;/a&gt; characters (for example, to change &lt;code&gt;\xE9&lt;/code&gt; aka e into &lt;code&gt;\&#39;{e}&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;\xD7&lt;/code&gt; aka × into &lt;code&gt;$\times$&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/times_symbol.png&#34; alt=&#34;MBT/Pas × BALB/cByJ&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I discovered that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XeTeX&#34;&gt;XeTeX&lt;/a&gt; supports Unicode, so there&amp;rsquo;s no need to do these sorts of substitutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I changed &lt;code&gt;pdflatex&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;xelatex&lt;/code&gt; in my &lt;code&gt;Makefile&lt;/code&gt;, and I&amp;rsquo;m done.  I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;: Now that I think about it, CSV is way more convenient than XLS(X) for simple data files, as you don&amp;rsquo;t have to traverse with the whole &lt;code&gt;$cell -&amp;gt; (Val)&lt;/code&gt; business.  But working with the Excel file directly is easier when the cells may contain lots of text with commas and such, like my abstracts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards making my own papers reproducible</title>
      <link>/2013/03/10/towards-making-my-own-papers-reproducible/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/10/towards-making-my-own-papers-reproducible/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Much has been written about &lt;a href=&#34;http://magazine.amstat.org/blog/2011/01/01/scipolicyjan11/&#34;&gt;reproducible research&lt;/a&gt;: that scientific papers should be accompanied by the data and software sufficient to reproduce the results.  It&amp;rsquo;s obviously a &lt;em&gt;Good Thing&lt;/em&gt;.  But it can be hard to stick to this ideal in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my early papers, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I can find the materials anymore, and that&amp;rsquo;s just 15 years back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my recent papers, I have developed a sort of system so that I can reproduce the results myself.  I use a combination tools, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.uni-muenchen.de/~leisch/Sweave/&#34;&gt;Sweave&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cpan.org&#34;&gt;perl&lt;/a&gt;, and, of course, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnu.org/software/make/&#34;&gt;make&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;ve not been distributing the detailed code behind my papers.  It&amp;rsquo;s not always pretty, and it is not well documented.  (And &amp;ldquo;not always&amp;rdquo; is a bit of a stretch &amp;ndash; more like &amp;ldquo;seldom.&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stodden.net&#34;&gt;Victoria Stodden&lt;/a&gt; visited Madison last fall, I was inspired to release this code, but I never carried through on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then last night I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/310633718551293953&#34;&gt;twittered&lt;/a&gt; an example graph from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/publications/phyloqtl.pdf&#34;&gt;a paper&lt;/a&gt;, was (appropriately) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fellgernon/status/310647658387734528&#34;&gt;asked to produce code&lt;/a&gt;, and so created a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/phyloQTLpaper/&#34;&gt;github repository&lt;/a&gt; with the bulk of the code for that paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The repository is incomplete: it doesn&amp;rsquo;t include the code to do the main analysis and simulations, but just to make the figures, starting from those results.  I&amp;rsquo;ll work to add those additional details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, even once complete, it will be far from perfect.  The code is (or will be) there, but it would take a bit of work for an interested reader to figure out what it is doing, since much of it is undocumented and poorly written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if we ask for perfection, we&amp;rsquo;ll get nothing.  If we ask for the minimal materials for reproducibility, we may get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s my goal: to focus first on &lt;em&gt;minimal accessibility&lt;/em&gt; of the code and data behind a paper, even if it is minimally readable and so might take quite a bit of effort for someone else to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last point: I use local &lt;a href=&#34;http://git-scm.com&#34;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; repositories for my draft analyses and for the whole process of writing a paper.  I could post that whole history, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2011/08/17/the-stupidest-r-code-ever/&#34;&gt;as I said before&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Open source means everyone can see my stupid mistakes. Version control means everyone can see every stupid mistake I&#39;ve ever made.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be easy to make my working repository public, but it would include things like referees&amp;rsquo; reports and my responses to them, as well as the gory details on all of the stupid things that I might do along the way to publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m more comfortable releasing just a snapshot of the final product.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What a waste of paper</title>
      <link>/2013/03/07/what-a-waste-of-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/07/what-a-waste-of-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A university press asked me to review a book manuscript, and the author &amp;ldquo;has asked that we not use electronic copies.&amp;rdquo; So they&amp;rsquo;re going to send me a hard copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My response: &amp;ldquo;If you only give me a paper copy, I&amp;rsquo;m going to just scan it and toss the paper. That seems like a waste of time (and paper and postage).&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should probably have said, &amp;ldquo;Then forget it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their response included, &amp;ldquo;What you do with it when it arrives I am just going to take a hear-no-evil approach to.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hopkins SPH logo, part 3: Karl&#39;s revenge</title>
      <link>/2013/03/06/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-3-karls-revenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/06/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-3-karls-revenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m finally back to the story of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/&#34;&gt;Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/identity/coreIdentity/logoIntro.shtml&#34;&gt;logo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/16/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-1/&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; in mid-November and &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/21/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-2/&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt; a week later.  I said that Part 3 was &amp;ldquo;coming soon,&amp;rdquo; but I&amp;rsquo;ve been a bit shy about revealing this.  You&amp;rsquo;ll see why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August, 2005, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~iruczins/&#34;&gt;Ingo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.albany.edu/sph/19585.php&#34;&gt;Greg&lt;/a&gt;, and I were sitting in a pub in Minneapolis in the early morning hours.  I think maybe &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bcaffo.com&#34;&gt;Brian&lt;/a&gt; was there, too.  We had a session, which Ingo had organized, at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2005/&#34;&gt;Joint Statistical Meetings&lt;/a&gt; the next morning (really &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; morning), and so we should have been sleeping.  (&lt;a href=&#34;http://sunduzkeles.org&#34;&gt;Sunduz&lt;/a&gt; was also in the session, but, sensibly, she wasn&amp;rsquo;t out drinking with us.)  I think this was later in the evening on the night I&amp;rsquo;d offended the guy from Insightful when I said that anyone who still used Splus rather than R was an idiot.  And it was just after Greg and I (and perhaps Brian, if he was there) paid the waitress to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bring the round of drinks that Ingo had ordered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we were talking about the Hopkins SPH logo (otherwise, why would I be discussing this?) as well as an innovative alternative that Brian Caffo had devised, and Ingo bet me to include Brian&amp;rsquo;s alternative logo in my talk the next day (or really &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; day): If I included the alternative logo in my talk, he&amp;rsquo;d buy me beer for a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I did, though I had to stay up quite a bit later to get the images together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kendzior/&#34;&gt;Christina&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.wisc.edu/~newton/&#34;&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt; were in the back of the room.  Ingo was sitting in the front row.  We&amp;rsquo;d used Greg&amp;rsquo;s laptop, so there was evidence.  I made a bit of fun of the Bloomberg name change, and I made a bit of fun of the logo, by showing the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mcusa.org/Portals/8/Images/logo_251x130.gif&#34;&gt;Missionary Church&lt;/a&gt; logo.  And then on my third slide, I paused for a bit and looked at Ingo, and he looked at me and then up at the screen, and when I saw that he&amp;rsquo;d seen it, I flipped to the next slide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Brian&amp;rsquo;s alternative logo, next to the original.  Well, it&amp;rsquo;s Brian&amp;rsquo;s design but my rendering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;JHBSPH logo&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/altlogo.png&#34; alt=&#34;Alternative logo&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/evidence.pdf&#34;&gt;here&amp;rsquo;s a PDF of the logos in context&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s the month of beer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/month_of_beer.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Month of beer&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ingo was willing to restock if necessary, but that wasn&amp;rsquo;t allowed.  We still have most of those coasters; they&amp;rsquo;ve been great toys for the kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October that year, I used the alternative logo on the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/offices-and-services/marketing-and-communications/policies/wall_of_wonder.html&#34;&gt;Wall of Wonder&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; itself, on a second bet, with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/faculty/directory/profile/3980/Pineda/Fernando_J.&#34;&gt;Fernando&lt;/a&gt; this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave another of those informal statistics lectures, this time on &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations/regression_ho.pdf&#34;&gt;What is regression?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;  Of course, they were pre-screening slides at that point, because of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/21/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-2&#34;&gt;first such informal talk&lt;/a&gt;.  But I gave them a last-minute substitution, with just the one logo change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/people/staff/hubbard.shtml&#34;&gt;Patty&lt;/a&gt; caught me, but she didn&amp;rsquo;t turn me in.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the second month of beer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/second_month_of_beer.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Second month of beer&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all seems a bit juvenile in retrospect.  I guess I&amp;rsquo;m getting (or &lt;em&gt;have gotten&lt;/em&gt;) old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~iruczins&#34;&gt;Ingo&lt;/a&gt; says that &amp;ldquo;juvenile&amp;rdquo; is another word for &amp;ldquo;hip and dynamic,&amp;rdquo; so I guess it&amp;rsquo;s just that I&amp;rsquo;m no longer hip and dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related posts on the Hopkins SPH logo: &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/16/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-1&#34;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/21/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-2/&#34;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
