<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>posters on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/tags/posters/</link>
    <description>Recent content in posters on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT license</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/posters/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Poster flop</title>
      <link>/2011/09/30/poster-flop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/30/poster-flop/</guid>
      <description>I gave my first fancy poster yesterday, at MathBio3.
I was hoping to use the experience as an opportunity to talk about how great poster sessions can be, and to refer to Terry Speed&amp;rsquo;s old IMS bulletin column in praise of poster sessions [pdf], and then to go on to discuss how, for me, the interpersonal interactions at poster sessions are rather awkward. (For example, if you look at someone&amp;rsquo;s poster for a while, with the presenter standing there watching you, are you obliged to ask a question, or can you slink off?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first fancy poster</title>
      <link>/2011/09/16/my-first-fancy-poster/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/16/my-first-fancy-poster/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m preparing my first large-format poster (for the MathBio3 conference, here in Madison in two weeks). Previously, my posters had just been on a series of pieces of regular paper. (Consider, for example, this poster from September, 1998.) But no one does that anymore, and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to stand out as being archaic. That is, I want to pretend to be modern.
Here&amp;rsquo;s my draft: I got a LaTeX template from Śaunak Sen, which originally came from Nathaniel Johnston and uses the Beamer poster style.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
