<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>health on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/tags/health/</link>
    <description>Recent content in health on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT license</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>classifying pvc states</title>
      <link>/2024/09/28/pvc-states/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2024/09/28/pvc-states/</guid>
      <description>Following up on my post about my heart arrhythmia, and my post about my current covid infection too: yesterday I was wearing my Polar H10 chest strap and watching my PVCs on my Android app, and I noticed very frequent PVCs. My heart seemed to be alternating between bigeminy (every other beat a PVC) and trigeminy (every third beat a PVC). I was also feeling particularly crappy from the covid.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>covid is so weird</title>
      <link>/2024/09/25/covid-is-so-weird/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2024/09/25/covid-is-so-weird/</guid>
      <description>Last December, I caught COVID for the first time, and I ended up having symptoms for 14 days and continuing to test positive on at-home rapid-tests for 18 days. I was testing daily at that point, and didn&amp;rsquo;t exit isolation until day 21, after 3 days of negative tests. I think I caught the infection early, and I started on Paxlovid immediately, and sort of wonder whether the Paxlovid contributed to the infection having lasted so long.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>premature ventricular complexes</title>
      <link>/2024/09/24/premature-ventricular-complexes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2024/09/24/premature-ventricular-complexes/</guid>
      <description>This is a long story about a personal health issue, but it&amp;rsquo;s also about programming and data analysis.
PVCs Early last year, a phlebotomist at the Red Cross (where I was donating platelets), when taking my pulse, observed that my heart was doing a bit of tango: beat-beat-pause-beat-beat-pause.
I had an appointment for a physical the following week, so I asked about it there, and the nurse confirmed the strange pulse rhythm.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
