<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>crayon colors, simplified</title>
      <link>/2017/05/02/crayon-colors-simplified/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/02/crayon-colors-simplified/</guid>
      <description>Back in 2014, I’d grabbed the Crayola crayon colors from Wikipedia and made them available as part of my R/broman package.
(I wrote about it on my wordpress blog, and then again and again.)
But it’s rather tedious to grab the colors.
There’s a useful function for viewing the available colors.
library(broman) plot_crayons() But grabbing a color, say “Purple Mountain’s Majesty”, requires rather verbose code.
brocolors(&amp;quot;crayons&amp;quot;)[&amp;quot;Purple Mountain&amp;#39;s Majesty&amp;quot;] ## Purple Mountain&amp;#39;s Majesty ## &amp;quot;#9d81ba&amp;quot; This morning, it was just too much for me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>caching blogdown</title>
      <link>/2017/05/01/caching-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 00:10:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/01/caching-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>blogdown is cool, but it seems that it builds every .Rmd file every time you run build_site(), so if your site includes an analysis that takes a while…well, every time you build the site it’s going to take a while.
I had the mistaken impression that blogdown would look at the timestamps on the .Rmd and .html and only build the .html if the .Rmd file is newer, but that’s not true.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>sqlite, feather, and fst</title>
      <link>/2017/04/30/sqlite-feather-and-fst/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 14:07:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/30/sqlite-feather-and-fst/</guid>
      <description>I don’t think I’m unusual among statisticians in having avoided working directly with databases for much of my career. The data for my projects have been reasonably small. (In fact, basically all of the data for my 20 years of projects are on my laptop’s drive.) Flat files (such as CSV files) were sufficient.
But I’ve finally entered the modern era of biggish data. (Why do they call it big data?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>old posts</title>
      <link>/2017/04/30/old-posts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 10:50:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/30/old-posts/</guid>
      <description>In moving away from my old wordpress site, I thought I’d look back at some of my old posts there. Here are the most frequently visited ones.
 Better-looking LaTeX/Beamer slides, 2013-10-07
 MongoDB with D3.js, 2015-06-22
 Crayon colors in R, 2014-05-07
 apply vs for, 2013-04-02
 Thoughts on statistical consulting, 2013-04-02
 Notifications from R, 2014-09-03
 A course in statistical programming, 2012-05-25
 Row names in data frames: beware of 1:nrow, 2012-03-21</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>new blog</title>
      <link>/2017/04/29/new-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2017 08:37:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/29/new-blog/</guid>
      <description>This is the new site for my blog; source at github.
I’m going to leave my old wordpress site as it is and not try to figure out how to move things over.
I’m not been writing much recently, in part because Wordpress is such a drag to work with. The present site uses blogdown, which is a joy. See the bookdown-based documentation (currently a bit thin) plus Amber Thomas’s tutorial and the examples at github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>about</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2017 08:36:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Karl Broman is Professor in the Department of Biostatistics and Medical Informatics at the University of Wisconsin&amp;ndash;Madison; research in statistical genetics; developer of R/qtl (for R).
 Website Github Twitter Old wordpress site  The source for this site is at GitHub.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>