<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>UW on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/tags/uw/</link>
    <description>Recent content in UW on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT license</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/uw/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>wtf uw 3: faculty are an impediment</title>
      <link>/2021/05/10/wtf-uw-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/05/10/wtf-uw-3/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m in a position of great privilege: a tenured full professor with solid funding, a history of success in both methodology and collaborative research, and some well-used software packages. So it seems wrong for me to complain about a lack of respect.
When I joined the faculty at UW-Madison in 2007, I felt like the administration had our backs and the state legislators were the only ones to be concerned about.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>wtf uw 2: the new wisconsin idea is money</title>
      <link>/2021/05/07/wtf-uw-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/05/07/wtf-uw-2/</guid>
      <description>Back in 1999, when I interviewed for my first faculty job (in the biostatistics department at the Johns Hopkins School of Public Health), I got to meet with the Dean, Al Sommer. He talked about how collegial the faculty are at Hopkins, and also about his work on vitamin A, which showed that an inexpensive vitamin A supplement aimed at reducing childhood blindness had the surprising result of also reducing mortality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>wtf uw 1: how can you treat people like that?</title>
      <link>/2021/05/06/wtf-uw-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/05/06/wtf-uw-1/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m just a statistician trying to write software, devise statistical methods, and muck around with data, to help my scientific collaborators. I&amp;rsquo;ve had no formal training in the politics of higher education, or even in teaching for that matter. But ugh the shit that&amp;rsquo;s been happening around UW-Madison lately. I need to follow the example of Anatole Beck and start speaking up and speaking out.
Yvonne Kim wrote two articles in the Capital Times in the last year that really pissed me off:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chris Walker at Faculty Senate</title>
      <link>/2016/04/15/chris-walker-at-faculty-senate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/04/15/chris-walker-at-faculty-senate/</guid>
      <description>Chris Walker&amp;rsquo;s powerful speech at the Faculty Senate on 4 Apr 2016 (see &amp;ldquo;Hateful shit at UW-Madison&amp;quot;) was recorded!
You must listen to it!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Action items in response to hateful shit</title>
      <link>/2016/04/05/action-items-in-response-to-hateful-shit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/04/05/action-items-in-response-to-hateful-shit/</guid>
      <description>UW-Madison faculty got an email update from Vice Provost and Chief Diversity Officer Patrick Sims regarding the things we can do in response to the hate and bias incidents on campus.
Here are the things he had mentioned yesterday at the Faculty Senate meeting:
  Address hate/bias incidents in your curriculum to ameliorate unacceptable occurrences in our campus community.
  Look at &amp;ldquo;bullying&amp;rdquo; language as a way to address possible hate/bias incidents in the classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hateful shit at UW-Madison</title>
      <link>/2016/04/04/hateful-shit-at-uw-madison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/04/04/hateful-shit-at-uw-madison/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a privileged white male university professor. As privileged as they come, really. My father was a professor of chemistry; my mother also has an advanced degree in chemistry. The jobs I&amp;rsquo;ve held have been more about personal fulfillment than money: dancer, dance teacher, secretary for intellectual property lawyers, research and teaching assistant, professor. People assume I know what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about, even if I&amp;rsquo;m in shorts and a t-shirt.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
