<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Things that annoy me on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/categories/things-that-annoy-me/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Things that annoy me on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT license</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/things-that-annoy-me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>I thought maybe I was being paranoid</title>
      <link>/2017/01/30/i-thought-maybe-i-was-being-paranoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/01/30/i-thought-maybe-i-was-being-paranoid/</guid>
      <description>An odd thing happened to me on twitter today.
UW System had tweeted a statement from system president Ray Cross concerning Trump&amp;rsquo;s executive order banning refugees and immigrants from 7 countries. Cross&amp;rsquo;s statement is close to the most empty, useless possible such statement.
So I tweeted back, asking him to revise his statement and actually take a stand against Trump&amp;rsquo;s executive order.

Note that I mentioned not just @RayWCross and @UWSystem, but also @POTUS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Action items in response to hateful shit</title>
      <link>/2016/04/05/action-items-in-response-to-hateful-shit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/04/05/action-items-in-response-to-hateful-shit/</guid>
      <description>UW-Madison faculty got an email update from Vice Provost and Chief Diversity Officer Patrick Sims regarding the things we can do in response to the hate and bias incidents on campus.
Here are the things he had mentioned yesterday at the Faculty Senate meeting:
  Address hate/bias incidents in your curriculum to ameliorate unacceptable occurrences in our campus community.
  Look at &amp;ldquo;bullying&amp;rdquo; language as a way to address possible hate/bias incidents in the classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hateful shit at UW-Madison</title>
      <link>/2016/04/04/hateful-shit-at-uw-madison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/04/04/hateful-shit-at-uw-madison/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a privileged white male university professor. As privileged as they come, really. My father was a professor of chemistry; my mother also has an advanced degree in chemistry. The jobs I&amp;rsquo;ve held have been more about personal fulfillment than money: dancer, dance teacher, secretary for intellectual property lawyers, research and teaching assistant, professor. People assume I know what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about, even if I&amp;rsquo;m in shorts and a t-shirt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>God-awful conference websites</title>
      <link>/2015/08/05/god-awful-conference-web-sites/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/08/05/god-awful-conference-web-sites/</guid>
      <description>What do I want in a conference website? Not this.
  I want to be able to browse sessions to find the ones I&amp;rsquo;m interested in. That means being able to see the session title and time as well as the speakers and talk titles. A super-long web page is perfectly fine.
  If you can&amp;rsquo;t show me everything at once, at least let me click-to-expand: for the talk titles, and then for the abstracts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If I could do it over again, I&#39;d self-publish</title>
      <link>/2014/08/12/if-i-could-do-it-over-again-id-self-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/08/12/if-i-could-do-it-over-again-id-self-publish/</guid>
      <description>In 2009, Śaunak Sen and I wrote a book about QTL mapping and the R/qtl software. We started working on it in the fall of 2006, and it was a heck of a lot of work.
We&amp;rsquo;d talked to several publishers, and ended up publishing with Springer. John Kimmel was the editor we worked with; I like John, and I felt that Springer (or John) did a good job of keeping prices reasonable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I still don&#39;t like it</title>
      <link>/2014/02/09/i-still-dont-like-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/09/i-still-dont-like-it/</guid>
      <description>I got a book in the mail this week, a book I hadn&amp;rsquo;t ordered and would never have ordered. The publisher sent me a complimentary copy, as I&amp;rsquo;d reviewed the book proposal last year. (It&amp;rsquo;s the one where the author refused to allow me to have an electronic copy.)
Actually, I soundly trashed the proposal in my review. In the nicest possible way, of course. For example, I said:
 And then there are things that are just plain wrong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fixing a font problem for XeLaTeX</title>
      <link>/2013/10/11/fixing-a-font-problem-for-xelatex/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/11/fixing-a-font-problem-for-xelatex/</guid>
      <description>If the topic sounds boring, well, it is really boring. I write it down here in case it&amp;rsquo;s useful to someone.
I was working on a talk about git &amp;amp; GitHub, and chose a different font (Helvetica Neue, sort of the default Apple font). I think the default font for LaTeX/Beamer is a bit too tall and thin for slides. Here&amp;rsquo;s the default:
And here&amp;rsquo;s what I wanted:
But it didn&amp;rsquo;t work on unix It worked fine with XeLaTeX on my Mac, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t working in Unix, and I&amp;rsquo;d like the source to be portable to others.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complaints about the NIH grant review process</title>
      <link>/2013/10/02/complaints-about-the-nih-grant-review-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/02/complaints-about-the-nih-grant-review-process/</guid>
      <description>Earlier this week, I met with a collaborator to discuss what to do with our NIH grant proposal, whose &amp;ldquo;A1&amp;rdquo; was &amp;ldquo;unscored&amp;rdquo; (ie, the revised version, and you don&amp;rsquo;t get a third try, received a &amp;ldquo;preliminary score&amp;rdquo; in the lower half and so was not discussed by the review panel and couldn&amp;rsquo;t be funded).
NIH proposals are typically reviewed by three people and given preliminary scores on five aspects (significance, approach, investigators, environment, innovation) and overall, and the top proposals based on those scores are discussed and scored by the larger panel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>$18 for a two page PDF? I still don&#39;t get it.</title>
      <link>/2013/05/02/18-for-a-two-page-pdf-i-still-dont-get-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/05/02/18-for-a-two-page-pdf-i-still-dont-get-it/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, I saw this tweet by @Ananyo
So I clicked the link to the Nature paper and realized, &amp;ldquo;Oh, yeah. I&amp;rsquo;ve got to enter through the UW library website.&amp;rdquo;
But then I thought, &amp;ldquo;Wait&amp;hellip;$18 for a two-page Nature comment? WTF?&amp;rdquo;
So I tweeted:
And thinking about it some more, I got more annoyed, and tweeted:
And then I thought, I&amp;rsquo;ll ask Nature directly:
And they responded:
But that didn&amp;rsquo;t quite answer my question.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Methods before results</title>
      <link>/2013/04/29/methods-before-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/29/methods-before-results/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s great that, in a step towards improved reproducibility, the Nature journals are removing page limits on Methods sections:
But couldn&amp;rsquo;t they include the Methods section in the pdf for the article? For example, consider this article in Nature Genetics; the Methods section is only available in the html version of the paper. The PDF says:
Methods are important.
  They shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be separated from the main text.
  They shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be placed after the results (as so many journals, including PLoS, do).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use meaningful URLs</title>
      <link>/2013/04/10/use-meaningful-urls/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/10/use-meaningful-urls/</guid>
      <description>QR codes are stupid. See the well-known flowchart.
And I don&amp;rsquo;t like Drupal. Sites that use it often give things URLs like https://www.genetics.wisc.edu/node/577 for their seminar list.
And can we get rid of the www?
&amp;ldquo;double-u double-u double-u &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Zzz&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
URLs should be meaningful and short. I like deep hierarchies of folders, but it makes for long URLs.
URL-shorteners help, but you don&amp;rsquo;t really want to read out (or type) one of those short URLs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data science is statistics</title>
      <link>/2013/04/05/data-science-is-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/05/data-science-is-statistics/</guid>
      <description>When physicists do mathematics, they don&amp;rsquo;t say they&amp;rsquo;re doing &amp;ldquo;number science&amp;rdquo;. They&amp;rsquo;re doing math.
If you&amp;rsquo;re analyzing data, you&amp;rsquo;re doing statistics. You can call it data science or informatics or analytics or whatever, but it&amp;rsquo;s still statistics.
If you say that one kind of data analysis is statistics and another kind is not, you&amp;rsquo;re not allowing innovation. We need to define the field broadly.
You may not like what some statisticians do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What a waste of paper</title>
      <link>/2013/03/07/what-a-waste-of-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/07/what-a-waste-of-paper/</guid>
      <description>A university press asked me to review a book manuscript, and the author &amp;ldquo;has asked that we not use electronic copies.&amp;rdquo; So they&amp;rsquo;re going to send me a hard copy.
My response: &amp;ldquo;If you only give me a paper copy, I&amp;rsquo;m going to just scan it and toss the paper. That seems like a waste of time (and paper and postage).&amp;rdquo;
I should probably have said, &amp;ldquo;Then forget it.&amp;rdquo;
Their response included, &amp;ldquo;What you do with it when it arrives I am just going to take a hear-no-evil approach to.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microsoft Office</title>
      <link>/2013/01/30/microsoft-office/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/01/30/microsoft-office/</guid>
      <description>The New York Times has an article about how Microsoft will have users pay a yearly fee for MS Office, instead of buying it outright.
There&amp;rsquo;s some mention of competition from Google Docs. Why should one still use Microsoft Office? The brilliant Excel graphs!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I don&#39;t want your irrelevant communications either</title>
      <link>/2012/12/12/i-dont-want-your-irrelevant-communications-either/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/12/12/i-dont-want-your-irrelevant-communications-either/</guid>
      <description>I got some spam from Quintiles and clicked the &amp;ldquo;unsubscribe&amp;rdquo; button. The form which came up said, &amp;ldquo;I would NOT like to receive future relevant communications from Quintiles.&amp;rdquo;
I should just forget about it, but the thought of some marketing jerk writing that while preparing their crap spam just really pisses me off.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
