<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Things That Annoy Me on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/categories/things-that-annoy-me/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Things That Annoy Me on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT License</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://kbroman.org/blog/categories/things-that-annoy-me/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>I thought maybe I was being paranoid</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2017/01/30/i-thought-maybe-i-was-being-paranoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2017/01/30/i-thought-maybe-i-was-being-paranoid/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;An odd thing happened to me on twitter today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/uwsystem&#34;&gt;UW System&lt;/a&gt; had &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/UWSystem/status/826167903145775104&#34;&gt;tweeted a statement&lt;/a&gt; from system president &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/raywcross&#34;&gt;Ray Cross&lt;/a&gt; concerning Trump&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/01/27/us/politics/trump-syrian-refugees.html&#34;&gt;executive order&lt;/a&gt; banning refugees and immigrants from 7 countries. Cross&amp;rsquo;s statement is close to the most empty, useless possible such statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;tweeted back&lt;/a&gt;, asking him to revise his statement and actually take a stand against Trump&amp;rsquo;s executive order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2017/01/disappearedtweet.png&#34; alt=&#34;disappearedtweet&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that I mentioned not just &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/raywcross&#34;&gt;@RayWCross&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/uwsystem&#34;&gt;@UWSystem&lt;/a&gt;, but also &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/potus&#34;&gt;@POTUS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty minutes later, the tweet had gotten a couple of ❤️&amp;rsquo;s, and then one RT, but for some reason the tweet itself had disappeared from my twitter feed (in the app I use, &lt;a href=&#34;https://tapbots.com/tweetbot/&#34;&gt;Tweetbot&lt;/a&gt;). I looked at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman&#34;&gt;my twitter account&lt;/a&gt; in a web browser, and sure enough the tweet wasn&amp;rsquo;t there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puzzled, and knowing I hadn&amp;rsquo;t deleted the tweet, I poked around and was able to find, somehow, the URL for the original tweet, and I could see &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;the tweet&lt;/a&gt; in a browser. So it hadn&amp;rsquo;t been &lt;em&gt;deleted&lt;/em&gt;, it had just been removed from my feed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kerri_gilbert&#34;&gt;@Kerri_Gilbert&lt;/a&gt; then &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Kerri_Gilbert/status/826181462567297025&#34;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; that she could see it in her feed but not if she went to my timeline. So I wasn&amp;rsquo;t completely crazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CFlensburg/&#34;&gt;@CFlensburg&lt;/a&gt; later &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CFlensburg/status/826231062460129280&#34;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; that he could see the tweet, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CFlensburg/status/826232029549178880&#34;&gt;he&amp;rsquo;s in Australia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now my hypothesis was: someone who looks after &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/potus&#34;&gt;@potus&lt;/a&gt; had somehow suppressed my tweet. Or was I being paranoid?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick google search (for &amp;ldquo;tweet disappeared from feed&amp;rdquo;) revealed a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com&#34;&gt;Washington Post&lt;/a&gt; article from 2015-10-30, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-intersect/wp/2015/10/30/a-guide-to-why-some-activists-believe-their-tweets-are-being-censored-in-the-u-s/&#34;&gt;Tweets are disappearing on Twitter. Why?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; This seems to explain what happened: my tweet was suppressed by some kind of &amp;ldquo;abuse filter.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article is an interesting read. It describes the experience of &lt;a href=&#34;http://members.efn.org/~paulmd/&#34;&gt;Paul Dietrich&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/paulmd199&#34;&gt;@Paulmd199&lt;/a&gt;), who wrote an analysis of his situation: &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://members.efn.org/~paulmd/OwnWork/AdventuresinCensorship.pdf&#34;&gt;Adventures in Twitter Censorship.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; Also an interesting read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And note that the tweet suppression is location-specific. It&amp;rsquo;s okay for &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CFlensburg/&#34;&gt;Australians&lt;/a&gt; to read &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;the tweet&lt;/a&gt;, but Americans need to be protected from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;but-why-this-tweet&#34;&gt;But why this tweet?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;tweet of mine&lt;/a&gt; was really a pretty bland tweet. I mean, I was directly criticizing my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.med.wisc.edu/about/administration/robert-golden-md/38&#34;&gt;boss&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://chancellor.wisc.edu/about/&#34;&gt;boss&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/raywcross&#34;&gt;boss&lt;/a&gt;, and we &lt;a href=&#34;http://host.madison.com/wsj/news/local/education/university/regents-committee-passes-new-uw-madison-tenure-policy-with-changes/article_8249f119-05e7-5459-b4d8-25eab3e3882c.html&#34;&gt;just barely have tenure at Wisconsin&lt;/a&gt; anymore, so I certainly wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to be abusive. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure why I actually mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/potus&#34;&gt;@potus&lt;/a&gt;, but I figured, &amp;ldquo;What the hell.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what sort of abuse detection algorithm would decide that &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt; was abusive? If there&amp;rsquo;s an abuse filter that would suppress &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt; but not all of the actual abuse rampant on twitter&amp;hellip;well that&amp;rsquo;s bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it was that I wrote &amp;ldquo;Sad.&amp;rdquo; (I thought that was funny. And hardly abusive.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I favor the theory that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t an algorithm but rather a person: that someone is assigned to read all mentions of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/potus&#34;&gt;@potus&lt;/a&gt; and if they deem something inappropriate, they flip a switch and the tweet gets suppressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So maybe I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; paranoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I forgot to mention: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nickfleisher&#34;&gt;@NickFleisher&lt;/a&gt; had the best response to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/UWSystem/status/826167903145775104&#34;&gt;Ray Cross&amp;rsquo;s lame statement&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nickfleisher/status/826184115456143360&#34;&gt;Revise and resubmit&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;ldquo;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Action items in response to hateful shit</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2016/04/05/action-items-in-response-to-hateful-shit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2016/04/05/action-items-in-response-to-hateful-shit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;UW-Madison faculty got an email update from Vice Provost and Chief Diversity Officer Patrick Sims regarding the things we can do in response to the hate and bias incidents on campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the things he had mentioned yesterday at the Faculty Senate meeting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Address hate/bias incidents in your curriculum to ameliorate unacceptable occurrences in our campus community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Look at &amp;ldquo;bullying&amp;rdquo; language as a way to address possible hate/bias incidents in the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commit to engaging in ongoing cultural competency training. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.library.wisc.edu/lcice/&#34;&gt;Learning Communities for Institutional Change &amp;amp; Excellence (LCICE)&lt;/a&gt; as an infrastructure already provides these services campus-wide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commit to experiencing the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.library.wisc.edu/lcice/&#34;&gt;leadership institute&lt;/a&gt; and become a facilitator, carving out 10-15% of your time towards these efforts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Support the request for additional staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://campusclimate.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;the Campus Climate website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An attached letter from the Hate &amp;amp; Bias incident team added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your school/college/department can host a bystander intervention workshop on hate and bias. This workshop will provide tools for UW-Madison community members on when and how to intervene. If you would like to host a workshop, please contact &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:Joshua.johnson@wisc.edu&#34;&gt;Joshua Moon Johnson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many incidents go unreported for a variety of reasons. We encourage students and campus community members to &lt;a href=&#34;www.students.wisc.edu/reporthate&#34;&gt;report incidents of hate and bias&lt;/a&gt; to ensure that campus can best support the victim and work to prevent future incidents. We encourage you to post &lt;a href=&#34;www.students.wisc.edu/reporthate&#34;&gt;the link to report&lt;/a&gt; on your school/college/department websites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oftentimes students do not report incidents because they are unaware of the reporting process. To increase awareness of the reporting process, we encourage you to share brochures and posters with information on how and why it is important to report. These will be distributed across campus in the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Students who are victims of hate and bias incidents may need immediate support. Please be sure to refer/provide students with appropriate resources such as mental health/counseling services through University Health Services (UHS). The &lt;a href=&#34;http://msc.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;Multicultural Student Center&lt;/a&gt; also has drop-in hours with UHS counselors as well as support and discussions groups for students of color.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many students who are victims of hate and bias incidents identify with an underrepresented racial group, gender identity or sexual orientation, or religious group. We encourage you to specifically reach out to marginalized student groups to raise awareness of the bystander intervention workshop and reporting process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a reasonably positive response to &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2016/04/04/hateful-shit-at-uw-madison/&#34;&gt;my email to my faculty colleagues&lt;/a&gt; suggesting that we all commit to cultural competency training. But the training from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.library.wisc.edu/lcice/&#34;&gt;LCICE&lt;/a&gt; mentioned above looks to be semester-long, Tuesdays 4:30-7:30pm. I think I&amp;rsquo;ll have a difficult time convincing my colleagues of that. We need something in between nothing and 45 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hateful shit at UW-Madison</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2016/04/04/hateful-shit-at-uw-madison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2016/04/04/hateful-shit-at-uw-madison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a privileged white male university professor. As privileged as they come, really. My father was a professor of chemistry; my mother also has an advanced degree in chemistry. The jobs I&amp;rsquo;ve held have been more about personal fulfillment than money: dancer, dance teacher, secretary for intellectual property lawyers, research and teaching assistant, professor. People assume I know what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about, even if I&amp;rsquo;m in shorts and a t-shirt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that&amp;rsquo;s just to say that, when it comes to the ongoing hateful acts that have been happening at the University of Wisconsin-Madison, I&amp;rsquo;m really the last one that you should be listening to. You should instead listen to UW students, such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unitedcouncilofuw.org/&#34;&gt;United Council of UW Students&lt;/a&gt;, who have submitted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unitedcouncilofuw.org/the-student-voice/2016/2/24/blackout-uw-system-administration-press-release-1212016&#34;&gt;a list of 5 reasonable demands&lt;/a&gt;, or Vice Provost and Chief Diversity Officer &lt;a href=&#34;http://provost.wisc.edu/climate.htm&#34;&gt;Patrick Sims&lt;/a&gt;, who made an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zMBQUzwnCL0&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&#34;&gt;important 8-min video&lt;/a&gt; in response to a recent hateful incident that you should now go away and watch (really, stop reading what I have to say and spend 8 minutes watching that video), or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dance.wisc.edu/dance/people/faculty/chris-walker&#34;&gt;Chris Walker&lt;/a&gt;, Asst Prof in the dance department, who spoke movingly today at the UW-Madison Faculty Senate meeting about the shit that faculty and students of color have to put up with on campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lot&amp;rsquo;s of crap has been happening in Wisconsin lately. My focus has been on what Scott Walker and company have been doing to the state and to the University of Wisconsin, most recently by making huge cuts to state support to the UW System and by weakening tenure and shared governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all been an embarrassment, and depressing, but in comparison to the hateful racist shit that&amp;rsquo;s been happening on campus, and Vice Provost Sims reported that there have been &amp;gt;30 &lt;em&gt;reported&lt;/em&gt; hate or bias incidents on campus this year, tenure and funding just don&amp;rsquo;t seem that important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Walker&amp;rsquo;s speech at the Faculty Senate today really hammered this home. As a black man on campus, he&amp;rsquo;s experienced a lot of shit: worse shit then we&amp;rsquo;re seeing in the papers. And if we don&amp;rsquo;t fix this, our students can&amp;rsquo;t be successful. We &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; fix this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can a biostatistics professor do? I&amp;rsquo;m open to suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for now, I&amp;rsquo;ll follow Patrick Sims&amp;rsquo;s suggestion and start with one of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unitedcouncilofuw.org/the-student-voice/2016/2/24/blackout-uw-system-administration-press-release-1212016&#34;&gt;United Council of UW Students&amp;rsquo; demands&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;We demand that the University of Wisconsin System creates and enforces comprehensive racial awareness and inclusion curriculum and trainings throughout all 26 UW Institution departments, mandatory for all students, faculty, staff, campus &amp; system administration, and regents. This curriculum and training must be vetted, maintained, and overseen by a board comprised of students, staff, and faculty of color.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve written an email to the faculty in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;my department&lt;/a&gt;, asking that we, as a department, &lt;em&gt;volunteer&lt;/em&gt; to participate in such racial awareness training:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2016/04/email_to_dept1.png&#34; alt=&#34;email_to_dept&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Correction&lt;/strong&gt;: There&amp;rsquo;s an error in my email; Chris Walker is Associate Professor, and has been for a couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: Chris Walker&amp;rsquo;s speech at the 4 Apr 2016 Faculty Senate meeting was &lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.wisc.edu/media/Professor+Chris+Walker/1_5k9npnxs&#34;&gt;recorded&lt;/a&gt;! Must listen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>God-awful conference websites</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2015/08/05/god-awful-conference-web-sites/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2015/08/05/god-awful-conference-web-sites/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;What do I want in a conference website? Not &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org/meetings/JSM/2015/onlineprogram/index.cfm&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want to be able to browse sessions to find the ones I&amp;rsquo;m interested in. That means being able to see the session title and time as well as the speakers and talk titles. A super-long web page is perfectly fine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you can&amp;rsquo;t show me everything at once, at least let me click-to-expand: for the talk titles, and then for the abstracts. Otherwise I have to keep clicking and going back.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want to be able to search for people. And if I&amp;rsquo;m searching for &lt;a href=&#34;http://web1.sph.emory.edu/users/hwu30/&#34;&gt;Hao Wu&lt;/a&gt;, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to look at &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the Wus. Or all of the Haos. I just want the Hao Wus. If I can&amp;rsquo;t search on &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Hao Wu&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;, at least let me search on &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Wu, Hao&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If my search returns nothing and I go back, bring me back to the same search form. Don&amp;rsquo;t make me have to click &amp;ldquo;Search for people&amp;rdquo; again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to be able to form a schedule of the sessions to attend. (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org/meetings/JSM/2015/onlineprogram/index.cfm&#34;&gt;JSM2015&lt;/a&gt; does that okay, but it&amp;rsquo;s not what I&amp;rsquo;d call &amp;ldquo;secure&amp;rdquo; and you have to find the damned things, first.) Really, I want to pick particular talks: this one in that session and that one in the other. But yeah, that seems a bit much to ask.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org/meetings/JSM/2015/onlineprogram/index.cfm&#34;&gt;JSM 2015 site&lt;/a&gt; is so terrible for browsing, I was happy to get the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2015/pdfs/JSM2015_ProgramBook.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf of the program&lt;/a&gt;. (Good luck finding it on the website on your own; ASA tweeted the link to me, due to my bitching and moaning.) You can browse the pdf. That&amp;rsquo;s the way I ended up finding the sessions I wanted to attend. It also had an ad for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/628797267978289152&#34;&gt;JSM 2015 mobile app&lt;/a&gt;. Did you know there was one? Good luck finding a link to &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; on their website, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pdf is useable, but much like the website, it fails to make use of the medium. I want:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bookmarks. I want to jump to where Monday&amp;rsquo;s sessions start without have to flip through the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hyperlinks. If you don&amp;rsquo;t include the abstracts, with links from the talk titles to the abstracts, at least include links to the web page that has the abstract so I don&amp;rsquo;t have to search on the web.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;More hyperlinks. The pdf has an index, with people and page numbers. Why not link those page numbers to the corresponding page?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I helped organize a &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org/ctc2013/&#34;&gt;small meeting&lt;/a&gt; in 2013. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org/ctc2013/program.html&#34;&gt;program on the web&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org/ctc2013/ctc2013_program.pdf&#34;&gt;corresponding pdf&lt;/a&gt; illustrate much of what I want. (No scheduling feature, but that meeting had no simultaneous sessions.) I included gratuitous network graphs of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org/ctc2013/vis/authors.html&#34;&gt;authors&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org/ctc2013/vis/abstracts.html&#34;&gt;abstracts&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s 2015. No conference site is truly complete without interactive network graphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update&#34;&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stat.auckland.ac.nz/showperson?firstname=Thomas&amp;amp;surname=Lumley&#34;&gt;Thomas Lumley&lt;/a&gt; commented below, if you search on &amp;ldquo;Wu&amp;rdquo; you get all of the &amp;ldquo;Wu&amp;rdquo;s but also there&amp;rsquo;s one &amp;ldquo;Wulfhorst&amp;rdquo;. And if you search on &amp;ldquo;Hao&amp;rdquo; you get only people whose &lt;em&gt;last&lt;/em&gt; name is &amp;ldquo;Hao&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tslumley/status/629096725978845185&#34;&gt;further pointed out&lt;/a&gt; that if you search for the affiliation &amp;ldquo;Auckland&amp;rdquo; the results don&amp;rsquo;t include &amp;ldquo;University of Auckland&amp;rdquo; but only &amp;ldquo;Auckland University of Technology&amp;rdquo;. And actually, if you search for &amp;ldquo;University of Auckland&amp;rdquo; you get nothing. You need to search for &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; University of Auckland&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If I could do it over again, I&#39;d self-publish</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/08/12/if-i-could-do-it-over-again-id-self-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/08/12/if-i-could-do-it-over-again-id-self-publish/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2009, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.epibiostat.ucsf.edu/biostat/sen/&#34;&gt;Śaunak Sen&lt;/a&gt; and I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rqtl.org&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; about QTL mapping and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rqtl.org&#34;&gt;R/qtl&lt;/a&gt; software. We started working on it in the fall of 2006, and it was a heck of a lot of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;d talked to several publishers, and ended up publishing with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com&#34;&gt;Springer&lt;/a&gt;. John Kimmel was the editor we worked with; I like John, and I felt that Springer (or &lt;em&gt;John&lt;/em&gt;) did a good job of keeping prices reasonable. We were able to publish in full color with a list price of $99, so that on Amazon it was about $65. (In April, 2013, there was a brief period where &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/321747087744184320&#34;&gt;it was just $42 at Amazon&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Springer did arrange several rounds of reviews; they typically pay reviewers $100 or a few books. But the copy editing was terrible (at the very least, you want a copy editor to &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; the book, and it was pretty clear that our copy editor &lt;em&gt;hadn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt;), and the actual type-setting and construction of the index was left to us, the authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels nice to have written a proper book, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think it makes that big of a difference, for me or for readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And John Kimmel has since left Springer to go to Chapman &amp;amp; Hall/CRC, and Springer has raised the price of our book to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com/life+sciences/systems+biology+and+bioinformatics/book/978-0-387-92124-2&#34;&gt;$169&lt;/a&gt;, so it&amp;rsquo;s now selling for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0387921249/7210-20&#34;&gt;$130 at Amazon&lt;/a&gt;. I think that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;obnoxious&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s not like they&amp;rsquo;ve gone back and printed extra copies, so it&amp;rsquo;s hard to see how their costs could have gone up. But in the publishing agreement we signed, we gave Springer full rights to set the price of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: it&amp;rsquo;s now listed at $199, though it&amp;rsquo;s still about $130 at Amazon.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a hard time recommending the book at that price; I&amp;rsquo;m tempted to help people find pirated PDFs online. (And seriously, if you can&amp;rsquo;t find a pirated copy, you should work on your internet skills.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I corresponded with an editor at Springer, on why our book has become so expensive and whether there&amp;rsquo;s anything we can do about it. They responded&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we do a new edition, it could be listed as $129.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the book is adopted by university classes, &amp;ldquo;the pricing grid it is based on would have lower prices.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our book is available electronically, for purchase by chapter as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purchase by chapter? Yeah, for &lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-0-387-92125-9&#34;&gt;$30 per chapter!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Springer has &lt;a href=&#34;http://statweb.stanford.edu/~tibs/ElemStatLearn/&#34;&gt;published books and allowed the authors to post a PDF&lt;/a&gt;, but only for really big sellers, and ours is definitely not in that category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m both disgusted and embarrassed by this situation. If I could do it all over again, I&amp;rsquo;d self-publish: post everything on the web, and arrange some way for folks to have it printed cheaply.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I still don&#39;t like it</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/02/09/i-still-dont-like-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/02/09/i-still-dont-like-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got a book in the mail this week, a book I hadn&amp;rsquo;t ordered and would never have ordered. The publisher sent me a complimentary copy, as I&amp;rsquo;d reviewed the book proposal last year. (It&amp;rsquo;s the one where &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/07/what-a-waste-of-paper/&#34;&gt;the author refused to allow me to have an electronic copy&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I soundly trashed the proposal in my review. In the nicest possible way, of course. For example, I said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
And then there are things that are just plain wrong. For example, &#34;We then express our confidence in the H0 with a p-value, which might crudely be considered the probability that the H0 is true.&#34; That is not a _crude_ interpretation of the p-value; that is just _wrong_.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like if a reviewer says, &amp;ldquo;This particular book should not be adopted,&amp;rdquo; the publisher can interpret that to also mean, &amp;ldquo;and whatever you do, don&amp;rsquo;t send me a copy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fixing a font problem for XeLaTeX</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/10/11/fixing-a-font-problem-for-xelatex/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/10/11/fixing-a-font-problem-for-xelatex/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;If the topic sounds boring, well, it is really boring. I write it down here in case it&amp;rsquo;s useful to someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was working on a &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/syounkin/GitPrimer.git&#34;&gt;talk about git &amp;amp; GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, and chose a different font (Helvetica Neue, sort of the default Apple font). I think the default font for LaTeX/Beamer is a bit too tall and thin for slides. Here&amp;rsquo;s the default:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/10/slide_default.png&#34; alt=&#34;Slide with default font&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s what I wanted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/10/slide_helveticaneue.png&#34; alt=&#34;Slide with Helvetica Neue&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;but-it-didn-t-work-on-unix&#34;&gt;But it didn&amp;rsquo;t work on unix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It worked fine with XeLaTeX on my Mac, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t working in Unix, and I&amp;rsquo;d like the source to be portable to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;XeLaTex was giving two errors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Invalid fontname `Helvetica Neue&#39;, contains &#39; &#39;

Font \zf@basefont=&amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot; at 10.0pt not loadable: Metric (TFM) file
or installed font not found.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It obviously wasn&amp;rsquo;t finding the font.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I futzed about for an hour, trying to figure out where fonts are located on my Mac, and where fonts are located on Unix, and doing various web searches. But no luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-solved-the-problem&#34;&gt;How I solved the problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I read &lt;a href=&#34;http://existentialtype.net/2008/07/12/fonts-in-latex-part-one-xelatex/&#34;&gt;this post on fonts in xelatex&lt;/a&gt;, and following that set of ideas, I figured out what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switch to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gust.org.pl/projects/e-foundry/tex-gyre/heros/index_html&#34;&gt;TeX Gyre Heros&lt;/a&gt; font. It looks just like Helvetica to me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Download &lt;code&gt;[qhv2.004otf.zip](http://www.gust.org.pl/projects/e-foundry/tex-gyre/heros/qhv2.004otf.zip)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On unix, unzip the file (which contains eight &lt;code&gt;[.otf](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenType)&lt;/code&gt; files) into &lt;code&gt;~/.fonts&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Mac, unzip the file, double-click the &lt;code&gt;.otf&lt;/code&gt; files and select &amp;ldquo;Install font.&amp;rdquo;  This uses the &lt;a href=&#34;http://support.apple.com/kb/HT2509&#34;&gt;Font Book&lt;/a&gt; application.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;code&gt;.tex&lt;/code&gt; file, use &lt;code&gt;\setsansfont{TeX Gyre Heros}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not thoroughly tested, but it works on two systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complaints about the NIH grant review process</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/10/02/complaints-about-the-nih-grant-review-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/10/02/complaints-about-the-nih-grant-review-process/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, I met with a collaborator to discuss what to do with our NIH grant proposal, whose &amp;ldquo;A1&amp;rdquo; was &amp;ldquo;unscored&amp;rdquo; (ie, the revised version, and you don&amp;rsquo;t get a third try, received a &amp;ldquo;preliminary score&amp;rdquo; in the lower half and so was not discussed by the review panel and couldn&amp;rsquo;t be funded).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NIH proposals are typically reviewed by three people and given preliminary scores on five aspects (significance, approach, investigators, environment, innovation) and overall, and the top proposals based on those scores are discussed and scored by the larger panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reviewers gave our proposal an 8 for &amp;ldquo;approach&amp;rdquo; (on a scale of 1-9, with 1 being good and 9 being terrible) with the following review comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
**4. Approach:**
**Strengths**

&gt;
&gt;

&gt;   * Well described details for mining of [data] and genotyping of [subjects].
&gt;

**Weaknesses**

&gt;
&gt;

&gt;   * There is no power analysis for Aim 2. Without knowing which and how many [phenotypes] will be evaluated it is not possible to estimate the statistical power.
&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valid comments, but is that really all the reviewer had to say? What about Aims 1 and 3, or the other aspects of Aim 2? &lt;em&gt;That is totally fucking inadequate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at this review again, I was reminded of how much I despise many aspects of the NIH review process. So it&amp;rsquo;s led me, finally, to write down some of the things that annoy me.
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-scoring-system-is-too-discrete&#34;&gt;The scoring system is too discrete&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been involved in reviewing NIH grants for 15 years. A bunch of changes were made in about 2009 or so, with a few things for the better (like having the review order of grants based on preliminary score) but many for the worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst change was to the scoring system. In the old system, reviewers scored grants on a scale of 1-5, in tenths (1.0, 1.1, 1.2, &amp;hellip;), with 1 being best and 5 being worst. Scores were averaged and multiplied by 100, so the best possible score was 100 and the worst was 500. (And note that the middle value was 300 not 250, a point of confusion for many.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new system, reviewers score grants on a scale of 1-9, in single digits, with 1 being best and 9 being worst (and 5 being the middle value). Scores are averaged and multiplied by ten, so the best possible score is 10 and the worst is 90.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the new scale was introduced, we were given the following handy chart:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/10/nih_score_chart.png&#34; alt=&#34;NIH 9-point score chart&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I understand it, there were two main reasons for revising the scoring system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fix the &amp;ldquo;grade inflation&amp;rdquo; problem (too many good scores)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reviewers can&amp;rsquo;t score grants with 0.1 precision.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as a fix for the grade inflation problem, revising the scoring system could only be a temporary solution. And as I understand it, the problem is now worse than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big problem with the new scoring system is that reviewers have just 9 choices of scores, whereas before they had 41. Yes, a reviewer can&amp;rsquo;t really discriminate 1.3 from 1.4. **But if you have 25 imprecise measure instruments, would it be better to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;average and then round&lt;/em&gt;, or&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;round and then average&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s obviously better to &lt;em&gt;average and then round&lt;/em&gt;, but the new scoring system &lt;em&gt;rounds and then averages&lt;/em&gt;. (&lt;a href=&#34;http://churchill.jax.org/about/churchill.shtml&#34;&gt;Gary Churchill&lt;/a&gt; pointed this out to me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to the frequent statements like, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;d put this somewhere between a 1 and a 2.&amp;rdquo; And with line (or &amp;ldquo;band&amp;rdquo;) between funded and not funded being well above 20, it seems like, in many cases, &lt;em&gt;whether a grant is funded has to do with the proportion of reviewers that give it a 1&lt;/em&gt; rather than a 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-bullet-point-based-reviews-lead-to-superficial-and-incomplete-comments&#34;&gt;The bullet-point-based reviews lead to superficial and incomplete comments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be that the written reviews of grant proposals were much like reviews of journal articles: for each aspect of a proposal (significance, approach, etc.), we&amp;rsquo;d write a few paragraphs, in some cases a full page. Such reviews were hard to write, were often long, and sometimes didn&amp;rsquo;t do a good job of making clear what were the really important issues and what were the less important ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the big review change in 2009, reviewers were asked to write bullet points for &amp;ldquo;Strengths&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Weaknesses.&amp;rdquo; (And in a Microsoft Word template!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a lot easier to write a few bullet points than to construct coherent prose, but the bullet points that reviewers produce are generally shallow and incomplete. In some cases, a reviewer&amp;rsquo;s thinking about a proposal may be left in a shallow and incomplete state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review at the top of this post is the best (or really &lt;em&gt;worst&lt;/em&gt;) instance of this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;don-t-drop-the-proposal-summary-from-the-beginning-of-the-discussion&#34;&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t drop the proposal summary from the beginning of the discussion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, the discussion of a proposal would begin with the primary reviewer giving a brief summary: what are the investigators proposing to do? This is critical, as only 3 of the 25 or so people on the panel will have read the proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know if they&amp;rsquo;re still doing this, but with the other changes to the review process, we were asked to skip the summary of proposal and just discuss the significance of the work. But how on earth can you talk about the significance of the work without some mention of what the work actually is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-electronic-grant-format-is-often-not-human-readable&#34;&gt;The electronic grant format is often not human readable.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first reviewed NIH grant proposals, we each got a copy-paper-sized box with all of the proposals (and when proposals were triaged, all 25 reviewers would simultaneously throw the proposal into a big pile). It was great to move to electronic versions of grants (initially scanned, then fully electronic), but the electronic versions of proposals are not constructed in a way that has a human reader in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front page of grants used to be quite clear and informative, but now all of the form-generated pages are a design mess. For example, the pages listing the key personnel and their institutions are really hard to parse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there are loads of useless pages describing what documents were included. Couldn&amp;rsquo;t the reviewers get a version without all of that crap?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the PDF bookmarks are often off by a page. If you want to go to the biosketches, you need to click the biosketch bookmark and then page down one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things aren&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; big of a deal, but they&amp;rsquo;re a constant annoyance, and they should be easy to fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony Scarpa, the former director of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://public.csr.nih.gov/Pages/default.aspx&#34;&gt;NIH Center for Scientific Review (CSR)&lt;/a&gt; who was responsible for the big change in the NIH review system, once visited U Wisconsin, and I asked him about whether these electronic proposals could be improved, and he said, &amp;ldquo;Oh, that&amp;rsquo;s not us; that&amp;rsquo;s grants.gov.&amp;rdquo; So I asked who I should talk to about the issue, and he said, &amp;ldquo;Call your Congressman.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;there-needs-to-be-some-review-of-reviewers&#34;&gt;There needs to be some review of reviewers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final comment: there needs to be some formal way for reviewers to comment on other reviewers. I think most reviewers are very careful and responsible, but there&amp;rsquo;s often at least one total jerk on a review panel: didn&amp;rsquo;t read the proposal carefully, didn&amp;rsquo;t write a coherent review, didn&amp;rsquo;t pay any attention to what the other reviewers said, gave completely unfair scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There should be some system for other reviewers to say, &amp;ldquo;So-and-so on the panel was a complete jerk and shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be brought back.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>$18 for a two page PDF? I still don&#39;t get it.</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/05/02/18-for-a-two-page-pdf-i-still-dont-get-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/05/02/18-for-a-two-page-pdf-i-still-dont-get-it/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Ananyo/status/329545985149775873&#34;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Ananyo&#34;&gt;@Ananyo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Time that biologists stopped telling the public oversimplistic fairy tales on Darwinian evolution, says P Ball ($) [nature.com/nature/journal...](http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v496/n7446/full/496419a.html)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I clicked the link to the Nature paper and realized, &amp;ldquo;Oh, yeah.  I&amp;rsquo;ve got to enter through the UW library website.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I thought, &amp;ldquo;Wait&amp;hellip;$18 for a two-page Nature comment?  WTF?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/329560393922002944&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
DNA: Celebrate the unknowns, like this Nature comment, which costs $18. [nature.com/nature/journal...](http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v496/n7446/full/496419a.html)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thinking about it some more, I got more annoyed, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/329566578024775683&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Why do publishers charge such high per-article fees? At $18/artcl, you&#39;d have to be desperate or stupid to pay; at $1-2, prob&#39;ly lots would.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I thought, I&amp;rsquo;ll &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/329575795716661250&#34;&gt;ask Nature directly&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
@NatureMagazine Why is the per-article charge so high? It seems like you&#39;d make more profit at $2/article.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/NatureMagazine&#34;&gt;they&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/NatureMagazine/status/329655405355614210&#34;&gt;responded&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
@kwbroman For a while now, individual papers can be rented through @readcube for $3-5. A full tablet subscription to Nature costs $35.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that didn&amp;rsquo;t quite answer my question.  So I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/329683444051365889&#34;&gt;asked&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
.@NatureMagazine So is the $18 charge for a 2 pg PDF just to discourage piracy?
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought a lot about whether to put &amp;ldquo;piracy&amp;rdquo; in quotes or not, or whether to write &amp;ldquo;copyright infringement&amp;rdquo; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anyway, they &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/NatureMagazine/status/329692960205725696&#34;&gt;responded&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
@kwbroman just as with any product, the more you buy, the more you save. Media/publishing subscriptions have worked this way for decades.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That again didn&amp;rsquo;t quite answer my question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;it-s-a-scam&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a scam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still don&amp;rsquo;t understand the $18 business.  It&amp;rsquo;s not &amp;ldquo;The more you buy, the more you save.&amp;rdquo;  It&amp;rsquo;s, &amp;ldquo;Buy the whole season for $35, or buy 5 min from Episode 1 for $18.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that the cover price of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com&#34;&gt;Wired&lt;/a&gt; is $5 per issue, while I could get a year&amp;rsquo;s subscription for $15-20.  But that&amp;rsquo;s not the same as $18 for &lt;em&gt;one article&lt;/em&gt; vs $200 per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The $18 for a two-page PDF is like 900 numbers and paycheck advances.  These are &lt;em&gt;scams&lt;/em&gt; taking advantage of desperate or stupid people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they don&amp;rsquo;t want to sell the PDFs for individual articles for a reasonable price, they should just not sell them at all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Methods before results</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/29/methods-before-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/29/methods-before-results/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s great that, in a step towards improved reproducibility, the Nature journals are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/ng/journal/v45/n5/full/ng.2621.html&#34;&gt;removing page limits on Methods sections&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
To allow authors to describe their experimental designs and methods in enough detail for others to interpret and replicate them, the participating journals are removing length restrictions on Methods sections.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But couldn&amp;rsquo;t they include the Methods section in the pdf for the article?  For example, consider &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/ng/journal/v45/n5/full/ng.2591.html&#34;&gt;this article in Nature Genetics&lt;/a&gt;; the Methods section is only available in the html version of the paper. The PDF says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Methods and any associated references are available in the online version of the paper.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Methods&lt;/em&gt; are important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be separated from the main text.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be placed after the results (as so many journals, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosbiology.org&#34;&gt;PLoS&lt;/a&gt;, do).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be in a smaller font than the main text (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org&#34;&gt;PNAS&lt;/a&gt; does).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They certainly shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be endnotes (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/276/5316/1268.long&#34;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; used to do).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;supplements-annoy-me-too&#34;&gt;Supplements annoy me too&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love supplemental material: authors can give the full details, and they can provide as many supplemental figures and tables as they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But supplements can be a real pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to have to click on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosgenetics.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pgen.1003321#s5&#34;&gt;10 different links&lt;/a&gt;.  Put it all in one document.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to have to open Word.  Put text and figures in a PDF.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to have to open Excel.  Put data in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caitlinrivers.com/1/post/2013/04/send-me-your-data-pdf-is-fine-said-no-one-ever-how-to-share-your-data-effectively.html&#34;&gt;plain text file&lt;/a&gt;, preferably as part of a git repository with related code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least supplements are now included at the journal sites!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/19/8/956.long&#34;&gt;This paper&lt;/a&gt; in Bioinformatics refers to a separate site for supplemental information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Expression data and supplementary information are available at
http://www.rii.com/publications/2003/HE_SDS.htm.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But &lt;code&gt;rii.com&lt;/code&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist anymore.  I was able to find &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.archive.org/web/20080719125540/http://www.rii.com/publications/2003/HE_SDS.html&#34;&gt;the supplement&lt;/a&gt; using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.archive.org&#34;&gt;Wayback Machine&lt;/a&gt;, but&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The link in the paper was wrong: It should be &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt; not &lt;code&gt;.htm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final version on Wayback has a corrupted PDF, though one can go back to previous versions that are okay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-like-genetics-http-www-genetics-org-and-g3-http-www-g3-journal-org&#34;&gt;I like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org&#34;&gt;Genetics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.g3-journal.org&#34;&gt;G3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org&#34;&gt;Genetics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.g3-journal.org&#34;&gt;G3&lt;/a&gt; put the Methods where they belong (before the results), and when you download the PDF for an article in Genetics, it includes the supplement.  For a G3 article, the supplement isn&amp;rsquo;t included in the article PDF, but at least you can the whole supplement as a single PDF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, consider my recent Genetics articles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org/content/190/2/403.full&#34;&gt;Genotype probabilities at intermediate generations in the construction of recombinant inbred lines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org/content/192/1/267.full&#34;&gt;Mapping quantitative trait loci onto a phylogenetic tree&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you click on &amp;ldquo;Full Text (PDF),&amp;rdquo; you get the article plus the 3 supplemental figures and 23 supplemental tables in the former case, and article plus the 17 supplemental figures and 2 supplemental tables in the latter case.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use meaningful URLs</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/10/use-meaningful-urls/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/10/use-meaningful-urls/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/natesmoyer/qr-codes-are-stupid&#34;&gt;QR codes are stupid&lt;/a&gt;.  See the well-known &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jcolman/status/320917928881033218&#34;&gt;flowchart&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don&amp;rsquo;t like &lt;a href=&#34;http://drupal.org&#34;&gt;Drupal&lt;/a&gt;.  Sites that use it give things URLs like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.wisc.edu/node/577&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;http://www.genetics.wisc.edu/node/577&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for their seminar list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And can we get rid of the &lt;code&gt;www&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&#34;What&#39;s your web site?&#34;

&#34;double-u double-u double-u ...&#34;

&#34;Zzz...&#34;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;URLs should be meaningful and short.  I like deep hierarchies of folders, but it makes for long URLs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bitly.com&#34;&gt;URL-shorteners&lt;/a&gt; help, but you don&amp;rsquo;t really want to read out (or type) one of those short URLs.  And they tell you nothing about where they&amp;rsquo;re going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you want is something like &lt;a href=&#34;http://bcaffo.com&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bcaffo.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://stodden.net&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;stodden.net&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  Or &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rqtl.org&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But&amp;hellip;I guess you could just say &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll send you an email.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;and-customize-title&#34;&gt;And customize &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while I have your attention, note that the title of your web page shows up on Google (and at the top of the browser).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s nice to see others make use of my html code, but you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;a href=&#34;http://darwin.cwru.edu/~iyengar/publications.html&#34;&gt;leave my name in the title of your publication page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put the important words first (not like the title for my &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/People/faculty/broman.htm&#34;&gt;official page&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;), and perhaps nothing else. For example, the title &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pophealth.wisc.edu/faculty/palta&#34;&gt;shouldn&amp;rsquo;t include &amp;ldquo;Drupal&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;: Read this: &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.not-implemented.com/urls-are-for-people-not-computers/&#34;&gt;URLs are for People, not Computers&lt;/a&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could have just given the URL:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.not-implemented.com/urls-are-for-people-not-computers/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;http://www.not-implemented.com/urls-are-for-people-not-computers&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data science is statistics</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/05/data-science-is-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/05/data-science-is-statistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When physicists do mathematics, they don&amp;rsquo;t say they&amp;rsquo;re doing &amp;ldquo;number science&amp;rdquo;.  They&amp;rsquo;re doing math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re analyzing data, you&amp;rsquo;re doing statistics.  You can call it data science or informatics or analytics or whatever, but it&amp;rsquo;s still statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you say that one kind of data analysis is statistics and another kind is not, you&amp;rsquo;re not allowing innovation.  We need to define the field broadly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may not like what &lt;a href=&#34;http://amstat.org&#34;&gt;some statisticians&lt;/a&gt; do.  You may feel they don&amp;rsquo;t share your values.  They may embarrass you.  But that shouldn&amp;rsquo;t lead us to abandon the term &amp;ldquo;statistics&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What a waste of paper</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/07/what-a-waste-of-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/07/what-a-waste-of-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A university press asked me to review a book manuscript, and the author &amp;ldquo;has asked that we not use electronic copies.&amp;rdquo; So they&amp;rsquo;re going to send me a hard copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My response: &amp;ldquo;If you only give me a paper copy, I&amp;rsquo;m going to just scan it and toss the paper. That seems like a waste of time (and paper and postage).&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should probably have said, &amp;ldquo;Then forget it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their response included, &amp;ldquo;What you do with it when it arrives I am just going to take a hear-no-evil approach to.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microsoft Office</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/01/30/microsoft-office/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/01/30/microsoft-office/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com&#34;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a href=&#34;http://nyti.ms/WdR6ya&#34;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; about how Microsoft will have users pay a yearly fee for MS Office, instead of buying it outright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s some mention of competition from &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.google.com&#34;&gt;Google Docs&lt;/a&gt;. Why should one still use Microsoft Office? The brilliant Excel graphs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;As for Google, Mr. DelBene said it has not &#34;in any way diminished demand&#34; for Office because Microsoft&#39;s applications are &#34;just so far beyond the capabilities that are in those alternative products.&#34; As an example, he cited a feature in Excel that analyzes a batch of numbers selected by a user and automatically recommends the best way to represent the data in a chart.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I don&#39;t want your irrelevant communications either</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/12/12/i-dont-want-your-irrelevant-communications-either/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/12/12/i-dont-want-your-irrelevant-communications-either/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got some spam from Quintiles and clicked the &amp;ldquo;unsubscribe&amp;rdquo; button.  The form which came up said, &amp;ldquo;I would NOT like to receive future relevant communications from Quintiles.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/quintiles_sucks.png&#34; alt=&#34;Quintiles sucks&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should just forget about it, but the thought of some marketing jerk writing that while preparing their crap spam just really pisses me off.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
