<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Software on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/tags/software/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Software on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT License</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/software/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Code review</title>
      <link>/2013/09/25/code-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/25/code-review/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;There was an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/news/mozilla-plan-seeks-to-debug-scientific-code-1.13812&#34;&gt;interesting news item&lt;/a&gt; in Nature on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_review&#34;&gt;code review&lt;/a&gt;.  It describes a project by some folks at Mozilla to review the code (well, really just 200-line snippets) from 6 selected papers in computational biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are very brief quotes from &lt;a href=&#34;http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/&#34;&gt;Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~rpeng/&#34;&gt;Roger Peng&lt;/a&gt;.  I expect that the author of the item, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nature/about/editors/index.html#ErikaCheckHayden&#34;&gt;Erika Check Hayden&lt;/a&gt;, spoke to Titus and Roger at length but could just include short bits from each, and so what they say probably doesn&amp;rsquo;t fully (or much at all) characterize their view of the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Titus is quoted as follows, in reference to another scientist who retracted five papers due to an error in his code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&#34;That&#39;s the kind of thing that should freak any scientist out.... We don&#39;t have good processes in place to detect that kind of thing in software.&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roger is quoted at the end, as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&#34;One worry I have is that, with reviews like this, scientists will be even more discouraged from publishing their code.... We need to get more code out there, not improve how it looks.&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with both of them, but my initial reaction, from the beginning of the piece, was closer to Roger&amp;rsquo;s: We often have a heck of time getting any code out of people; if we are too hard on people regarding the quality of their code, they might become even less willing to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, we want people to produce good code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;that works&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;that&amp;rsquo;s readable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;that&amp;rsquo;s reusable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it would be great if, for every bit of code, there was a second programmer who studied it, verified that it was doing the right thing, and offered suggestions for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, on the other hand, it seems really unlikely that journals have the resources to do this. And I worry that a study showing that much scientific software is crap will make people even less willing to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to see the code associated with scientific articles made readily available, during the review process and beyond. But I don&amp;rsquo;t think we (as a scientific community) want to enforce rigorous code review prior to publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, on twitter, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ctitusbrown/status/382862626692149248&#34;&gt;Titus took issue&lt;/a&gt; with the &amp;ldquo;not improve how it looks&amp;rdquo; part of what Roger said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&#34;.@kwbroman @simplystats @rdpeng Please read &lt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_review&gt; you are deeply, significantly, and completely wrong about code review.&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characterizing code review as strictly cosmetic was an unfortunate, gross simplification. (And how code looks &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; important.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have enough time this morning to really clean up my thoughts on this issue, and I want to get this out and move on to reading that dissertation that I have to get through by tomorrow. So, let me summarize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want scientific code to be &lt;em&gt;well written&lt;/em&gt;: does what it&amp;rsquo;s intended to do, readable, reusable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want scientific code to be &lt;em&gt;available&lt;/em&gt;. (Otherwise we can&amp;rsquo;t verify that it does what it&amp;rsquo;s intended to do, or reuse it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we&amp;rsquo;re too hard on people for writing substandard code, we&amp;rsquo;ll discourage the availability. It&amp;rsquo;s an important trade-off.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
