<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>data analysis on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/tags/data-analysis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in data analysis on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT license</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/data-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>data analysis principles</title>
      <link>/2019/08/15/data-analysis-principles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/08/15/data-analysis-principles/</guid>
      <description>I was looking through some of my old notes and came across this list of &amp;ldquo;data analysis principles&amp;rdquo;.
answer the question understand where the data came from make a graph does the result make sense? if it seems too good to be true, it probably is form a diagnostic checklist: think of ways things could go wrong and how they might be revealed follow up on all aberrations every estimate needs an SE consider taking logs consider taking differences use common axis scales avoid normality assumptions remember Simpson&amp;rsquo;s paradox I also found this list of &amp;ldquo;key statistics concepts&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initial steps towards reproducible research</title>
      <link>/2014/12/04/initial-steps-towards-reproducible-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/12/04/initial-steps-towards-reproducible-research/</guid>
      <description>In anticipation of next week&amp;rsquo;s Reproducible Science Hackathon at NESCent, I was thinking about Christie Bahlai&amp;rsquo;s post on &amp;ldquo;Baby steps for the open-curious.&amp;rdquo;
Moving from Ye Olde Standard Computational Science Practice to a fully reproducible workflow seems a monumental task, but partially reproducible is better than not-at-all reproducible, and it&amp;rsquo;d be good to give people some advice on how to get started - to encourage them to get started.
So, I spent some time today writing another of my minimal tutorials, on initial steps towards reproducible research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;My&#34; chromosome 8p inversion</title>
      <link>/2013/05/08/my-chromosome-8p-inversion/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/05/08/my-chromosome-8p-inversion/</guid>
      <description>There was lots of discussion on twitter yesterday about Graham Coop&amp;rsquo;s paper with Peter Ralph (or vice versa), on The geography of recent genetic ancestry across Europe, particularly regarding the FAQ they&amp;rsquo;d created.
I was eager to take a look, and, it&amp;rsquo;s slightly embarrassing to say, I first did a search to see if they&amp;rsquo;d made a connection to any of my work. (I&amp;rsquo;m probably not the only one to do that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data science is statistics</title>
      <link>/2013/04/05/data-science-is-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/05/data-science-is-statistics/</guid>
      <description>When physicists do mathematics, they don&amp;rsquo;t say they&amp;rsquo;re doing &amp;ldquo;number science&amp;rdquo;. They&amp;rsquo;re doing math.
If you&amp;rsquo;re analyzing data, you&amp;rsquo;re doing statistics. You can call it data science or informatics or analytics or whatever, but it&amp;rsquo;s still statistics.
If you say that one kind of data analysis is statistics and another kind is not, you&amp;rsquo;re not allowing innovation. We need to define the field broadly.
You may not like what some statisticians do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5/9 data journalists use Excel</title>
      <link>/2013/01/15/59-data-journalists-use-excel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/01/15/59-data-journalists-use-excel/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip;if I&amp;rsquo;ve counted correctly.
I&amp;rsquo;d not heard the term &amp;ldquo;data journalist&amp;rdquo; before. It&amp;rsquo;s nice that they have an open handbook.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
