<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jobs on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/tags/jobs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Jobs on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT License</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/jobs/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiring computational biologists</title>
      <link>/2013/09/25/hiring-computational-biologists/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/25/hiring-computational-biologists/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://discovery.wisc.edu/home/morgridge/morgridge.cmsx&#34;&gt;Morgridge Institute for Research&lt;/a&gt; (MIR), a private research institute associated with UW-Madison, is looking to hire some computational folks working in biology. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/About/Jobs/adPLV77619.pdf&#34;&gt;One position&lt;/a&gt; is joint with my department,  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;Biostatistics &amp;amp; Medical Informatics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yet-another-symposium&#34;&gt;Yet another symposium&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday afternoon, they held a symposium on &amp;ldquo;Computation in Biology&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/09/computation-in-biology-agenda.pdf&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the agenda.&lt;/a&gt;) Great speakers: &lt;a href=&#34;http://faculty.biomath.ucla.edu/msuchard/&#34;&gt;Marc Suchard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://shoichetlab.compbio.ucsf.edu/&#34;&gt;Brian Shoichet&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://pages.cs.wisc.edu/~dpage/&#34;&gt;David Page&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/winston-hide/&#34;&gt;Winston Hide&lt;/a&gt;. They were asked to speak broadly about computation in biology and on the key issues for the future, and there was plenty of time for discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what MIR was hoping to get out of the symposium, but if they were looking for guidance regarding their hiring efforts, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t effective. At the beginning, the discussion was quite heated but not terribly constructive. In the middle, it became more like the usual sort of question/answer after a seminar. I must admit I didn&amp;rsquo;t stay to the end. Perhaps some important insights were gained after I left. But it seems unlikely that the symposium provided much guidance about hiring in computational biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-key-issues&#34;&gt;The key issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are what I think the key issues are, when a scientific organization is looking to hire some computational folks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you want a targeted search (for particular kinds of applications or approaches), or do you want to leave it general and just pick the best folks who apply?. (&lt;em&gt;In my experience, targeted searches don&amp;rsquo;t work as well; you miss out on some great people.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What service role is expected of the person? Do you want them to meet some particular scientists&amp;rsquo; needs, or are you going to let them do whatever they want, with the hope that they form useful (to the organization) collaborations? (&lt;em&gt;The expectations should be made explicit.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;At promotion time, who is going to evaluate the person? If it&amp;rsquo;s a separate academic department (say, Statistics, or maybe Biochemistry), do they share your organization&amp;rsquo;s values? (&lt;em&gt;Some of the best applied computational scientists may not be generating the NIH grants that a traditional biological sciences department might expect, nor the JASA or Biometrics papers that a Statistics department might expect.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Will the person have appropriate mentors? Is there anyone at the institution who really understands the nature of their position and what they need to do to succeed? (&lt;em&gt;I worry particularly about computational scientists who are isolated from their computational peers.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have any great answers, but those are the issues that I&amp;rsquo;m concerned about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;: The real point I&amp;rsquo;m trying to make: academics doesn&amp;rsquo;t do a good job of rewarding tool building (eg, software tools). It&amp;rsquo;s often viewed as better to write papers with toy implementations than to make generally useful software. That&amp;rsquo;s a real problem for computational biology, and for folks seeking to hire truly useful computational biologists.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
