<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>History on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/tags/history/</link>
    <description>Recent content in History on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT License</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://kbroman.org/blog/tags/history/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The mustache photo</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/08/28/the-mustache-photo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/08/28/the-mustache-photo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A certain photo of me has been following me around for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/pictures/moustache.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Karl with a mustache, 15 Nov 2002&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/pictures/moustache.jpg&#34;&gt;sitting on my website&lt;/a&gt;, so I suppose I have only myself to blame. I actually quite like the photo. I look happy. I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; happy. I&amp;rsquo;m not always happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s shown up in a lot of talks, particularly by &lt;a href=&#34;http://rafalab.dfci.harvard.edu/&#34;&gt;a certain friend of mine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/StrictlyStat/status/495240349225607169&#34;&gt;appeared on the seminar board&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Hopkins Biostat&lt;/a&gt; earlier this month. Perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/simplystats/status/505066800842047488&#34;&gt;still there&lt;/a&gt;. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/simplystats/status/505066800842047488&#34;&gt;My own innocent comments&lt;/a&gt; prompt some of this.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://hilaryparker.com&#34;&gt;Hilary Parker&lt;/a&gt; confirmed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[trufax -- this photo would make its way into department events all. the. time.](https://twitter.com/hspter/status/505091094804455424)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;[like if there was no pizza for computing club, &#34;no pizza&#34; would link to this photo](https://twitter.com/hspter/status/505091356822609922)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems time to tell the story behind the photo. This will probably be longer than it should be. But I&amp;rsquo;ve included photos of cats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;movember&#34;&gt;Movember&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think November, 2002, was the first time that a group of young &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Hopkins Biostat&lt;/a&gt; faculty participated in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://us.movember.com/&#34;&gt;Movember Campaign&lt;/a&gt;, in which guys shave and then grow a mustache (or moustache) for a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For various reasons, I didn&amp;rsquo;t actually participate. Among the least important: I had a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Dyke_beard&#34;&gt;Van Dyke&lt;/a&gt; at the time. It probably took me a couple of months to grow the thing, so damned if I was going to shave it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/pictures/van_dyke.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Karl with a Van Dyke beard (playing with Francis), 10 Nov 2002&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(There was a big controversy during the competition. &lt;a href=&#34;http://rafalab.dfci.harvard.edu/&#34;&gt;Rafa&lt;/a&gt; was growing an impressive handlebar mustache, but it was revealed that on weekends or when traveling, he&amp;rsquo;d grow out the bit on his chin, so that it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a proper mustache anymore. I believe he was disqualified.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-beard-trimming-incident&#34;&gt;A beard-trimming incident&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I thought the whole &lt;a href=&#34;http://us.movember.com/&#34;&gt;Movember&lt;/a&gt; thing went from Nov 1 to Nov 30. But this photo was taken 15 Nov 2002, and I recall that it was the last day of this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Hopkins Biostat&lt;/a&gt; competition. Actually, if you look at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://us.movember.com/about/history#2003&#34;&gt;history of Movember&lt;/a&gt;, it seems that &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; started in 2003, so the Hopkins guys were ahead of their time. (And surely it was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bcaffo.com/&#34;&gt;Brian&lt;/a&gt; who was responsible for this? As I recall, he was trying to introduce some Florida traditions, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mud_bogging&#34;&gt;mud bogging&lt;/a&gt; was viewed to be infeasible.) So maybe we went from Oct 15 to Nov 15?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it was the morning of 15 Nov 2002, and I had a bit of an accident with my beard trimmer – I forgot to use the guard or some such. And so I shaved off a big patch of the beard part. Well, it was the last day of the mustache competition, so I figured what the heck, I&amp;rsquo;ll shave it all off, except for the mustache. I think I was made an honorary participant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;jhsph-happy-hour&#34;&gt;JHSPH Happy Hour&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/departments/biochemistry-and-molecular-biology/&#34;&gt;Biochemistry&lt;/a&gt; graduate students organize a Happy Hour every Friday at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Biostat Faculty&lt;/a&gt; were enthusiastic participants. (As you may recall, Happy Hour was featured in the whole JHSPH logo saga; see parts &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/16/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-1/&#34;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/21/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-2/&#34;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/06/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-3-karls-revenge/&#34;&gt;three&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/pictures/moustache&#34;&gt;The photo&lt;/a&gt; was taken at Happy Hour. So that&amp;rsquo;s why I was happy. (There exists a dual photo of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~jmcgread/&#34;&gt;John McGready&lt;/a&gt;, who was a true participant in the competition. But, as I recall, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to detect the presence of a mustache in the photo of John, so it&amp;rsquo;s not gotten the same play.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;wilmer-dinner&#34;&gt;Wilmer dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may ask, &amp;ldquo;But why were you wearing a proper shirt and a sport coat? This was long after that incident with the Dean, where you were subsequently required to wear a proper shirt on a daily basis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, my wife worked at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/wilmer/&#34;&gt;Wilmer Eye Institute&lt;/a&gt;, and we were going straight from Happy Hour to dinner with a group of her colleagues. I think it was in honor of some important visitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why bring this up? Well, at the dinner, I was sitting next to &lt;a href=&#34;https://webapps.jhu.edu/namedprofessorships/professorshipdetail.cfm?professorshipID=145&#34;&gt;Oliver Shein&lt;/a&gt;, and for reasons that I suspect you can infer quite well yourself, I was unusually exuberant, and I was telling him about the mustache competition. He asked me, &amp;ldquo;Is there a prize for the winner?&amp;rdquo; And I responded, &amp;ldquo;A really bad mustache!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was then that I realized the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/profiles/results/directory/profile/0002003/oliver-schein&#34;&gt;Oliver Shein is a mustache guy&lt;/a&gt;. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-mustache-didn-t-last-long&#34;&gt;The mustache didn&amp;rsquo;t last long&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like people think I was a mustache guy myself, from that photo. But it actually lasted just the one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/pictures/karl_and_fisher.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Karl clean-shaven (with Fisher), 17 Nov 2002&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-s-really-shocking-about-the-photo&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s really shocking about the photo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure why my Hopkins friends are so fascinated by the photo. Possible explanations include&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the mustache&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;that I look happy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;that I&amp;rsquo;m wearing a shirt with a collar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;that I&amp;rsquo;m wearing &lt;em&gt;a sport jacket&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m just glad to have people thinking of me, even if I&amp;rsquo;m not entire sure what they&amp;rsquo;re thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
