<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>publishing on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/tags/publishing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in publishing on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT license</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 23:16:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/publishing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>omg, bookdown!</title>
      <link>/2017/05/31/omg-bookdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 23:16:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/31/omg-bookdown/</guid>
      <description>So I heard Yihui Xie talk about bookdown, and I read, with considerable excitement, his bookdown book. (There’s a blurb from me at Amazon saying nice things about it, after all). But I must admit that I read the book on my iPad, with my feet up. And so my understanding, while reasonably complete, was somewhat theoretical.
I mean, from my own book writing experience, I felt like, “Hell if I’m going to be writing another book.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>omg, bookdown!</title>
      <link>/2017/05/31/omg-bookdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 23:16:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/31/omg-bookdown/</guid>
      <description>So I heard Yihui Xie talk about bookdown, and I read, with considerable excitement, his bookdown book. (There&amp;rsquo;s a blurb from me at Amazon saying nice things about it, after all). But I must admit that I read the book on my iPad, with my feet up. And so my understanding, while reasonably complete, was somewhat theoretical.
I mean, from my own book writing experience, I felt like, &amp;ldquo;Hell if I&amp;rsquo;m going to be writing another book.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scholarly Publishing Symposium at UW-Madison</title>
      <link>/2014/10/30/scholarly-publishing-symposium-at-uw-madison/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/10/30/scholarly-publishing-symposium-at-uw-madison/</guid>
      <description>At the Scholarly Publishing Symposium at UW-Madison today. Has interesting list of supplemental materials, but apparently only on paper:
So here they are electronically.
  Know your Copy Rights, Association of Research Libraries
  Optimize Your Publishing, The Right to Research Coalition
  Right to Research, The Right to Research Coalition
  About SPARC (Scholarly Publishing and Academic Research Coalition)
  Open Data Factsheet, SPARC</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If I could do it over again, I&#39;d self-publish</title>
      <link>/2014/08/12/if-i-could-do-it-over-again-id-self-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/08/12/if-i-could-do-it-over-again-id-self-publish/</guid>
      <description>In 2009, Śaunak Sen and I wrote a book about QTL mapping and the R/qtl software. We started working on it in the fall of 2006, and it was a heck of a lot of work.
We&amp;rsquo;d talked to several publishers, and ended up publishing with Springer. John Kimmel was the editor we worked with; I like John, and I felt that Springer (or John) did a good job of keeping prices reasonable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I still don&#39;t like it</title>
      <link>/2014/02/09/i-still-dont-like-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/09/i-still-dont-like-it/</guid>
      <description>I got a book in the mail this week, a book I hadn&amp;rsquo;t ordered and would never have ordered. The publisher sent me a complimentary copy, as I&amp;rsquo;d reviewed the book proposal last year. (It&amp;rsquo;s the one where the author refused to allow me to have an electronic copy.)
Actually, I soundly trashed the proposal in my review. In the nicest possible way, of course. For example, I said:
 And then there are things that are just plain wrong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>$18 for a two page PDF? I still don&#39;t get it.</title>
      <link>/2013/05/02/18-for-a-two-page-pdf-i-still-dont-get-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/05/02/18-for-a-two-page-pdf-i-still-dont-get-it/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, I saw this tweet by @Ananyo
 Time that biologists stopped telling the public oversimplistic fairy tales on Darwinian evolution, says P Ball ($) nature.com/nature/journal&amp;hellip;
 So I clicked the link to the Nature paper and realized, &amp;ldquo;Oh, yeah. I&amp;rsquo;ve got to enter through the UW library website.&amp;rdquo;
But then I thought, &amp;ldquo;Wait&amp;hellip;$18 for a two-page Nature comment? WTF?&amp;rdquo;
So I tweeted:
 DNA: Celebrate the unknowns, like this Nature comment, which costs $18.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open access, animated</title>
      <link>/2012/10/25/open-access-animated/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/25/open-access-animated/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s a great interview with Jonathan Eisen and Nick Shockey on open access publishing, nicely animated by Jorge Cham, who does the Piled Higher and Deeper comic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web-enabled publishing environment</title>
      <link>/2012/10/23/web-enabled-publishing-environment/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/23/web-enabled-publishing-environment/</guid>
      <description>Karl Rohe has an interesting commentary in Amstat News this month, on how our current publishing system is obstructing research progress, and what a better future might look like.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Positive comments on peer review</title>
      <link>/2012/04/27/positive-comments-on-peer-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/27/positive-comments-on-peer-review/</guid>
      <description>We all complain about peer review, particularly when our best work is rejected by every journal from Nature Genetics down to that journal that will publish anything, so that it finally appears in a volume to honor some guy that only he will read.
However, sometimes an anonymous reviewer will identify an important flaw in a paper that you can fix before it&amp;rsquo;s published, thus saving you from potential public embarrassment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UW-Madison news item about Elsevier boycott</title>
      <link>/2012/02/21/uw-madison-news-item-about-elsevier-boycott/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/21/uw-madison-news-item-about-elsevier-boycott/</guid>
      <description>There&amp;rsquo;s an article in the UW-Madison newsletter about the Elsevier boycott. I&amp;rsquo;m quoted as follows:
 &amp;ldquo;The main issue is that scientists want their papers to be read and available, and not just to scientists at well-funded universities. We are spending, collectively, a good amount of money that goes toward profit for these journal companies, and that could be redirected.&amp;rdquo;
  At this point, Broman says scientists are in control.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I just refused an Elsevier review</title>
      <link>/2012/02/10/i-just-refused-an-elsevier-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/10/i-just-refused-an-elsevier-review/</guid>
      <description>This afternoon I refused a request from the American Journal of Human Genetics to review a paper, though the abstract was extremely interesting. AJHG is published by Elsevier, and I&amp;rsquo;d signed the declaration at http://thecostofknowledge.com to not publish or review for Elsevier journals. If only AJHG were still with the University of Chicago Press&amp;hellip;
Michael Eisen recently wrote:
 The boycott isn&amp;rsquo;t perfect. I wish they hadn&amp;rsquo;t focused exclusively on Elsevier – they are hardly the only bad actors in the field.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More on open access</title>
      <link>/2012/02/03/more-on-open-access/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/03/more-on-open-access/</guid>
      <description>I am quite persuaded by Michael Eisen&amp;rsquo;s recent comments on open access:
 &amp;hellip;it is simply unacceptable for any scientist who decries Elsevier&amp;rsquo;s actions and believes that the subscription based model is no longer serving science to send a single additional paper to journals that do not provide full OA [open access] to every paper they publish.
 But how can I do that if Genetics isn&amp;rsquo;t fully open? Genetics charges an extra $1200 to make an article open access.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paying for scholarly publications</title>
      <link>/2012/02/02/paying-for-scholarly-publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/02/paying-for-scholarly-publications/</guid>
      <description>I have a couple of papers that I should be writing, but recent discussion (the whole PIPA/SOPA thing [see Michael Eisen&amp;rsquo;s OpEd in the New York Times]; the Elsevier boycott) has turned my thoughts to publishing generally.
So I&amp;rsquo;ll take some time out (way too much time out) to comment on the value and costs of publishing and peer review, how to pay for it, PubMedCentral, etc.
The value of publishing Obviously the most important thing is to communicate the results of research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elsevier boycott</title>
      <link>/2012/02/01/elsevier-boycott/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/01/elsevier-boycott/</guid>
      <description>I expect you&amp;rsquo;ve already heard about the Elsevier boycott, started based on comments from Timothy Gowers. While he focused on his own discipline (mathematics), the boycott site now has people broken down by subject. On 1 Feb, there were 2700+ signatories, including 600+ mathematicians (but only 15 statisticians). There have been a couple of articles about this in the Chronicle of Higher Education: here and here.
I signed the boycott, and will refuse to review papers for Evilsevier journals, and will try to steer my coauthors away from them.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
