<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tenure on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/tags/tenure/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tenure on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT license</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/tenure/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Things to avoid as a new faculty member</title>
      <link>/2013/12/05/things-to-avoid-as-a-new-faculty-member/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/12/05/things-to-avoid-as-a-new-faculty-member/</guid>
      <description>The transition from graduate student or postdoc to tenure-track faculty member is hard. You discover that there are a ton of new things to learn.
Here are some thoughts on things to avoid.
You may see lots of ways in which your department could be improved; don&amp;rsquo;t try to fix all of them at once.
You may see needs for many new courses. Don&amp;rsquo;t try to develop all of them. Try to teach the same courses at least three years in a row.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to evaluate faculty?</title>
      <link>/2012/09/08/how-to-evaluate-faculty/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/09/08/how-to-evaluate-faculty/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip;rate their departments.
The tenure guidelines for the Physical Sciences Division at UW-Madison include the following instructions (see section J-1 on page 12):
Provide a list of the five leading institutions for research (and outreach/extension activities) in the candidate&amp;rsquo;s discipline. The committee recognizes that the best work in the candidate&amp;rsquo;s specialty may not be carried out at the top ranked institutions in the broader discipline. However, it will look for a balance of evaluations from referees at the leading institutions who can evaluate the research and its impact on the broader field, and from the leaders in the subfield if they are at different institutions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
