<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>data visualization on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>https://kbroman.org/blog/tags/data-visualization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in data visualization on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT License</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 May 2017 16:22:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://kbroman.org/blog/tags/data-visualization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>updating d3panels and R/qtlcharts for D3 version 4</title>
      <link>https://kbroman.org/blog/2017/05/11/updating-d3panels-and-r/qtlcharts-for-d3-version-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2017 16:22:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kbroman.org/blog/2017/05/11/updating-d3panels-and-r/qtlcharts-for-d3-version-4/</guid>
      <description>I just spent some time updating my d3panels library and R/qtlcharts package for D3 version 4. It took just about a day, and the majority of the time was spent puzzling over d3-force and d3-brush.
(Note that I just barely know what I’m doing, by which I mean I don’t know what I’m doing. I’m able to get things to work, but I don’t always know why.)
I was very glad that I’d written a bunch of tests, because I could use those to figure out what was working and what was not working, and whether my changes were effective.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>crayon colors, simplified</title>
      <link>https://kbroman.org/blog/2017/05/02/crayon-colors-simplified/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kbroman.org/blog/2017/05/02/crayon-colors-simplified/</guid>
      <description>Back in 2014, I’d grabbed the Crayola crayon colors from Wikipedia and made them available as part of my R/broman package.
(I wrote about it on previously, and then again and again.)
But using my package to get the crayon colors can be rather tedious.
It’s easy to view the available colors.
library(broman) plot_crayons() But grabbing a color, say “Purple Mountain’s Majesty”, requires rather verbose code.
brocolors(&amp;quot;crayons&amp;quot;)[&amp;quot;Purple Mountain&amp;#39;s Majesty&amp;quot;] ## Purple Mountain&amp;#39;s Majesty ## &amp;quot;#9d81ba&amp;quot; This morning, it was just too much for me.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>