<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>graphics on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/tags/graphics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in graphics on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT license</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 20:05:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/graphics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>halloween 2017</title>
      <link>/2017/10/31/halloween-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 20:05:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/31/halloween-2017/</guid>
      <description>It was easier than ever to count trick-or-treaters this year; there were just 6 groups of kids, for a total of 18, and 12 of them came within 2 minutes (a group of 8 girls followed immediately by a group of 4 girls). Here’s a graph; compare it to 2016 and 2011.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Halloween 2016 count</title>
      <link>/2016/10/31/halloween-2016-count/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/10/31/halloween-2016-count/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s a graph of the numbers of trick-or-treat-ers we saw this evening, by time. 10 of the 25 kids arrived in one big group. (Compare this to our 2011 experience.)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MongoDB with D3.js</title>
      <link>/2015/06/22/mongodb-with-d3-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/06/22/mongodb-with-d3-js/</guid>
      <description>I consider interactive data visualization to be the critical tool for exploration of high-dimensional data.
That&amp;rsquo;s led me to spend a good amount of time in the last few years learning some new skills (D3 and CoffeeScript) and developing some new tools, particularly the R package R/qtlcharts, which provides interactive versions of the many data visualizations in R/qtl, my long-in-development R package for mapping genetic loci (called quantitative trait loci, QTL) that underlie complex trait variation in experimental organisms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Car crash stats revisited: My measurement errors</title>
      <link>/2014/11/03/car-crash-stats-revisited-my-measurement-errors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/11/03/car-crash-stats-revisited-my-measurement-errors/</guid>
      <description>Last week, I created revised versions of graphs of car crash statistics by state (including an interactive version), from a post by Mona Chalabi at 538.
Since I was working on those at the last minute in the middle of the night, to be included as an example in a lecture on creating effective figures and tables, I just read the data off printed versions of the bar charts, using a ruler.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive plot of car crash stats</title>
      <link>/2014/10/30/interactive-plot-of-car-crash-stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/10/30/interactive-plot-of-car-crash-stats/</guid>
      <description>I spent the afternoon making a D3-based interactive version of the graphs of car crash statistics by state that I&amp;rsquo;d discussed yesterday: my attempt to improve on the graphs in Mona Chalabi&amp;rsquo;s post at 538.
See it in action here.
Code on github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improved graphs of car crash stats</title>
      <link>/2014/10/29/improved-graphs-of-car-crash-stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/10/29/improved-graphs-of-car-crash-stats/</guid>
      <description>Last week, Mona Chalabi wrote an interesting post on car crash statistics by state, at fivethirtyeight.com.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t like the figures so much, though. There were a number of them like this:
I&amp;rsquo;m giving a talk today about data visualization [slides | github], and I thought this would make a good example, so I spent some time creating versions that I like better.
There are two basic issues with Mona Chalabi&amp;rsquo;s graphs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing an R package&#39;s interactive graphs</title>
      <link>/2014/08/01/testing-an-r-packages-interactive-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/08/01/testing-an-r-packages-interactive-graphs/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on an R package, R/qtlcharts, with D3-based interactive graphs for quantitative trait locus mapping experiments.
Testing the interactive charts it produces is a bit of a pain. It seems like I pretty much have to just open a series of examples in a web browser and tab through them manually, checking that they look okay, that the interactions seem to work, and that they&amp;rsquo;re not giving any sort of errors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014 UseR conference, days 1-2</title>
      <link>/2014/07/02/2014-user-conference-days-1-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/07/02/2014-user-conference-days-1-2/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m at UCLA for the UseR Conference. I attended once before, and I really enjoyed it. And I&amp;rsquo;m really enjoying this one. I&amp;rsquo;m learning a ton, and I find the talks very inspiring.
In my comments below, I give short shrift to some speakers (largely by not having attended their talks), and I&amp;rsquo;m critical in some places about the conference organization. Having co-organized a small conference last year, I appreciate the difficulties.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Further points on crayon colors</title>
      <link>/2014/05/09/further-points-on-crayon-colors/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/05/09/further-points-on-crayon-colors/</guid>
      <description>I saw this great post on crayola crayon colors at the Learning R blog, reproducing a nice graph of the Crayola crayon colors over time. (Also see this even nicer version.)
The Learning R post shows how to grab the crayon colors from the wikipedia page, &amp;ldquo;List of Crayola crayon colors,&amp;rdquo; directly in R. Here&amp;rsquo;s the code (after some slight modifications due to changes in the page since 2010):
library(XML) theurl &amp;lt;- &amp;#34;https://en.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two more points about crayon colors</title>
      <link>/2014/05/08/two-more-points-about-crayon-colors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/05/08/two-more-points-about-crayon-colors/</guid>
      <description>If you want to use crayon colors in R but you don&amp;rsquo;t want to rely on my R/broman package, you can just grab the code. Copy the relevant lines from the R/brocolors.R file:
crayons = c(&amp;#34;Almond&amp;#34;=&amp;#34;#efdecd&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Antique Brass&amp;#34;=&amp;#34;#cd9575&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Apricot&amp;#34;=&amp;#34;#fdd9b5&amp;#34;, ... &amp;#34;Yellow Green&amp;#34;=&amp;#34;#c5e384&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Yellow Orange&amp;#34;=&amp;#34;#ffb653&amp;#34;) I spent a bit of time thinking about how best to sort the colors in a meaningful way, for the plot_crayons() function. But then decided to stop thinking and just do something brainless: measure distance between colors by RMS difference of the RGB values, and then use hierarchical clustering.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crayon colors in R</title>
      <link>/2014/05/07/crayon-colors-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/05/07/crayon-colors-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Last night I was working on a talk on creating effective graphs. Mostly, I needed to update the colors, as there&amp;rsquo;d been some gaudy ones in its previous form (e.g., slide 22).
I usually pick colors using the crayons in the Mac Color Picker. But that has just 40 crayons, and I wanted more choices.
That led me to the list of Crayola crayon colors on wikipedia. I wrote a ruby script to grab the color names and codes and added them to my R/broman package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data structures are important</title>
      <link>/2013/03/19/data-structures-are-important/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/19/data-structures-are-important/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve created another D3 example, of QTL analysis for a phenotype measured over time. (Click on the image for the interactive version.)
The code is on github. It took me about a day.
The hardest part was figuring out the right data structures. A pixel here is linked to curves over there and over there and over there. You need to set things up so it&amp;rsquo;s easy to traverse such linkages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why aren&#39;t all of our graphs interactive?</title>
      <link>/2013/03/16/why-arent-all-of-our-graphs-interactive/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/16/why-arent-all-of-our-graphs-interactive/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve come to believe that, for high-dimensional data, visualizations (aka graphs), and particularly interactive graphs, can be more important than precise statistical inference.
We first need to be able to view and explore the data, and when it is unusually abundant, that is especially hard. This was a primary contributor to my recent embarrassments, in which clear problems in the data were not discovered when they should have been.
I gave a talk on interactive graphs (with the title above) at Johns Hopkins last fall, and then a related talk at ENAR earlier this week, and I have a few thoughts to add here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive eQTL plot with d3.js</title>
      <link>/2013/03/06/interactive-eqtl-plot-with-d3-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/06/interactive-eqtl-plot-with-d3-js/</guid>
      <description>I just finished an interactive eQTL plot using D3, in preparation for my talk on interactive graphics at the ENAR meeting next week.
The code (in CoffeeScript) is available at github. But beware: it&amp;rsquo;s pretty awful.
The hardest part was setting up the data files. Well, that plus the fact that I just barely know what I&amp;rsquo;m doing in D3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive MA plot</title>
      <link>/2013/02/11/interactive-ma-plot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/11/interactive-ma-plot/</guid>
      <description>The New York Times has an interesting interactive graphic on boys&amp;rsquo; and girls&amp;rsquo; average scores on a science exam, by country.
It&amp;rsquo;s nice to see a scatterplot. (Often one would see just a bar plot, with female and male bars side-by-side.) Even better, this is an &amp;ldquo;MA plot.&amp;rdquo; That is, rather than just plot males vs females, they show the difference vs the average.
The wikipedia entry for MA plot says such a plot of difference vs average is in medical statistics known as a Bland-Altman plot and in other fields is known as a Tukey mean-difference plot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive graphics with d3.js</title>
      <link>/2013/02/08/interactive-graphics-with-d3-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/08/interactive-graphics-with-d3-js/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m making some progress learning D3 (for interactive graphics), by which I mean I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten a couple of examples to work.
Many box plots First, an example for displaying many distributions. Here I&amp;rsquo;m considering a set of nearly 500 gene expression microarrays, each with 40,000 or so measurements. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to look at 500 box plots side-by-side, and with 40k measurements, traditional box plots don&amp;rsquo;t give enough information about the tails.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microsoft Office</title>
      <link>/2013/01/30/microsoft-office/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/01/30/microsoft-office/</guid>
      <description>The New York Times has an article about how Microsoft will have users pay a yearly fee for MS Office, instead of buying it outright.
There&amp;rsquo;s some mention of competition from Google Docs. Why should one still use Microsoft Office? The brilliant Excel graphs!
As for Google, Mr. DelBene said it has not &amp;ldquo;in any way diminished demand&amp;rdquo; for Office because Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s applications are &amp;ldquo;just so far beyond the capabilities that are in those alternative products.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Curved arrows in R</title>
      <link>/2012/10/11/curved-arrows-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/11/curved-arrows-in-r/</guid>
      <description>I briefly investigated how to draw curved arrows in R. Here&amp;rsquo;s a small piece of the figure that I ultimately created:
A google search for &amp;ldquo;curved arrows in R&amp;rdquo; revealed three options:
curvedarrow in the diagram package
The internal function igraph.Arrows within the igraph package (mentioned by Gabor Csardi in R help)
Using xspline for the shaft and adding the head &amp;ldquo;by hand&amp;rdquo; (mentioned by Greg Snow)
I wasn&amp;rsquo;t too happy with how the arrow heads looked using the diagram package, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to have to fiddle around with xspline, and igraph worked quite easily, so I went with that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Odd smoother</title>
      <link>/2012/09/27/odd-smoother/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/09/27/odd-smoother/</guid>
      <description>I was flipping though the contents of G3 and saw this paper, which includes Jim Cheverud as an author.
I poked through the paper, and my eye was attracted to the following figure. These are supposed to be functions, but some weird smoother was used, and the results are not functions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hilarious graph</title>
      <link>/2012/09/11/hilarious-graph/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/09/11/hilarious-graph/</guid>
      <description>I read an interesting post on the NY Times site this morning, which said:
Analyzing data from the 2008 American National Election Study, we found no relationship between negative feelings toward African-Americans and opposition to government-provided health care among whites without college degrees. For college-educated whites, however, negative racial feelings were strongly associated with increased opposition to such reform. As the graph below shows, for whites without college degrees, feelings toward African-Americans are unrelated to whether respondents support or oppose government-provided health care.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning a new language</title>
      <link>/2012/06/21/learning-a-new-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/06/21/learning-a-new-language/</guid>
      <description>It had been a very long time since I&amp;rsquo;d tried to learn a new programming language. I started C in 1987, S in 1992, and Perl in 1997, but nothing really new in the subsequent 15 years.
A friend now has me doing D, wanting to find time to learn ruby, and, most recently, playing with JavaScript and D3.
I&amp;rsquo;m really excited about D3. It&amp;rsquo;s long past time for dynamic, interactive graphics to be routine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trees</title>
      <link>/2012/05/17/trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/05/17/trees/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m frequently picking pieces of paper up off the floor &amp;ndash; bits of the kids&amp;rsquo; artwork. Today I found one with this:
That&amp;rsquo;s actually mine, so I thought I&amp;rsquo;d share it. Here&amp;rsquo;s a link to the full page.
These scratchings are related to a bit of theory I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on (with considerable help), regarding phylogenetic trees. It&amp;rsquo;s part of this paper, which I&amp;rsquo;m getting ready to re-submit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microarrays suck</title>
      <link>/2012/04/25/microarrays-suck/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/25/microarrays-suck/</guid>
      <description>Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s just that I&amp;rsquo;m stupid and haven&amp;rsquo;t been paying proper attention to Rafa&amp;rsquo;s work in the past decade, but microarray data have really been kicking my ass the last few weeks. Here are a few of the lessons that I&amp;rsquo;ve re-learned.
Lesson 1: What the hell is that? Many (or all) of my interesting findings have been completely fortuitous results of exploring apparent artifacts in data (autozygosity in the CEPH families, a large, common human inversion polymorphism, and most recently sample mixups).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Halloween 2011 count</title>
      <link>/2011/10/31/halloween-2011-count/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/31/halloween-2011-count/</guid>
      <description>We don&amp;rsquo;t get many kids seeking candy at our house. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if there just aren&amp;rsquo;t many kids in the neighborhood, or if it&amp;rsquo;s our location (next to the pond, with a big gap before the next house).
I decided to keep track. As usual, we bought a huge bag of candy, and we still had about half of it left to hand out tonight. But only 19 kids came.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Infographic</title>
      <link>/2011/09/22/infographics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/22/infographics/</guid>
      <description>I saw this great infographic at Andrew Gelman&amp;rsquo;s blog:
I&amp;rsquo;m inclined to buy an art print.
Note the relationship between the central panel and the cover of the latest Amstat News (always a good source for embarrassing figures):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick labels within figures</title>
      <link>/2011/08/26/quick-labels-within-figures-done-right/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/26/quick-labels-within-figures-done-right/</guid>
      <description>One of the coolest R packages I heard about at the useR! Conference: Toby Dylan Hocking&amp;rsquo;s directlabels package for putting labels directly next to the relevant curves or point clouds in a figure.
I think I first learned about this idea from Andrew Gelman: that a separate legend requires a lot of back-and-forth glances, so it&amp;rsquo;s better to put the labels right by the relevant bits. For example, like this:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>useR! Conference 2011 highlights</title>
      <link>/2011/08/20/user-conference-2011-highlights/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/20/user-conference-2011-highlights/</guid>
      <description>I was at the useR! Conference at The University of Warwick in Coventry, UK, last week. My goal in going was to learn the latest things regarding (simple) dynamic graphics, (simple) web-based apps, parallel computing, and memory management (dealing with big data sets). I got just what I was hoping for and more. There are a lot of useful tools available that I want to adopt. I&amp;rsquo;ll summarize the high points below, with the particular areas of interest to me covered more exhaustively than just &amp;ldquo;highlights&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
