<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Stupid on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/tags/stupid/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Stupid on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT License</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://kbroman.org/blog/tags/stupid/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>I thought maybe I was being paranoid</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2017/01/30/i-thought-maybe-i-was-being-paranoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2017/01/30/i-thought-maybe-i-was-being-paranoid/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;An odd thing happened to me on twitter today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/uwsystem&#34;&gt;UW System&lt;/a&gt; had &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/UWSystem/status/826167903145775104&#34;&gt;tweeted a statement&lt;/a&gt; from system president &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/raywcross&#34;&gt;Ray Cross&lt;/a&gt; concerning Trump&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/01/27/us/politics/trump-syrian-refugees.html&#34;&gt;executive order&lt;/a&gt; banning refugees and immigrants from 7 countries. Cross&amp;rsquo;s statement is close to the most empty, useless possible such statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;tweeted back&lt;/a&gt;, asking him to revise his statement and actually take a stand against Trump&amp;rsquo;s executive order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2017/01/disappearedtweet.png&#34; alt=&#34;disappearedtweet&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that I mentioned not just &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/raywcross&#34;&gt;@RayWCross&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/uwsystem&#34;&gt;@UWSystem&lt;/a&gt;, but also &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/potus&#34;&gt;@POTUS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty minutes later, the tweet had gotten a couple of ❤️&amp;rsquo;s, and then one RT, but for some reason the tweet itself had disappeared from my twitter feed (in the app I use, &lt;a href=&#34;https://tapbots.com/tweetbot/&#34;&gt;Tweetbot&lt;/a&gt;). I looked at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman&#34;&gt;my twitter account&lt;/a&gt; in a web browser, and sure enough the tweet wasn&amp;rsquo;t there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puzzled, and knowing I hadn&amp;rsquo;t deleted the tweet, I poked around and was able to find, somehow, the URL for the original tweet, and I could see &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;the tweet&lt;/a&gt; in a browser. So it hadn&amp;rsquo;t been &lt;em&gt;deleted&lt;/em&gt;, it had just been removed from my feed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kerri_gilbert&#34;&gt;@Kerri_Gilbert&lt;/a&gt; then &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Kerri_Gilbert/status/826181462567297025&#34;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; that she could see it in her feed but not if she went to my timeline. So I wasn&amp;rsquo;t completely crazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CFlensburg/&#34;&gt;@CFlensburg&lt;/a&gt; later &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CFlensburg/status/826231062460129280&#34;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; that he could see the tweet, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CFlensburg/status/826232029549178880&#34;&gt;he&amp;rsquo;s in Australia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now my hypothesis was: someone who looks after &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/potus&#34;&gt;@potus&lt;/a&gt; had somehow suppressed my tweet. Or was I being paranoid?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick google search (for &amp;ldquo;tweet disappeared from feed&amp;rdquo;) revealed a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com&#34;&gt;Washington Post&lt;/a&gt; article from 2015-10-30, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-intersect/wp/2015/10/30/a-guide-to-why-some-activists-believe-their-tweets-are-being-censored-in-the-u-s/&#34;&gt;Tweets are disappearing on Twitter. Why?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; This seems to explain what happened: my tweet was suppressed by some kind of &amp;ldquo;abuse filter.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article is an interesting read. It describes the experience of &lt;a href=&#34;http://members.efn.org/~paulmd/&#34;&gt;Paul Dietrich&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/paulmd199&#34;&gt;@Paulmd199&lt;/a&gt;), who wrote an analysis of his situation: &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://members.efn.org/~paulmd/OwnWork/AdventuresinCensorship.pdf&#34;&gt;Adventures in Twitter Censorship.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; Also an interesting read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And note that the tweet suppression is location-specific. It&amp;rsquo;s okay for &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CFlensburg/&#34;&gt;Australians&lt;/a&gt; to read &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;the tweet&lt;/a&gt;, but Americans need to be protected from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;but-why-this-tweet&#34;&gt;But why this tweet?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;tweet of mine&lt;/a&gt; was really a pretty bland tweet. I mean, I was directly criticizing my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.med.wisc.edu/about/administration/robert-golden-md/38&#34;&gt;boss&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://chancellor.wisc.edu/about/&#34;&gt;boss&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/raywcross&#34;&gt;boss&lt;/a&gt;, and we &lt;a href=&#34;http://host.madison.com/wsj/news/local/education/university/regents-committee-passes-new-uw-madison-tenure-policy-with-changes/article_8249f119-05e7-5459-b4d8-25eab3e3882c.html&#34;&gt;just barely have tenure at Wisconsin&lt;/a&gt; anymore, so I certainly wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to be abusive. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure why I actually mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/potus&#34;&gt;@potus&lt;/a&gt;, but I figured, &amp;ldquo;What the hell.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what sort of abuse detection algorithm would decide that &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt; was abusive? If there&amp;rsquo;s an abuse filter that would suppress &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/826174494096109568&#34;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt; but not all of the actual abuse rampant on twitter&amp;hellip;well that&amp;rsquo;s bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it was that I wrote &amp;ldquo;Sad.&amp;rdquo; (I thought that was funny. And hardly abusive.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I favor the theory that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t an algorithm but rather a person: that someone is assigned to read all mentions of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/potus&#34;&gt;@potus&lt;/a&gt; and if they deem something inappropriate, they flip a switch and the tweet gets suppressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So maybe I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; paranoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I forgot to mention: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nickfleisher&#34;&gt;@NickFleisher&lt;/a&gt; had the best response to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/UWSystem/status/826167903145775104&#34;&gt;Ray Cross&amp;rsquo;s lame statement&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nickfleisher/status/826184115456143360&#34;&gt;Revise and resubmit&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;ldquo;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Write unit tests!</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2015/12/07/write-unit-tests/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2015/12/07/write-unit-tests/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2000, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org&#34;&gt;R/qtl&lt;/a&gt;, an R package for mapping the genetic loci (called quantitative trait loci, QTL) that contribute to variation in quantitative traits in experimental crosses. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/publications/rqtl.pdf&#34;&gt;Bioinformatics paper about it&lt;/a&gt; is my most cited; also see my 2014 JORS paper, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/publications/rqtl_14yrs.pdf&#34;&gt;Fourteen years of R/qtl: Just barely sustainable&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a bit of a miracle that R/qtl works and gives the right answers, as it includes essentially no formal tests. The only regular tests are that the examples in the help files don&amp;rsquo;t produce any errors that halt the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been working on &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/qtl2&#34;&gt;R/qtl2&lt;/a&gt;, a reimplementation of R/qtl to better handle high-dimensional data and more complex crosses, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org/content/190/2/437.short&#34;&gt;Diversity Outbred mice&lt;/a&gt;. In doing so, I&amp;rsquo;m trying to make use of the software engineering principles that I&amp;rsquo;ve learned over the last 15 years, which pretty much correspond to the ideas in &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.1001745&#34;&gt;Best Practices for Scientific Computing&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.third-bit.com/&#34;&gt;Greg Wilson&lt;/a&gt; et al., PLOS Biology 12(1): e1001745, &lt;a href=&#34;http://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1001745&#34;&gt;doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.1001745&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still working on &amp;ldquo;Make names consistent, distinctive, and meaningful&amp;rdquo;, but I&amp;rsquo;m doing pretty well on writing shorter functions with less repeated code, and &lt;em&gt;particularly importantly&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m writing extensive unit tests.
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is to break up your code into small functions that ideally do just one thing. (These are the &amp;ldquo;units&amp;rdquo;.) And then write tests that explicitly check whether those functions are giving the correct answers. That is, don&amp;rsquo;t just test that the code &lt;em&gt;runs&lt;/em&gt;; you want to know that your code is &lt;em&gt;giving the right answers&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, I was working on implementing a basic genome scan function. I included the option of doing weighted least squares with known weights, because it&amp;rsquo;s easy enough to do, and R/qtl had done that. (I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; that feature, but it&amp;rsquo;s been there.) And my results were matching those that R/qtl provided. Well, mostly: in the case of multiple phenotypes, with some phenotypes having missing values, and when doing a weighted analysis, the results from R/qtl and R/qtl2 were quite different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect you may be questioning the logic of testing code by comparing it to software that has not been formally tested. I was thinking the same thing. And so I wrote some tests that compared results to those using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;lm()&lt;/code&gt; function. And (surprise) the results from &lt;code&gt;lm()&lt;/code&gt; matched R/qtl2 but not R/qtl. So it was R/qtl that was the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that had me debugging the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/qtl/blob/master/R/scanone.R&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;scanone&lt;/code&gt; function in R/qtl&lt;/a&gt;, the R code for which is &lt;strong&gt;831&lt;/strong&gt; lines long and was written according to the principle, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll just add this one thing and then clean things up later,&amp;rdquo; with &amp;ldquo;later&amp;rdquo; really meaning &amp;ldquo;never&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;this one thing&amp;rdquo; really meaning &amp;ldquo;all the things.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did, after resorting to a bunch of print/cat statements, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/qtl/commit/254a1c728&#34;&gt;find the bug&lt;/a&gt;. In subsetting the data to remove individuals with missing values, I&amp;rsquo;d forgotten to subset the weights. Back in 2012, I&amp;rsquo;d &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/qtl/commit/a07c575&#34;&gt;fixed a related bug&lt;/a&gt;, but apparently it was only a partial fix. In thinking about the bug again while writing this post, and in looking back at the 2012 bug fix, I realized that I probably had the same bug in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/qtl/blob/master/R/scantwo.R&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;scantwo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (which is &lt;strong&gt;1443&lt;/strong&gt; lines long). Sure enough, and so now there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/qtl/commit/c71b3dfce9&#34;&gt;yet another bug fix&lt;/a&gt;, though not yet on &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://thebird.nl/&#34;&gt;Pjotr Prins&lt;/a&gt; was the first to encourage me towards software testing. &lt;a href=&#34;http://had.co.nz/&#34;&gt;Hadley Wickham&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hadley/testthat&#34;&gt;testthat&lt;/a&gt; package makes it easy to do in R packages. In his &lt;a href=&#34;https://journal.r-project.org/archive/2011-1/RJournal_2011-1_Wickham.pdf&#34;&gt;paper about testthat&lt;/a&gt;, Hadley wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;It&#39;s not that we don&#39;t test our code, it&#39;s that we don&#39;t store our tests so they can be re-run automatically.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my favorite comment on testing; it totally applies to (old) me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Write unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you find a bug, first write a test for it and then fix the bug.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you find a bug, look for other possible instances of that bug, and fix them too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more about testing in R packages, see the &lt;a href=&#34;http://r-pkgs.had.co.nz/tests.html&#34;&gt;Testing&lt;/a&gt; chapter in Hadley&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1491910593/7210-20&#34;&gt;R packages book&lt;/a&gt;. Also see the &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/Tools4RR/assets/lectures/09_testdebug_withnotes.pdf&#34;&gt;slides for my lecture on testing and debugging&lt;/a&gt; in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/Tools4RR/&#34;&gt;Tools for Reproducible Research&lt;/a&gt; course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>God-awful conference websites</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2015/08/05/god-awful-conference-web-sites/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2015/08/05/god-awful-conference-web-sites/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;What do I want in a conference website? Not &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org/meetings/JSM/2015/onlineprogram/index.cfm&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want to be able to browse sessions to find the ones I&amp;rsquo;m interested in. That means being able to see the session title and time as well as the speakers and talk titles. A super-long web page is perfectly fine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you can&amp;rsquo;t show me everything at once, at least let me click-to-expand: for the talk titles, and then for the abstracts. Otherwise I have to keep clicking and going back.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want to be able to search for people. And if I&amp;rsquo;m searching for &lt;a href=&#34;http://web1.sph.emory.edu/users/hwu30/&#34;&gt;Hao Wu&lt;/a&gt;, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to look at &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the Wus. Or all of the Haos. I just want the Hao Wus. If I can&amp;rsquo;t search on &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Hao Wu&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;, at least let me search on &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Wu, Hao&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If my search returns nothing and I go back, bring me back to the same search form. Don&amp;rsquo;t make me have to click &amp;ldquo;Search for people&amp;rdquo; again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to be able to form a schedule of the sessions to attend. (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org/meetings/JSM/2015/onlineprogram/index.cfm&#34;&gt;JSM2015&lt;/a&gt; does that okay, but it&amp;rsquo;s not what I&amp;rsquo;d call &amp;ldquo;secure&amp;rdquo; and you have to find the damned things, first.) Really, I want to pick particular talks: this one in that session and that one in the other. But yeah, that seems a bit much to ask.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org/meetings/JSM/2015/onlineprogram/index.cfm&#34;&gt;JSM 2015 site&lt;/a&gt; is so terrible for browsing, I was happy to get the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2015/pdfs/JSM2015_ProgramBook.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf of the program&lt;/a&gt;. (Good luck finding it on the website on your own; ASA tweeted the link to me, due to my bitching and moaning.) You can browse the pdf. That&amp;rsquo;s the way I ended up finding the sessions I wanted to attend. It also had an ad for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/628797267978289152&#34;&gt;JSM 2015 mobile app&lt;/a&gt;. Did you know there was one? Good luck finding a link to &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; on their website, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pdf is useable, but much like the website, it fails to make use of the medium. I want:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bookmarks. I want to jump to where Monday&amp;rsquo;s sessions start without have to flip through the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hyperlinks. If you don&amp;rsquo;t include the abstracts, with links from the talk titles to the abstracts, at least include links to the web page that has the abstract so I don&amp;rsquo;t have to search on the web.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;More hyperlinks. The pdf has an index, with people and page numbers. Why not link those page numbers to the corresponding page?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I helped organize a &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org/ctc2013/&#34;&gt;small meeting&lt;/a&gt; in 2013. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org/ctc2013/program.html&#34;&gt;program on the web&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org/ctc2013/ctc2013_program.pdf&#34;&gt;corresponding pdf&lt;/a&gt; illustrate much of what I want. (No scheduling feature, but that meeting had no simultaneous sessions.) I included gratuitous network graphs of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org/ctc2013/vis/authors.html&#34;&gt;authors&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org/ctc2013/vis/abstracts.html&#34;&gt;abstracts&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s 2015. No conference site is truly complete without interactive network graphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update&#34;&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stat.auckland.ac.nz/showperson?firstname=Thomas&amp;amp;surname=Lumley&#34;&gt;Thomas Lumley&lt;/a&gt; commented below, if you search on &amp;ldquo;Wu&amp;rdquo; you get all of the &amp;ldquo;Wu&amp;rdquo;s but also there&amp;rsquo;s one &amp;ldquo;Wulfhorst&amp;rdquo;. And if you search on &amp;ldquo;Hao&amp;rdquo; you get only people whose &lt;em&gt;last&lt;/em&gt; name is &amp;ldquo;Hao&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tslumley/status/629096725978845185&#34;&gt;further pointed out&lt;/a&gt; that if you search for the affiliation &amp;ldquo;Auckland&amp;rdquo; the results don&amp;rsquo;t include &amp;ldquo;University of Auckland&amp;rdquo; but only &amp;ldquo;Auckland University of Technology&amp;rdquo;. And actually, if you search for &amp;ldquo;University of Auckland&amp;rdquo; you get nothing. You need to search for &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; University of Auckland&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If I could do it over again, I&#39;d self-publish</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/08/12/if-i-could-do-it-over-again-id-self-publish/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/08/12/if-i-could-do-it-over-again-id-self-publish/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2009, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.epibiostat.ucsf.edu/biostat/sen/&#34;&gt;Śaunak Sen&lt;/a&gt; and I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rqtl.org&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; about QTL mapping and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rqtl.org&#34;&gt;R/qtl&lt;/a&gt; software. We started working on it in the fall of 2006, and it was a heck of a lot of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;d talked to several publishers, and ended up publishing with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com&#34;&gt;Springer&lt;/a&gt;. John Kimmel was the editor we worked with; I like John, and I felt that Springer (or &lt;em&gt;John&lt;/em&gt;) did a good job of keeping prices reasonable. We were able to publish in full color with a list price of \$99, so that on Amazon it was about \$65. (In April, 2013, there was a brief period where &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/321747087744184320&#34;&gt;it was just \$42 at Amazon&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Springer did arrange several rounds of reviews; they typically pay reviewers \$100 or a few books. But the copy editing was terrible (at the very least, you want a copy editor to &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; the book, and it was pretty clear that our copy editor &lt;em&gt;hadn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt;), and the actual type-setting and construction of the index was left to us, the authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels nice to have written a proper book, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think it makes that big of a difference, for me or for readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And John Kimmel has since left Springer to go to Chapman &amp;amp; Hall/CRC, and Springer has raised the price of our book to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com/life+sciences/systems+biology+and+bioinformatics/book/978-0-387-92124-2&#34;&gt;\$169&lt;/a&gt;, so it&amp;rsquo;s now selling for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0387921249/7210-20&#34;&gt;\$130 at Amazon&lt;/a&gt;. I think that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;obnoxious&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s not like they&amp;rsquo;ve gone back and printed extra copies, so it&amp;rsquo;s hard to see how their costs could have gone up. But in the publishing agreement we signed, we gave Springer full rights to set the price of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: it&amp;rsquo;s now listed at \$199, though it&amp;rsquo;s still about \$130 at Amazon.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a hard time recommending the book at that price; I&amp;rsquo;m tempted to help people find pirated PDFs online. (And seriously, if you can&amp;rsquo;t find a pirated copy, you should work on your internet skills.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I corresponded with an editor at Springer, on why our book has become so expensive and whether there&amp;rsquo;s anything we can do about it. They responded&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we do a new edition, it could be listed as \$129.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the book is adopted by university classes, &amp;ldquo;the pricing grid it is based on would have lower prices.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our book is available electronically, for purchase by chapter as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purchase by chapter? Yeah, for &lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-0-387-92125-9&#34;&gt;\$30 per chapter!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Springer has &lt;a href=&#34;http://statweb.stanford.edu/~tibs/ElemStatLearn/&#34;&gt;published books and allowed the authors to post a PDF&lt;/a&gt;, but only for really big sellers, and ours is definitely not in that category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m both disgusted and embarrassed by this situation. If I could do it all over again, I&amp;rsquo;d self-publish: post everything on the web, and arrange some way for folks to have it printed cheaply.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I still don&#39;t like it</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/02/09/i-still-dont-like-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/02/09/i-still-dont-like-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got a book in the mail this week, a book I hadn&amp;rsquo;t ordered and would never have ordered. The publisher sent me a complimentary copy, as I&amp;rsquo;d reviewed the book proposal last year. (It&amp;rsquo;s the one where &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/07/what-a-waste-of-paper/&#34;&gt;the author refused to allow me to have an electronic copy&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I soundly trashed the proposal in my review. In the nicest possible way, of course. For example, I said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there are things that are just plain wrong. For example, &amp;ldquo;We then express our confidence in the H0 with a p-value, which might crudely be considered the probability that the H0 is true.&amp;rdquo; That is not a &lt;em&gt;crude&lt;/em&gt; interpretation of the p-value; that is just &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like if a reviewer says, &amp;ldquo;This particular book should not be adopted,&amp;rdquo; the publisher can interpret that to also mean, &amp;ldquo;and whatever you do, don&amp;rsquo;t send me a copy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Things to avoid as a new faculty member</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/12/05/things-to-avoid-as-a-new-faculty-member/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/12/05/things-to-avoid-as-a-new-faculty-member/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The transition from graduate student or postdoc to tenure-track faculty member is hard. You discover that there are a ton of new things to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some thoughts on things to &lt;em&gt;avoid&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may see lots of ways in which your department could be improved; don&amp;rsquo;t try to fix all of them at once.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may see needs for many new courses.  Don&amp;rsquo;t try to develop all of them.  Try to teach the same courses at least three years in a row.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t agree to work with just any student who asks.  While a good student can really help, a bad student can suck up all your time and energy. Students may be worried about money and feigning interest in order to get a research position, but if they&amp;rsquo;re not &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; interested, they won&amp;rsquo;t make much progress and it will be bad for both of you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t agree to collaborate with someone in the two weeks before a grant deadline. You might get stuck in a commitment with some total jerk.  Find out if you&amp;rsquo;d really enjoy working with them, first.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t agree to write a book chapter.  It&amp;rsquo;s almost as much work as a formal paper, but not as many people will read it and it won&amp;rsquo;t count for much on your CV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It was a really bad idea to use slides in that class</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/10/08/it-was-a-really-bad-idea-to-use-slides-in-that-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/10/08/it-was-a-really-bad-idea-to-use-slides-in-that-class/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I gave a presentation in the Statistical Consulting course at UW-Madison today. I&amp;rsquo;ve done so a number of times in the past 6 years. Until today, I&amp;rsquo;d just spoken informally from a few pages of notes. (Earlier this year, I wrote up those notes as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/02/thoughts-on-statistical-consulting/&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, just 45 min before the class, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d quickly create some slides to present. I thought it&amp;rsquo;d be an interesting &amp;ldquo;experiment&amp;rdquo; (not in the formal sense):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Could I quickly create usable slides using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/10/07/better-looking-latexbeamer-slides/&#34;&gt;LateX/Beamer template I wrote about yesterday&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Would it be useful to have slides in this class?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome was pretty clear: It was easy to create a bunch of bullet-point-based slides. They look nice. (See the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/teaching/misc/consulting.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf here&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/kbroman/Talk_StatConsulting.git&#34;&gt;source here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But&lt;/strong&gt;, the slides themselves worse than useless: Unnecessary, and they interfered with the desired informal nature of the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t be using those slides again. I&amp;rsquo;ll go back to just talking from notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the students were really good and involved and asked great questions, anyway. So no real harm done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complaints about the NIH grant review process</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/10/02/complaints-about-the-nih-grant-review-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/10/02/complaints-about-the-nih-grant-review-process/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, I met with a collaborator to discuss what to do with our NIH grant proposal, whose &amp;ldquo;A1&amp;rdquo; was &amp;ldquo;unscored&amp;rdquo; (ie, the revised version, and you don&amp;rsquo;t get a third try, received a &amp;ldquo;preliminary score&amp;rdquo; in the lower half and so was not discussed by the review panel and couldn&amp;rsquo;t be funded).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NIH proposals are typically reviewed by three people and given preliminary scores on five aspects (significance, approach, investigators, environment, innovation) and overall, and the top proposals based on those scores are discussed and scored by the larger panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reviewers gave our proposal an 8 for &amp;ldquo;approach&amp;rdquo; (on a scale of 1-9, with 1 being good and 9 being terrible) with the following review comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Approach:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strengths&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Well described details for mining of [data] and genotyping of [subjects].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weaknesses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no power analysis for Aim 2. Without knowing which and how many [phenotypes] will be evaluated it is not possible to estimate the statistical power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valid comments, but is that really all the reviewer had to say? What about Aims 1 and 3, or the other aspects of Aim 2? &lt;em&gt;That is totally fucking inadequate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at this review again, I was reminded of how much I despise many aspects of the NIH review process. So it&amp;rsquo;s led me, finally, to write down some of the things that annoy me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-scoring-system-is-too-discrete&#34;&gt;The scoring system is too discrete&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been involved in reviewing NIH grants for 15 years. A bunch of changes were made in about 2009 or so, with a few things for the better (like having the review order of grants based on preliminary score) but many for the worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst change was to the scoring system. In the old system, reviewers scored grants on a scale of 1-5, in tenths (1.0, 1.1, 1.2, &amp;hellip;), with 1 being best and 5 being worst. Scores were averaged and multiplied by 100, so the best possible score was 100 and the worst was 500. (And note that the middle value was 300 not 250, a point of confusion for many.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new system, reviewers score grants on a scale of 1-9, in single digits, with 1 being best and 9 being worst (and 5 being the middle value). Scores are averaged and multiplied by ten, so the best possible score is 10 and the worst is 90.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the new scale was introduced, we were given the following handy chart:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/10/nih_score_chart.png&#34; alt=&#34;NIH 9-point score chart&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I understand it, there were two main reasons for revising the scoring system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fix the &amp;ldquo;grade inflation&amp;rdquo; problem (too many good scores)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reviewers can&amp;rsquo;t score grants with 0.1 precision.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as a fix for the grade inflation problem, revising the scoring system could only be a temporary solution. And as I understand it, the problem is now worse than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big problem with the new scoring system is that reviewers have just 9 choices of scores, whereas before they had 41. Yes, a reviewer can&amp;rsquo;t really discriminate 1.3 from 1.4. &lt;strong&gt;But if you have 25 imprecise measure instruments, would it be better to&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;average and then round&lt;/em&gt;, or&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;round and then average&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s obviously better to &lt;em&gt;average and then round&lt;/em&gt;, but the new scoring system &lt;em&gt;rounds and then averages&lt;/em&gt;. (&lt;a href=&#34;http://churchill.jax.org/about/churchill.shtml&#34;&gt;Gary Churchill&lt;/a&gt; pointed this out to me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to the frequent statements like, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;d put this somewhere between a 1 and a 2.&amp;rdquo; And with line (or &amp;ldquo;band&amp;rdquo;) between funded and not funded being well above 20, it seems like, in many cases, &lt;em&gt;whether a grant is funded has to do with the proportion of reviewers that give it a 1&lt;/em&gt; rather than a 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-bullet-point-based-reviews-lead-to-superficial-and-incomplete-comments&#34;&gt;The bullet-point-based reviews lead to superficial and incomplete comments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be that the written reviews of grant proposals were much like reviews of journal articles: for each aspect of a proposal (significance, approach, etc.), we&amp;rsquo;d write a few paragraphs, in some cases a full page. Such reviews were hard to write, were often long, and sometimes didn&amp;rsquo;t do a good job of making clear what were the really important issues and what were the less important ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the big review change in 2009, reviewers were asked to write bullet points for &amp;ldquo;Strengths&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Weaknesses.&amp;rdquo; (And in a Microsoft Word template!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a lot easier to write a few bullet points than to construct coherent prose, but the bullet points that reviewers produce are generally shallow and incomplete. In some cases, a reviewer&amp;rsquo;s thinking about a proposal may be left in a shallow and incomplete state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review at the top of this post is the best (or really &lt;em&gt;worst&lt;/em&gt;) instance of this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;don-t-drop-the-proposal-summary-from-the-beginning-of-the-discussion&#34;&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t drop the proposal summary from the beginning of the discussion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, the discussion of a proposal would begin with the primary reviewer giving a brief summary: what are the investigators proposing to do? This is critical, as only 3 of the 25 or so people on the panel will have read the proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know if they&amp;rsquo;re still doing this, but with the other changes to the review process, we were asked to skip the summary of proposal and just discuss the significance of the work. But how on earth can you talk about the significance of the work without some mention of what the work actually is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-electronic-grant-format-is-often-not-human-readable&#34;&gt;The electronic grant format is often not human readable.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first reviewed NIH grant proposals, we each got a copy-paper-sized box with all of the proposals (and when proposals were triaged, all 25 reviewers would simultaneously throw the proposal into a big pile). It was great to move to electronic versions of grants (initially scanned, then fully electronic), but the electronic versions of proposals are not constructed in a way that has a human reader in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front page of grants used to be quite clear and informative, but now all of the form-generated pages are a design mess. For example, the pages listing the key personnel and their institutions are really hard to parse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there are loads of useless pages describing what documents were included. Couldn&amp;rsquo;t the reviewers get a version without all of that crap?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the PDF bookmarks are often off by a page. If you want to go to the biosketches, you need to click the biosketch bookmark and then page down one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things aren&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; big of a deal, but they&amp;rsquo;re a constant annoyance, and they should be easy to fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony Scarpa, the former director of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://public.csr.nih.gov/Pages/default.aspx&#34;&gt;NIH Center for Scientific Review (CSR)&lt;/a&gt; who was responsible for the big change in the NIH review system, once visited U Wisconsin, and I asked him about whether these electronic proposals could be improved, and he said, &amp;ldquo;Oh, that&amp;rsquo;s not us; that&amp;rsquo;s grants.gov.&amp;rdquo; So I asked who I should talk to about the issue, and he said, &amp;ldquo;Call your Congressman.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;there-needs-to-be-some-review-of-reviewers&#34;&gt;There needs to be some review of reviewers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final comment: there needs to be some formal way for reviewers to comment on other reviewers. I think most reviewers are very careful and responsible, but there&amp;rsquo;s often at least one total jerk on a review panel: didn&amp;rsquo;t read the proposal carefully, didn&amp;rsquo;t write a coherent review, didn&amp;rsquo;t pay any attention to what the other reviewers said, gave completely unfair scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There should be some system for other reviewers to say, &amp;ldquo;So-and-so on the panel was a complete jerk and shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be brought back.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Department websites</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/09/11/department-websites/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/09/11/department-websites/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I was thinking about department websites, partly because &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;my own department&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt; is terrible, and recently a colleague asked me whether I could suggest some &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; department sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll describe the basic principles for a good department website, and then I&amp;rsquo;ll comment on a number of examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first: No discussion of academic web pages is complete without referring to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/773/&#34;&gt;xkcd comic&lt;/a&gt; on University websites, so let&amp;rsquo;s start with that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/773/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/university_website.png&#34; alt=&#34;xkcd comic: University Websites&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;basic-principles&#34;&gt;Basic principles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are what I see to be the basic principles for constructing a department website:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Think of the audiences and what they&amp;rsquo;d be looking for&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prospective students&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prospective/visiting faculty&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Current students&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Collaborators&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Administrators&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Current faculty&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Department staff&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keep the important stuff near the top; minimize bloat&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the key stuff that should be prominent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Degree programs; courses; how to apply&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Faculty and student pages&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Staff contact information&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seminars&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Job opportunities&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t use stock photos or (even worse!) clip art&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avoid deep nesting of information&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have meaningful URLs (in particular, don&amp;rsquo;t let &lt;a href=&#34;https://drupal.org/&#34;&gt;drupal&lt;/a&gt; use &lt;code&gt;node/134&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have a consistent style across the official pages &amp;ndash; particularly in the location and layout of menus of hyperlinks&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I prefer minimalism. Think &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com&#34;&gt;google&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com&#34;&gt;apple&lt;/a&gt; rather than &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.microsoft.com&#34;&gt;Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-examples&#34;&gt;Some examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I briefly perused a number of statistics and biostatistics department websites. Here are my first impressions. The sites for &lt;a href=&#34;http://statistics.berkeley.edu/&#34;&gt;Berkeley&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://statistics.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;Stanford&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.umn.edu/&#34;&gt;Minnesota&lt;/a&gt; Statistics were my favorites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Hopkins Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key bits are half-way down the page, due to unnecessary (in my mind) school-related crap along the top, plus the news items. The &amp;ldquo;Quick find&amp;rdquo; looks-like-a-drop-down-menu at the top right seems to just link to a &lt;em&gt;different department&amp;rsquo;s web page&lt;/em&gt;. The news items at the top result in the menu moving upward when you click on a link (as those news items don&amp;rsquo;t appear in the subsequent pages).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/biostatistics&#34;&gt;Harvard Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s too much school-related crap at the top, but it&amp;rsquo;s not as bad as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Hopkins site&lt;/a&gt;. I like having pages &amp;ldquo;For Prospective Students,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;For Current Students,&amp;rdquo; etc., but they pop to pages that look totally different and lose that menu, so you have to go back and then forward again. &amp;ldquo;Student Profiles&amp;rdquo; maybe should just be called &amp;ldquo;Student Profile&amp;rdquo; as there doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be more than one. The &amp;ldquo;BIO&amp;rdquo; in &amp;ldquo;BIO Faculty&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;BIO Researchers&amp;rdquo; was a little confusing: Is it obvious what &amp;ldquo;BIO&amp;rdquo; means, and is it really necessary?  I&amp;rsquo;d put the Faculty and Researchers links closer to the top and may try to distinguish the different classes of links: the ones that people are really there for, and then all of the &amp;ldquo;For Such-and-Such&amp;rdquo; somewhat separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.washington.edu/&#34;&gt;Washington Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reasonably clean, but a bit of the &lt;code&gt;node/134&lt;/code&gt; problem. And there are two kinds of menus: tabs at the top, and a menu at the right side. I think it&amp;rsquo;s okay, but it was a bit confusing initially: It wasn&amp;rsquo;t immediately obvious that I click a different tab to get a different set of menu choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sph.unc.edu/department-pages/biostatistics/&#34;&gt;UNC-Chapel Hill Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main page looks nice, but the sub-pages have a different format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.ncsu.edu/&#34;&gt;NC State Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I generally like it, but why split the faculty list across multiple pages? I see no reason to limit the length of a web page; scrolling is our friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sph.umn.edu/biostatistics/&#34;&gt;Minnesota Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Way&lt;/em&gt; too much bloat at the top; links all over the place at the bottom&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.umn.edu/&#34;&gt;Minnesota Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this one. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure about the color choices, but the site is clean, and it&amp;rsquo;s easy to navigate. And I like the choice and order of topics in the menu at the left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://statistics.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;Stanford Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like this one: Just the facts, plus a picture of Sequoia Hall. There&amp;rsquo;s a little menu bar at the top that has the key stuff. You want to know about courses or degree programs? Click &amp;ldquo;Academics.&amp;rdquo; You want to know about People or Seminars? They&amp;rsquo;re right there at the top. How do you apply? Click &amp;ldquo;Admissions.&amp;rdquo; They could maybe trim the news on the left of the front page; some of it is getting old and at least one of the links doesn&amp;rsquo;t work anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://statistics.berkeley.edu/&#34;&gt;Berkeley Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berkeley is slightly better than Stanford. The websites, I mean. It&amp;rsquo;s simple, there&amp;rsquo;s a clean little menu at the top, and the menus at the top have clear little drop-down menus when you hover over things. I like that they use more horizontal space. I guess I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t put &amp;ldquo;Seminars&amp;rdquo; under &amp;ldquo;Research&amp;rdquo; Nor would I put &amp;ldquo;Alumni Connections&amp;rdquo; under &amp;ldquo;Industry.&amp;rdquo; So there are ways in which Stanford is better than Berkeley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sph.umich.edu/biostat/&#34;&gt;Michigan Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front page looks a bit cluttered. And they list University rankings front and center, which is a bit of an embarrassment. There&amp;rsquo;s a bit of school-related stuff at the top, but it&amp;rsquo;s not as bothersome as some others. There may be too many choices on the left. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to pick out the ones you want, even if they&amp;rsquo;re there. And &amp;ldquo;Students&amp;rdquo; should really be &amp;ldquo;For Students,&amp;rdquo; while &amp;ldquo;Careers&amp;rdquo; should really be &amp;ldquo;Alumni Profiles.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I could look at a ton more, but I&amp;rsquo;m sort of sick of this. Go have a look yourself, and let me know if you find good ones.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>$18 for a two page PDF? I still don&#39;t get it.</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/05/02/18-for-a-two-page-pdf-i-still-dont-get-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/05/02/18-for-a-two-page-pdf-i-still-dont-get-it/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Ananyo/status/329545985149775873&#34;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Ananyo&#34;&gt;@Ananyo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Time that biologists stopped telling the public oversimplistic fairy tales on Darwinian evolution, says P Ball (\$) [nature.com/nature/journal...](http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v496/n7446/full/496419a.html)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I clicked the link to the Nature paper and realized, &amp;ldquo;Oh, yeah.  I&amp;rsquo;ve got to enter through the UW library website.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I thought, &amp;ldquo;Wait&amp;hellip;\$18 for a two-page Nature comment?  WTF?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/329560393922002944&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
DNA: Celebrate the unknowns, like this Nature comment, which costs \$18. [nature.com/nature/journal...](http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v496/n7446/full/496419a.html)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thinking about it some more, I got more annoyed, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/329566578024775683&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Why do publishers charge such high per-article fees? At \$18/artcl, you&#39;d have to be desperate or stupid to pay; at \$1-2, prob&#39;ly lots would.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I thought, I&amp;rsquo;ll &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/329575795716661250&#34;&gt;ask Nature directly&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
@NatureMagazine Why is the per-article charge so high? It seems like you&#39;d make more profit at \$2/article.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/NatureMagazine&#34;&gt;they&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/NatureMagazine/status/329655405355614210&#34;&gt;responded&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
@kwbroman For a while now, individual papers can be rented through @readcube for \$3-5. A full tablet subscription to Nature costs \$35.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that didn&amp;rsquo;t quite answer my question.  So I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/329683444051365889&#34;&gt;asked&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
.@NatureMagazine So is the \$18 charge for a 2 pg PDF just to discourage piracy?
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought a lot about whether to put &amp;ldquo;piracy&amp;rdquo; in quotes or not, or whether to write &amp;ldquo;copyright infringement&amp;rdquo; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anyway, they &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/NatureMagazine/status/329692960205725696&#34;&gt;responded&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
@kwbroman just as with any product, the more you buy, the more you save. Media/publishing subscriptions have worked this way for decades.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That again didn&amp;rsquo;t quite answer my question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;it-s-a-scam&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a scam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still don&amp;rsquo;t understand the \$18 business.  It&amp;rsquo;s not &amp;ldquo;The more you buy, the more you save.&amp;rdquo;  It&amp;rsquo;s, &amp;ldquo;Buy the whole season for \$35, or buy 5 min from Episode 1 for \$18.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that the cover price of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com&#34;&gt;Wired&lt;/a&gt; is \$5 per issue, while I could get a year&amp;rsquo;s subscription for \$15-20.  But that&amp;rsquo;s not the same as \$18 for &lt;em&gt;one article&lt;/em&gt; vs \$200 per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The \$18 for a two-page PDF is like 900 numbers and paycheck advances.  These are &lt;em&gt;scams&lt;/em&gt; taking advantage of desperate or stupid people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they don&amp;rsquo;t want to sell the PDFs for individual articles for a reasonable price, they should just not sell them at all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Methods before results</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/29/methods-before-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/29/methods-before-results/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s great that, in a step towards improved reproducibility, the Nature journals are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/ng/journal/v45/n5/full/ng.2621.html&#34;&gt;removing page limits on Methods sections&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
To allow authors to describe their experimental designs and methods in enough detail for others to interpret and replicate them, the participating journals are removing length restrictions on Methods sections.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But couldn&amp;rsquo;t they include the Methods section in the pdf for the article?  For example, consider &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/ng/journal/v45/n5/full/ng.2591.html&#34;&gt;this article in Nature Genetics&lt;/a&gt;; the Methods section is only available in the html version of the paper. The PDF says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Methods and any associated references are available in the online version of the paper.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Methods&lt;/em&gt; are important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be separated from the main text.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be placed after the results (as so many journals, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosbiology.org&#34;&gt;PLoS&lt;/a&gt;, do).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be in a smaller font than the main text (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pnas.org&#34;&gt;PNAS&lt;/a&gt; does).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;They certainly shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be endnotes (as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/276/5316/1268.long&#34;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; used to do).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;supplements-annoy-me-too&#34;&gt;Supplements annoy me too&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love supplemental material: authors can give the full details, and they can provide as many supplemental figures and tables as they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But supplements can be a real pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to have to click on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosgenetics.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pgen.1003321#s5&#34;&gt;10 different links&lt;/a&gt;.  Put it all in one document.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to have to open Word.  Put text and figures in a PDF.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to have to open Excel.  Put data in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caitlinrivers.com/1/post/2013/04/send-me-your-data-pdf-is-fine-said-no-one-ever-how-to-share-your-data-effectively.html&#34;&gt;plain text file&lt;/a&gt;, preferably as part of a git repository with related code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least supplements are now included at the journal sites!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/19/8/956.long&#34;&gt;This paper&lt;/a&gt; in Bioinformatics refers to a separate site for supplemental information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Expression data and supplementary information are available at
http://www.rii.com/publications/2003/HE_SDS.htm.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But &lt;code&gt;rii.com&lt;/code&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist anymore.  I was able to find &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.archive.org/web/20080719125540/http://www.rii.com/publications/2003/HE_SDS.html&#34;&gt;the supplement&lt;/a&gt; using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.archive.org&#34;&gt;Wayback Machine&lt;/a&gt;, but&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The link in the paper was wrong: It should be &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt; not &lt;code&gt;.htm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final version on Wayback has a corrupted PDF, though one can go back to previous versions that are okay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-like-genetics-http-www-genetics-org-and-g3-http-www-g3-journal-org&#34;&gt;I like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org&#34;&gt;Genetics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.g3-journal.org&#34;&gt;G3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org&#34;&gt;Genetics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.g3-journal.org&#34;&gt;G3&lt;/a&gt; put the Methods where they belong (before the results), and when you download the PDF for an article in Genetics, it includes the supplement.  For a G3 article, the supplement isn&amp;rsquo;t included in the article PDF, but at least you can the whole supplement as a single PDF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, consider my recent Genetics articles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org/content/190/2/403.full&#34;&gt;Genotype probabilities at intermediate generations in the construction of recombinant inbred lines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.org/content/192/1/267.full&#34;&gt;Mapping quantitative trait loci onto a phylogenetic tree&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you click on &amp;ldquo;Full Text (PDF),&amp;rdquo; you get the article plus the 3 supplemental figures and 23 supplemental tables in the former case, and article plus the 17 supplemental figures and 2 supplemental tables in the latter case.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use meaningful URLs</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/10/use-meaningful-urls/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/10/use-meaningful-urls/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/natesmoyer/qr-codes-are-stupid&#34;&gt;QR codes are stupid&lt;/a&gt;.  See the well-known &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jcolman/status/320917928881033218&#34;&gt;flowchart&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I don&amp;rsquo;t like &lt;a href=&#34;http://drupal.org&#34;&gt;Drupal&lt;/a&gt;.  Sites that use it give things URLs like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genetics.wisc.edu/node/577&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;http://www.genetics.wisc.edu/node/577&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for their seminar list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And can we get rid of the &lt;code&gt;www&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&#34;What&#39;s your web site?&#34;

&#34;double-u double-u double-u ...&#34;

&#34;Zzz...&#34;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;URLs should be meaningful and short.  I like deep hierarchies of folders, but it makes for long URLs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bitly.com&#34;&gt;URL-shorteners&lt;/a&gt; help, but you don&amp;rsquo;t really want to read out (or type) one of those short URLs.  And they tell you nothing about where they&amp;rsquo;re going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you want is something like &lt;a href=&#34;http://bcaffo.com&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bcaffo.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://stodden.net&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;stodden.net&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  Or &lt;a href=&#34;http://rqtl.org&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rqtl.org&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But&amp;hellip;I guess you could just say &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll send you an email.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;and-customize-title&#34;&gt;And customize &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while I have your attention, note that the title of your web page shows up on Google (and at the top of the browser).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s nice to see others make use of my html code, but you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;a href=&#34;http://darwin.cwru.edu/~iyengar/publications.html&#34;&gt;leave my name in the title of your publication page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put the important words first (not like the title for my &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/People/faculty/broman.htm&#34;&gt;official page&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;), and perhaps nothing else. For example, the title &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pophealth.wisc.edu/faculty/palta&#34;&gt;shouldn&amp;rsquo;t include &amp;ldquo;Drupal&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;: Read this: &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.not-implemented.com/urls-are-for-people-not-computers/&#34;&gt;URLs are for People, not Computers&lt;/a&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could have just given the URL:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.not-implemented.com/urls-are-for-people-not-computers/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;http://www.not-implemented.com/urls-are-for-people-not-computers&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beware of grep with a list</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/03/beware-of-grep-with-a-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/04/03/beware-of-grep-with-a-list/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another &lt;a href=&#34;http://r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; tip: beware of &lt;code&gt;as.character&lt;/code&gt; applied to a list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; as.character( list(letters[1:3], letters[4:6]) )
[1] &amp;quot;c(\&amp;quot;a\&amp;quot;, \&amp;quot;b\&amp;quot;, \&amp;quot;c\&amp;quot;)&amp;quot; &amp;quot;c(\&amp;quot;d\&amp;quot;, \&amp;quot;e\&amp;quot;, \&amp;quot;f\&amp;quot;)&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really, beware of &lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt; with a list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; grep(&amp;quot;c&amp;quot;, list(letters[1:3], letters[4:6]))
[1] 1 2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might have thought that the result would be just &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;, but &lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt; expects a vector of character strings.  If the input is not that, it uses &lt;code&gt;as.character()&lt;/code&gt;.  Since the result of that starts with &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;c(&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt; finds &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;c&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; in each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/7591632/why-this-behavior-when-coercing-a-list-to-character-via-as-character&#34;&gt;related discussion&lt;/a&gt; (from Sept 2011) on &lt;a href=&#34;http://stackoverflow.com&#34;&gt;stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What a waste of paper</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/07/what-a-waste-of-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/07/what-a-waste-of-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A university press asked me to review a book manuscript, and the author &amp;ldquo;has asked that we not use electronic copies.&amp;rdquo; So they&amp;rsquo;re going to send me a hard copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My response: &amp;ldquo;If you only give me a paper copy, I&amp;rsquo;m going to just scan it and toss the paper. That seems like a waste of time (and paper and postage).&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should probably have said, &amp;ldquo;Then forget it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their response included, &amp;ldquo;What you do with it when it arrives I am just going to take a hear-no-evil approach to.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hopkins SPH logo, part 3: Karl&#39;s revenge</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/06/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-3-karls-revenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/06/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-3-karls-revenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m finally back to the story of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/&#34;&gt;Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/identity/coreIdentity/logoIntro.shtml&#34;&gt;logo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/16/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-1/&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; in mid-November and &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/21/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-2/&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt; a week later.  I said that Part 3 was &amp;ldquo;coming soon,&amp;rdquo; but I&amp;rsquo;ve been a bit shy about revealing this.  You&amp;rsquo;ll see why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August, 2005, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~iruczins/&#34;&gt;Ingo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.albany.edu/sph/19585.php&#34;&gt;Greg&lt;/a&gt;, and I were sitting in a pub in Minneapolis in the early morning hours.  I think maybe &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bcaffo.com&#34;&gt;Brian&lt;/a&gt; was there, too.  We had a session, which Ingo had organized, at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2005/&#34;&gt;Joint Statistical Meetings&lt;/a&gt; the next morning (really &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; morning), and so we should have been sleeping.  (&lt;a href=&#34;http://sunduzkeles.org&#34;&gt;Sunduz&lt;/a&gt; was also in the session, but, sensibly, she wasn&amp;rsquo;t out drinking with us.)  I think this was later in the evening on the night I&amp;rsquo;d offended the guy from Insightful when I said that anyone who still used Splus rather than R was an idiot.  And it was just after Greg and I (and perhaps Brian, if he was there) paid the waitress to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bring the round of drinks that Ingo had ordered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we were talking about the Hopkins SPH logo (otherwise, why would I be discussing this?) as well as an innovative alternative that Brian Caffo had devised, and Ingo bet me to include Brian&amp;rsquo;s alternative logo in my talk the next day (or really &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; day): If I included the alternative logo in my talk, he&amp;rsquo;d buy me beer for a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I did, though I had to stay up quite a bit later to get the images together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kendzior/&#34;&gt;Christina&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.wisc.edu/~newton/&#34;&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt; were in the back of the room.  Ingo was sitting in the front row.  We&amp;rsquo;d used Greg&amp;rsquo;s laptop, so there was evidence.  I made a bit of fun of the Bloomberg name change, and I made a bit of fun of the logo, by showing the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mcusa.org/Portals/8/Images/logo_251x130.gif&#34;&gt;Missionary Church&lt;/a&gt; logo.  And then on my third slide, I paused for a bit and looked at Ingo, and he looked at me and then up at the screen, and when I saw that he&amp;rsquo;d seen it, I flipped to the next slide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Brian&amp;rsquo;s alternative logo, next to the original.  Well, it&amp;rsquo;s Brian&amp;rsquo;s design but my rendering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;JHBSPH logo&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/altlogo.png&#34; alt=&#34;Alternative logo&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/evidence.pdf&#34;&gt;here&amp;rsquo;s a PDF of the logos in context&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s the month of beer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/month_of_beer.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Month of beer&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ingo was willing to restock if necessary, but that wasn&amp;rsquo;t allowed.  We still have most of those coasters; they&amp;rsquo;ve been great toys for the kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October that year, I used the alternative logo on the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/offices-and-services/marketing-and-communications/policies/wall_of_wonder.html&#34;&gt;Wall of Wonder&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; itself, on a second bet, with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/faculty/directory/profile/3980/Pineda/Fernando_J.&#34;&gt;Fernando&lt;/a&gt; this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave another of those informal statistics lectures, this time on &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations/regression_ho.pdf&#34;&gt;What is regression?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;  Of course, they were pre-screening slides at that point, because of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/21/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-2&#34;&gt;first such informal talk&lt;/a&gt;.  But I gave them a last-minute substitution, with just the one logo change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/people/staff/hubbard.shtml&#34;&gt;Patty&lt;/a&gt; caught me, but she didn&amp;rsquo;t turn me in.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the second month of beer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/second_month_of_beer.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Second month of beer&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all seems a bit juvenile in retrospect.  I guess I&amp;rsquo;m getting (or &lt;em&gt;have gotten&lt;/em&gt;) old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~iruczins&#34;&gt;Ingo&lt;/a&gt; says that &amp;ldquo;juvenile&amp;rdquo; is another word for &amp;ldquo;hip and dynamic,&amp;rdquo; so I guess it&amp;rsquo;s just that I&amp;rsquo;m no longer hip and dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related posts on the Hopkins SPH logo: &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/16/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-1&#34;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/21/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-2/&#34;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>D3.js difficulties</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/02/08/d3-js-difficulties/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/02/08/d3-js-difficulties/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m pleased with my progress learning javascript and &lt;a href=&#34;http://d3js.org&#34;&gt;D3&lt;/a&gt;. (I&amp;rsquo;m actually writing &lt;a href=&#34;http://coffeescript.org&#34;&gt;coffeescript&lt;/a&gt; rather than javascript.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I spent a lot of time thrashing about yesterday, due mostly to two silly errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;put-the-script-in-the-body&#34;&gt;Put the script in the body&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I&amp;rsquo;d tried to make a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/D3/error1/error1.html&#34;&gt;truly simple example&lt;/a&gt;, making just an SVG with a little rectangle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;html lang=&amp;quot;en&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;meta charset=&amp;quot;utf-8&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Put script in body&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;script type=&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot;
        src=&amp;quot;http://d3js.org/d3.v3.min.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;

    &amp;lt;script type=&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    var h=50;
    var svg = d3.select(&amp;quot;body&amp;quot;).append(&amp;quot;svg&amp;quot;)
                .attr(&amp;quot;height&amp;quot;, h).attr(&amp;quot;width&amp;quot;, h);
    svg.append(&amp;quot;rect&amp;quot;).attr(&amp;quot;x&amp;quot;, 0).attr(&amp;quot;y&amp;quot;, 0)
                .attr(&amp;quot;height&amp;quot;, h).attr(&amp;quot;width&amp;quot;,h);
    &amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this gives nothing.  You need to move the script from the &lt;code&gt;head&lt;/code&gt; to the &lt;code&gt;body&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/D3/error1/error1b.html&#34;&gt;as it is here&lt;/a&gt;.  Then it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t really understand this.  Perhaps I should go back to my reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: I think I&amp;rsquo;ve figured this out.  If you put the script in the &lt;code&gt;head&lt;/code&gt;, the code gets run before the &lt;code&gt;body&lt;/code&gt; exists, and so there&amp;rsquo;s no &lt;code&gt;body&lt;/code&gt; in which to append the SVG.  &lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;: Put the link to your script at the very bottom of the html file.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;don-t-forget-enter&#34;&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget &lt;code&gt;enter()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In D3, you bind data to a bunch of objects, and attributes of the objects can be controlled by features of the data.  I write code sort of like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;svg.append(&amp;quot;g&amp;quot;).selectAll(&amp;quot;empty&amp;quot;)
   .data(thedata)
   .enter()
   .append(&amp;quot;rect&amp;quot;)
   .attr(&amp;quot;x&amp;quot;, (d) -&amp;gt; start[d])
   .attr(&amp;quot;y&amp;quot;, pad.top)
   .attr(&amp;quot;width&amp;quot;, (d) -&amp;gt; end[d] - start[d])
   .attr(&amp;quot;height&amp;quot;, (d) -&amp;gt; hInner)
   .attr(&amp;quot;fill&amp;quot;, (d) -&amp;gt; color[d])
   .attr(&amp;quot;stroke&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;none&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My most common mistake so far: I forget the &lt;code&gt;.enter()&lt;/code&gt; part.  You don&amp;rsquo;t get a error message, but the objects don&amp;rsquo;t get created.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microsoft Office</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/01/30/microsoft-office/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/01/30/microsoft-office/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com&#34;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a href=&#34;http://nyti.ms/WdR6ya&#34;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; about how Microsoft will have users pay a yearly fee for MS Office, instead of buying it outright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s some mention of competition from &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.google.com&#34;&gt;Google Docs&lt;/a&gt;. Why should one still use Microsoft Office? The brilliant Excel graphs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;As for Google, Mr. DelBene said it has not &#34;in any way diminished demand&#34; for Office because Microsoft&#39;s applications are &#34;just so far beyond the capabilities that are in those alternative products.&#34; As an example, he cited a feature in Excel that analyzes a batch of numbers selected by a user and automatically recommends the best way to represent the data in a chart.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I don&#39;t want your irrelevant communications either</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/12/12/i-dont-want-your-irrelevant-communications-either/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/12/12/i-dont-want-your-irrelevant-communications-either/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got some spam from Quintiles and clicked the &amp;ldquo;unsubscribe&amp;rdquo; button.  The form which came up said, &amp;ldquo;I would NOT like to receive future relevant communications from Quintiles.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/quintiles_sucks.png&#34; alt=&#34;Quintiles sucks&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should just forget about it, but the thought of some marketing jerk writing that while preparing their crap spam just really pisses me off.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Child abuse and neglect is cancelled today</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/29/child-abuse-and-neglect-is-cancelled-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/29/child-abuse-and-neglect-is-cancelled-today/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On a classroom door:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/neglect_cancelled.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hopkins SPH logo, part 2</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/21/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/21/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, I wrote about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/16/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-1/&#34;&gt;Johns Hopkins &lt;strong&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/strong&gt; School of Public Health logo&lt;/a&gt;.  I now present part 2 of the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopkins SPH had done some fancy renovations of part of the building, including an important new feature, the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/offices-and-services/marketing-and-communications/policies/wall_of_wonder.html&#34;&gt;Wall of Wonder&lt;/a&gt;&amp;ldquo;: a big display composed of nine LCD screens in the atrium of the building, to display various PR type stuff.  (&amp;ldquo;Wall of Wonder&amp;rdquo; (WOW) is the official name!  Consider the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/offices-and-services/marketing-and-communications/policies/wall_of_wonder.html&#34;&gt;Wall of Wonder policies&lt;/a&gt;, inspired by the events I detail below.) Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations/graphs_photos/IMG_0213a.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of us in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Hopkins Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt; had the idea to have a short seminar series on Friday afternoon just before Happy Hour, making use of the WOW.  (Fridays at 4, biochemistry graduate students sell beer, and lots of SPH faculty, staff, and students gather to drink and chat.)  The concept was informal lectures about different statistics topics, suitable for a general audience.  Here&amp;rsquo;s the list of talks from 2005-2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I volunteered to do the first one, on &amp;ldquo;How to display data badly,&amp;rdquo; a lecture I&amp;rsquo;d given in my &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/teaching/labstat/&#34;&gt;Statistics for laboratory scientists&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; course, inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstor.org/sici?sici=0003-1305%28198405%2938%3A2%3C137%3AHTDDB%3E2.0.CO%3B2-N&#34;&gt;Howard Wainer&amp;rsquo;s 1984 article&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amstat.org/publications/tas.cfm&#34;&gt;The American Statistician&lt;/a&gt;.  It took a lot of negotiations to get access to the WOW, and even more to get beer served early and at the seminar.  But &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/faculty/directory/profile/3859/Zeger/Scott&#34;&gt;we&lt;/a&gt; pulled it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of my talk was to take a reasonably good graph, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/fig1a.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and then show how to turn it into a terrible graph, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/fig1h.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, as an ancillary commentary on the use of gratuitous animation in slides, I animated &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/16/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-1/&#34;&gt;the School&amp;rsquo;s logo&lt;/a&gt; on each slide, with those animations becoming increasingly intrusive as the talk went on.  Then, at the summary slide, it was flying all around.  I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to refer to the logo in any way, or say anything about slide animations at all.  I just thought it would be a funny backdrop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, to get the slides on the computer that drives the big screen, you need to send them to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/offices-and-services/marketing-and-communications/&#34;&gt;Office of Communications&lt;/a&gt;.  So I did that the morning of, and then went off to teach a class.  When I got back to my office, I had a voice mail from someone in Communications, saying that they had applied &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/identity/commonCommunications/pptPresentations.shtml&#34;&gt;the School&amp;rsquo;s PowerPoint template&lt;/a&gt; to my slides.  (This was back in the days when I was using PowerPoint; you can see the slides for all of the talks I&amp;rsquo;ve given since 1998 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;; I stopped using PowerPoint in 2006.) The Communications person said that since she wasn&amp;rsquo;t as facile with PowerPoint as I was, I might want to take a look at the slides to be sure they were okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the animated logo was gone.  But also my slides had a blue background, while the School&amp;rsquo;s template had a light background, and so all of my &amp;ldquo;nice&amp;rdquo; figures looked terrible, being big blue rectangles in the middle of a light background.  And this was a talk about good (well, actually bad) graphics!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could tell it would take all the time I had left before the talk to fix the figures, so I had to choose:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fight, but probably lose, and then be stuck with ugly slides.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cave in, and clean up the slides.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could say I chose the former option, but I&amp;rsquo;m weak, and I chose the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After, there was considerable discussion in the Dean&amp;rsquo;s office about my &amp;ldquo;abuse&amp;rdquo; of the School&amp;rsquo;s logo.  And they created &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/offices-and-services/marketing-and-communications/policies/wall_of_wonder.html&#34;&gt;a formal policy&lt;/a&gt; on the use of the Wall of Wonder, which includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;When there are School events that involve external audiences the Office of External Affairs will manage the content of the Wall so that it is appropriate for the event.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the slides as presented, as well as the &amp;ldquo;Director&amp;rsquo;s Cut&amp;rdquo;, at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations/index.html#wow&#34;&gt;my web page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a slide from the Director&amp;rsquo;s Cut (the colors matched better originally; that they don&amp;rsquo;t now is an instance of one of the many reasons I hate PowerPoint):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/before.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s how it was presented:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/11/after.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related posts on the Hopkins SPH logo: &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/16/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-1&#34;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/06/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-3-karls-revenge/&#34;&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hopkins SPH logo, part 1</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/16/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/16/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was just telling &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stodden.net&#34;&gt;a distinguished visitor&lt;/a&gt; a few of my various stories about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Johns Hopkins &lt;strong&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/strong&gt; School of Public Health&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/identity/coreIdentity/logoIntro.shtml&#34;&gt;logo&lt;/a&gt;. She suggested that it would be a great blog topic. And now that I&amp;rsquo;m a tenured faculty member at a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;different university&lt;/a&gt; and so can&amp;rsquo;t get into any [further] trouble over this&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the logo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/logo.png&amp;amp;h=150&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logo was newly released while I was a faculty member in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;Department of Biostatistics&lt;/a&gt; at Hopkins.  It was part of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brand_management&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;branding&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; effort for the school that was a near-constant source of amusement for me, though I think I did strain an eye muscle or two from all the rolling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the logo was first revealed to the faculty, the website describing it (which was not unlike the current &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/identity/coreIdentity/logoIntro.shtml&#34;&gt;pedantic website&lt;/a&gt; describing the rules for its use) mentioned the &amp;ldquo;flame of leaning&amp;rdquo; rather than &amp;ldquo;of &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;rdquo;  I made the tactical error of pointing this out to the web folks, so it was fixed before we had sufficient time to make fun of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the day the logo was revealed, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/people/staff/moffitt.shtml&#34;&gt;someone&lt;/a&gt; said it looked like the logo for some religious organization.  A google search for &amp;ldquo;globe flame logo&amp;rdquo; instantly revealed the logo for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mcusa.org&#34;&gt;Missionary Church&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mcusa.org/Portals/8/Images/logo_251x130.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can the similarity be due to chance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s more to come on the logo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you really care about the JHBSPH logo, be sure to pay close attention to the list of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jhsph.edu/identity/coreIdentity/incorrectLogoUsage.shtml&#34;&gt;Incorrect Logo Usages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related posts on the Hopkins SPH logo: &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/11/21/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-2/&#34;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2013/03/06/the-hopkins-sph-logo-part-3-karls-revenge/&#34;&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Puzzling typo</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/10/27/puzzling-typo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/10/27/puzzling-typo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/27/opinion/a-failed-earthquake-prediction-a-crime.html&#34;&gt;a nice op-ed&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com&#34;&gt;NY Times&lt;/a&gt; about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/23/world/europe/italy-convicts-7-for-failure-to-warn-of-quake.html&#34;&gt;crazy conviction of seven Italian scientists for failure to warn about an unpredictable earthquake&lt;/a&gt;. But I spent quite a while puzzling over the following typo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/nytimes_article_detail.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third highlighted line should be in the middle of the fourth one, to give &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;who allow flimsy buildings to be built&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;  I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how such an error can occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/nytimes_article.pdf&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a PDF of the full article.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The future of personalized medicine</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/10/11/the-future-of-personalized-medicine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/10/11/the-future-of-personalized-medicine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Scientists&amp;rdquo; ripping people off by selling them basically useless genetic information with a bullshit report: &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/10/10/are-you-likely-to-respond-to-exercise/?smid=pl-share&#34;&gt;a genetic test for exercise&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hilarious graph</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/09/11/hilarious-graph/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/09/11/hilarious-graph/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;a href=&#34;http://campaignstops.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/09/10/the-unexpected-impact-of-coded-appeals/?hp&#34;&gt;an interesting post&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nytimes.com&#34;&gt;NY Times&lt;/a&gt; site this morning, which said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Analyzing data from the 2008 American National Election Study, we found no relationship between negative feelings toward African-Americans and opposition to government-provided health care among whites without  college degrees. For college-educated whites, however, negative racial feelings were strongly associated with increased opposition to such reform. As the graph below shows, for whites without college degrees, feelings toward African-Americans are unrelated to whether respondents support or oppose government-provided health care. For college-educated whites, however, increases in negative feelings are associated with large increases in opposition to government-provided health care.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2012/09/11/opinion/11campstops-graph/11campstops-graph-blog480.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;hilariously empty graph&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They must be right; they have a graph!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to evaluate faculty?</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/09/08/how-to-evaluate-faculty/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/09/08/how-to-evaluate-faculty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;rate their departments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.secfac.wisc.edu/divcomm/physical/TenureGuidelines.pdf&#34;&gt;tenure guidelines&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.secfac.wisc.edu/divcomm/physical/index.htm&#34;&gt;Physical Sciences Division&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;UW-Madison&lt;/a&gt; include the following instructions (see section I-1 on page 11):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Provide a list of the five leading institutions for research (and outreach/extension activities) in the candidate&#39;s discipline. The committee recognizes that the best work in the candidate&#39;s specialty may not be carried out at the top ranked institutions in the broader discipline.  However, it will look for a balance of evaluations from referees at the leading institutions who can evaluate the research and its impact on the broader field, and from the leaders in the subfield if they are at different institutions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use the ranking of a referee&amp;rsquo;s institution as an indication of his/her ability to evaluate the importance of a candidate&amp;rsquo;s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This disgusts me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the analogy of measuring the importance of an academic paper by the &amp;ldquo;impact factor&amp;rdquo; of the journal in which it appeared, with measuring the quality of a researcher by the quality of his/her institution.  I thought the absurdity of the latter would, by association, make plain the absurdity of the former.  I hadn&amp;rsquo;t thought that the absurdity of the latter might be in question.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genetic testing of sperm donors</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/05/16/genetic-testing-of-sperm-donors/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/05/16/genetic-testing-of-sperm-donors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A recent New York Times article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/15/health/in-sperm-banks-a-matrix-of-untested-genetic-diseases.html&#34;&gt;discusses the potential need for genetic screening of sperm donors&lt;/a&gt;. A couple of points struck me as rather odd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One, the mention of fragile X syndrome, has been corrected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
An earlier version of this article erroneously included fragile X syndrome in a list of genetic diseases that have affected children conceived with donated sperm. (Although a sperm donor who is a carrier of the fragile X premutation may pass it along to his daughters, the disease, which affects twice as many boys as girls, is almost always inherited from the mother.)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Sperm donors are no more likely to carry genetic diseases than anybody else, but they can father a far greater number of children: 50, 100 or even 150, each a potential inheritor of flawed genes, and each a vector for making those genes more pervasive in the general population.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the frequency of offspring of sperm donors with genetic diseases would be the same whether there were many more donors with one child each or fewer donors with many children each, and so it&amp;rsquo;s not clear how sperm donors fathering many children is an argument for genetic testing, except that with fewer donors for the same number of offspring, one would not need to perform as many genetic tests, and so there would be a considerable cost savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article led with a story about a couple whose child, fathered by a sperm donor, has cystic fibrosis.  But the chance of that is the same whether or not the sperm came from a donor or in the usual way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boring us to submission</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/05/07/boring-us-to-submission/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/05/07/boring-us-to-submission/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;University of Wisconsin-Madison&lt;/a&gt; has embarked on a big &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hrdesign.wisc.edu&#34;&gt;human resources redesign&lt;/a&gt;.  I think the university administration has devised the ideal strategy to ensure little faculty input in the process: they&amp;rsquo;ve made it so dreadfully dull and full of business speak that we can&amp;rsquo;t bear to read through the material or show up to one of the many &amp;ldquo;engagement sessions&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What reasonable faculty member would seek to attend an &amp;ldquo;engagement session&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there are diagrams like this:
&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/hrd_project_structure-1024x770.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And stuff like this:
&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/hrd_vision.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they talk about market-based blah blah blah, my eyes glaze over and I want to take a nap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a great deal of discussion of this stuff at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.secfac.wisc.edu/senate/index.htm&#34;&gt;faculty senate&lt;/a&gt; meeting today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.education.wisc.edu/ci/faculty/details.asp?id=nfeinstein&#34;&gt;Noah Feinstein&lt;/a&gt; asked an important question: on what evidence are the &lt;a href=&#34;http://hrdesign.wisc.edu/work-team-draft-recommendations&#34;&gt;various recommendations&lt;/a&gt; based?  I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure it involves a lot of exploding pie charts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://eps.education.wisc.edu/faculty/rab.asp&#34;&gt;Sara Goldrick-Rab&lt;/a&gt; made the most interesting point of the meeting: the market doesn&amp;rsquo;t reward good teaching. She has &lt;a href=&#34;http://eduoptimists.blogspot.com/2012/05/faculty-involvement-hr-design-at-uw.html&#34;&gt;much more to say&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://eduoptimists.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;her blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I&amp;rsquo;ve been introduced to &lt;a href=&#34;http://eduoptimists.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;Sara&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt; may be viewed as an early positive outcome of the process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microarrays suck</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/04/25/microarrays-suck/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/04/25/microarrays-suck/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s just that I&amp;rsquo;m stupid and haven&amp;rsquo;t been paying proper attention to &lt;a href=&#34;http://rafalab.jhsph.edu/&#34;&gt;Rafa&amp;rsquo;s work&lt;/a&gt; in the past decade, but microarray data have really been kicking my ass the last few weeks.  Here are a few of the lessons that I&amp;rsquo;ve re-learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lesson-1-what-the-hell-is-that&#34;&gt;Lesson 1: What the hell is that?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many (or all) of my interesting findings have been completely fortuitous results of exploring apparent artifacts in data (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/publications/autozyg.pdf&#34;&gt;autozygosity in the CEPH families&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/publications/inversion.pdf&#34;&gt;a large, common human inversion polymorphism&lt;/a&gt;, and most recently &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biostat.wisc.edu/~kbroman/presentations/enar2012.pdf&#34;&gt;sample mixups&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago, I was working on writing up a paper, and saw an unusual plot, and thought, &amp;ldquo;Hmm, that&amp;rsquo;s interesting,&amp;rdquo; and so I made some more plots.  And then I saw this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/weird_correlation_matrix1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an image of the correlations between samples, across genes, for a study with 500 microarrays on each of 6 tissues.  The samples are sorted by sex (female on bottom left; male on top right) and then by ID.  I was initially puzzling over the sex difference in other tissues (same-sex pairs are positively correlated; opposite-sex pairs are negatively correlated), but when I saw this tissue, I was struck by the plaid pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following up on this, it seems that the plaid pattern is the result of a set of bad arrays that should have been but hadn&amp;rsquo;t been detected before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lesson-2-look&#34;&gt;Lesson 2: Look&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have found this array problem if I hadn&amp;rsquo;t looked.  And in my several years working on this project, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t looked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was overwhelmed by the 500 microarrays × 6 tissues × 40,000 probes, and so didn&amp;rsquo;t make the sorts of plots that I should have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, this is the first real microarray project I&amp;rsquo;ve been involved in, and I haven&amp;rsquo;t known what to look for.  (I should have looked at images of correlation matrices with arrays sorted by similarity as determined from hierarchical clustering.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t make 3000 choose 2 scatterplots, but you can look at summaries of the marginal distributions of the 3000 arrays.  I was thinking about how to depict 500 box plots, and came up with this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/many_boxplots.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are ~500 arrays here, with the lines indicating quantiles: 1, 5, 10, 25, 50, 75, 90, 95, 99%iles.  The first batch of arrays are the bad ones.  You can see that those have a shift upward in median but also a heavy lower tail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quite like the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code is available within my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kbroman/broman&#34;&gt;R/broman&lt;/a&gt; package on &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;, though there&amp;rsquo;s not much to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lesson-3-don-t-trust-anyone&#34;&gt;Lesson 3: Don&amp;rsquo;t trust anyone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t even trust yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I relied on others to do the data cleaning.  I should have checked things more carefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked at the data quite closely a year or so ago and detected sample mix-ups.  In correcting those mistakes, I spent a lot of time looking at the array data and trying to identify bad arrays.  Clearly I didn&amp;rsquo;t look closely enough, or I just looked at the wrong things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lesson-4-take-your-time&#34;&gt;Lesson 4: Take your time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists are under a lot of pressure to produce and often are not exploring data as thoroughly as the data deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you rush through data diagnostics, you could embarrass yourself later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, take the time to follow up on apparent artifacts.  For me, the unintended analyses are more interesting than the planned ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-basic-strategy-for-data-diagnostics&#34;&gt;My basic strategy for data diagnostics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expect errors&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Think about what might have gone wrong and how such problems might be revealed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make lots of specially-tailored plots&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create a (potentially informal) pipeline of all of the useful diagnostics you&amp;rsquo;ve used in the past&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make more plots just because you think they might interesting&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If something looks odd, figure out why&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ENAR 2012</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/04/18/enar-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/04/18/enar-2012/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/meetings.cfm&#34;&gt;ENAR meeting&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enar.org/&#34;&gt;eastern North America portion&lt;/a&gt; of International Biometric Society) was a few weeks ago in Washington, DC. It was great to see &lt;a href=&#34;http://biostat.jhsph.edu&#34;&gt;old friends&lt;/a&gt;, and I learned a number of things outside of the sessions, but mostly I was annoyed by the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ways-to-annoy-me&#34;&gt;Ways to annoy me&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Distorted aspect ratios: I&amp;rsquo;m often seeing LCD projectors set up in wide format, stretching a presentation that was developed in the old 4:3 style. Is it not obvious that preserving the aspect ratio is more important than filling the screen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is especially bad with photographs:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/davidian.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;                 &lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/davidian_stretch.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;* It also makes fonts ugly:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/davidian_slide.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;     &lt;img src=&#34;http://kbroman.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/davidian_slide_stretch.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outlines for talks (especially 15 min talks): If you have only 15 min, don&amp;rsquo;t waste any time telling us what you&amp;rsquo;re going to be telling us; just tell us.  And even if you&amp;rsquo;ve got 45 min, I find the &amp;ldquo;Background, Methods, Simulations, Application, Discussion&amp;rdquo; outline totally useless, and anything more complicated than that seldom makes sense until the speaker is part way through the talk.  Why try to explain terminology before you&amp;rsquo;ve gotten to the background section?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m running out of time so I&amp;rsquo;m going to skip the real data analysis and go quickly through some asymptotic results.&amp;rdquo;  Someone actually said that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Opening night poster session (and for three hours!): It actually seemed to be working, but I sure wouldn&amp;rsquo;t want to be standing next to a poster from 8-11pm.  I would prefer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;posters available to look at throughout the meeting&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;multiple poster sessions (so presenters have some opportunity to talk to each other)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;nothing happening at the time of a poster session&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dull talks by famous people: (I&amp;rsquo;m not talking about &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;, fine reader, but the other famous people.)  Biology meetings will have a few invited speakers but the bulk of the talks will be chosen based on submitted abstracts.  Statistics meetings seem more often arranged to have people submit proposals for full sessions, with a slate of pre-selected speakers, and it is those sessions that are reviewed.  That seems the perfect design if you want crappy talks by famous people.  Perhaps I&amp;rsquo;m annoyed only because I&amp;rsquo;m a non-famous person who can give a good talk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>as.character() for rownames()</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/03/22/as-character-for-rownames/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/03/22/as-character-for-rownames/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/03/21/row-names-in-data-frames-beware-of-1nrow/#comment-330&#34;&gt;Rainer pointed out&lt;/a&gt;, in response to my post, &lt;a href=&#34;http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/03/21/row-names-in-data-frames-beware-of-1nrow/&#34;&gt;Row names in data frames: Beware of 1:nrow&lt;/a&gt;, that if I&amp;rsquo;d used &lt;code&gt;rownames(x) &amp;lt;- as.character(1:3)&lt;/code&gt; rather than &lt;code&gt;rownames(x) &amp;lt;- 1:3&lt;/code&gt;, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have had the problem I&amp;rsquo;d seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; x &amp;lt;- z &amp;lt;- data.frame(id=1:3)
&amp;gt; y &amp;lt;- data.frame(id=4:6)
&amp;gt; rownames(x) &amp;lt;- 1:3
&amp;gt; rownames(y) &amp;lt;- LETTERS[4:6]
&amp;gt; rownames(z) &amp;lt;- as.character(1:3)
&amp;gt; rbind(y,x)
  id
D  1
E  2
F  3
4  1
5  2
6  3
&amp;gt; rbind(y,z)
  id
D  1
E  2
F  3
1  1
2  2
3  3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you type &lt;code&gt;rownames(x)&lt;/code&gt; you see the same result as &lt;code&gt;rownames(z)&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;is.character(rownames(x))&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;is.character(rownames(z))&lt;/code&gt; both return TRUE, but if you look at the &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;row.names&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; attribute directly, you see they are different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; rownames(x)
[1] &amp;quot;1&amp;quot; &amp;quot;2&amp;quot; &amp;quot;3&amp;quot;
&amp;gt; rownames(z)
[1] &amp;quot;1&amp;quot; &amp;quot;2&amp;quot; &amp;quot;3&amp;quot;
&amp;gt; is.character(rownames(x))
[1] TRUE
&amp;gt; is.character(rownames(z))
[1] TRUE
&amp;gt; attr(x, &amp;quot;row.names&amp;quot;)
[1] 1 2 3
&amp;gt; attr(z, &amp;quot;row.names&amp;quot;)
[1] &amp;quot;1&amp;quot; &amp;quot;2&amp;quot; &amp;quot;3&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why is &lt;code&gt;1:3&lt;/code&gt; treated so differently from &lt;code&gt;2:4&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;&amp;gt; w &amp;lt;- data.frame(id=1:3)
&amp;gt; rownames(w) &amp;lt;- 2:4
&amp;gt; attr(w, &amp;quot;row.names&amp;quot;)
[1] 2 3 4
&amp;gt; rownames(rbind(y,w))
[1] &amp;quot;D&amp;quot; &amp;quot;E&amp;quot; &amp;quot;F&amp;quot; &amp;quot;2&amp;quot; &amp;quot;3&amp;quot; &amp;quot;4&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
