<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>D3 on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>/tags/d3/</link>
    <description>Recent content in D3 on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT license</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 May 2017 16:22:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/d3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>updating d3panels and R/qtlcharts for D3 version 4</title>
      <link>/2017/05/11/updating-d3panels-and-r/qtlcharts-for-d3-version-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2017 16:22:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/05/11/updating-d3panels-and-r/qtlcharts-for-d3-version-4/</guid>
      <description>I just spent some time updating my d3panels library and R/qtlcharts package for D3 version 4. It took just about a day, and the majority of the time was spent puzzling over d3-force and d3-brush.
(Note that I just barely know what I&amp;rsquo;m doing, by which I mean I don&amp;rsquo;t know what I&amp;rsquo;m doing. I&amp;rsquo;m able to get things to work, but I don&amp;rsquo;t always know why.)
I was very glad that I&amp;rsquo;d written a bunch of tests, because I could use those to figure out what was working and what was not working, and whether my changes were effective.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MongoDB with D3.js</title>
      <link>/2015/06/22/mongodb-with-d3-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/06/22/mongodb-with-d3-js/</guid>
      <description>I consider interactive data visualization to be the critical tool for exploration of high-dimensional data.
That&amp;rsquo;s led me to spend a good amount of time in the last few years learning some new skills (D3 and CoffeeScript) and developing some new tools, particularly the R package R/qtlcharts, which provides interactive versions of the many data visualizations in R/qtl, my long-in-development R package for mapping genetic loci (called quantitative trait loci, QTL) that underlie complex trait variation in experimental organisms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive plot of car crash stats</title>
      <link>/2014/10/30/interactive-plot-of-car-crash-stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/10/30/interactive-plot-of-car-crash-stats/</guid>
      <description>I spent the afternoon making a D3-based interactive version of the graphs of car crash statistics by state that I&amp;rsquo;d discussed yesterday: my attempt to improve on the graphs in Mona Chalabi&amp;rsquo;s post at 538.

See it in action here.
Code on github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing an R package&#39;s interactive graphs</title>
      <link>/2014/08/01/testing-an-r-packages-interactive-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/08/01/testing-an-r-packages-interactive-graphs/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on an R package, R/qtlcharts, with D3-based interactive graphs for quantitative trait locus mapping experiments.
Testing the interactive charts it produces is a bit of a pain. It seems like I pretty much have to just open a series of examples in a web browser and tab through them manually, checking that they look okay, that the interactions seem to work, and that they&amp;rsquo;re not giving any sort of errors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data structures are important</title>
      <link>/2013/03/19/data-structures-are-important/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/19/data-structures-are-important/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve created another D3 example, of QTL analysis for a phenotype measured over time. (Click on the image for the interactive version.)

The code is on github. It took me about a day.
The hardest part was figuring out the right data structures. A pixel here is linked to curves over there and over there and over there. You need to set things up so it&amp;rsquo;s easy to traverse such linkages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why aren&#39;t all of our graphs interactive?</title>
      <link>/2013/03/16/why-arent-all-of-our-graphs-interactive/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/16/why-arent-all-of-our-graphs-interactive/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve come to believe that, for high-dimensional data, visualizations (aka graphs), and particularly interactive graphs, can be more important than precise statistical inference.
We first need to be able to view and explore the data, and when it is unusually abundant, that is especially hard. This was a primary contributor to my recent embarrassments, in which clear problems in the data were not discovered when they should have been.
I gave a talk on interactive graphs (with the title above) at Johns Hopkins last fall, and then a related talk at ENAR earlier this week, and I have a few thoughts to add here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive eQTL plot with d3.js</title>
      <link>/2013/03/06/interactive-eqtl-plot-with-d3-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/06/interactive-eqtl-plot-with-d3-js/</guid>
      <description>I just finished an interactive eQTL plot using D3, in preparation for my talk on interactive graphics at the ENAR meeting next week.

The code (in CoffeeScript) is available at github. But beware: it&amp;rsquo;s pretty awful.
The hardest part was setting up the data files. Well, that plus the fact that I just barely know what I&amp;rsquo;m doing in D3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;</title>
      <link>/2013/03/02/charsetutf-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/02/charsetutf-8/</guid>
      <description>To use the latest version of D3, you need to use charset=&amp;quot;utf-8&amp;quot; in the call to &amp;lt;script&amp;gt;.
I&amp;rsquo;m giving a talk at ENAR in just over a week, on interactive graphics. My slides (still in preparation) are on the web.
The slides were working fine locally on my laptop, but they weren&amp;rsquo;t working on my web server&amp;hellip;I was getting a syntax error regarding an illegal character.
I figured out that I needed to add charset=&amp;quot;utf-8&amp;quot;, like so:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>D3.js difficulties</title>
      <link>/2013/02/08/d3-js-difficulties/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/08/d3-js-difficulties/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m pleased with my progress learning javascript and D3. (I&amp;rsquo;m actually writing coffeescript rather than javascript.)
But I spent a lot of time thrashing about yesterday, due mostly to two silly errors.
Put the script in the body First, I&amp;rsquo;d tried to make a truly simple example, making just an SVG with a little rectangle.
&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt; &amp;lt;html lang=&amp;#34;en&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;head&amp;gt; &amp;lt;meta charset=&amp;#34;utf-8&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Put script in body&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt; &amp;lt;script type=&amp;#34;text/javascript&amp;#34; src=&amp;#34;http://d3js.org/d3.v3.min.js&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt; &amp;lt;script type=&amp;#34;text/javascript&amp;#34;&amp;gt; var h=50; var svg = d3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive graphics with d3.js</title>
      <link>/2013/02/08/interactive-graphics-with-d3-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/08/interactive-graphics-with-d3-js/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m making some progress learning D3 (for interactive graphics), by which I mean I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten a couple of examples to work.
Many box plots First, an example for displaying many distributions. Here I&amp;rsquo;m considering a set of nearly 500 gene expression microarrays, each with 40,000 or so measurements. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to look at 500 box plots side-by-side, and with 40k measurements, traditional box plots don&amp;rsquo;t give enough information about the tails.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
