<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Computing on the stupidest thing...</title>
    <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/tags/computing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Computing on the stupidest thing...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>The text in this work is licensed under CC-BY-4.0, https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode; code licensed under the MIT License</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://kbroman.org/blog/tags/computing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Startling lack of training in statistical computing</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/03/14/startling-lack-of-training-in-statistical-computing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/03/14/startling-lack-of-training-in-statistical-computing/</guid>
      <description>It is shocking to me that a statistics department would offer a graduate-level statistical computing course only every fourth year.
I had been arguing for a statistical programming course: that we supplement the usual course on the theory of statistical computing (numerical linear algebra, EM algorithm, MCMC, etc.) with a course on the practice of statistical computing.
But I was assuming that the more theoretical statistical computing course was actually being taught.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Googling errors</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/02/14/googling-errors/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2014/02/14/googling-errors/</guid>
      <description>@roguelynn tweeted the other day:
If attendees of this weekend’s intro to python workshop leave with one thing, it’ll be to Google your error messages first and foremost.
&amp;mdash; __root__ (@roguelynn) February 6, 2014  I had just talked about the technique in my Tools for Reproducible Research course, and I had a few recent examples.
Gtk-WARNING **: cannot open display: I was logged into a department server, trying to clone a private repository from GitHub, and got an error like</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A course in statistical programming</title>
      <link>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/05/25/a-course-in-statistical-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kbroman.org/blog/2012/05/25/a-course-in-statistical-programming/</guid>
      <description>Graduate students in statistics often take (or at least have the opportunity to take) a statistical computing course, but often such courses are focused on methods (like numerical linear algebra, the EM algorithm, and MCMC) and not on actual coding.
For example, here&amp;rsquo;s a course in &amp;ldquo;advanced statistical computing&amp;rdquo; that I taught at Johns Hopkins back in 2001.
Many (perhaps most) good programmers learned to code outside of formal courses. But many statisticians are terrible programmers and would benefit by a formal course.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>